<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    

    <title>Quick & Tasty - Get Cooking!</title>
    <generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
		<icon>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/apple-touch-icon-precomposed.png</icon>
    <subtitle>Quick and Tasty</subtitle>
    <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2016-04-23T14:54:37+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</id>
    <author>
			<name>Wim Vanderbauwhede</name>
			<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
			<email>wimvanderbauwhede@yahoo.co.uk</email>
		</author>

    
    <entry>
        <title>The most underrated kitchen appliance</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/microwave-cooking/"/>
        <updated>2016-04-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/microwave-cooking</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim Vanderbauwhede</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					<email>wimvanderbauwhede@yahoo.co.uk</email>
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/microwave_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;!-- &quot;The most underrated kitchen appliance&quot; --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The microwave oven is probably the most common appliance in any kitchen, but also the most underrated one. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people use the microwave oven to heat ready meals or defrost food, but don’t see it as an appliance for cooking proper food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is really a shame as cooking food in the microwave has many advantages: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tasty&lt;/em&gt;: food cooked in the microwave retains its natural taste and texture.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Quick&lt;/em&gt;: generally microwave cooking needs shorter cooking times than other cooking methods.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Healthy&lt;/em&gt;: most food retains &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; nutrients and vitamins when cooked in the microwave, as explained by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.health.harvard.edu/staying-healthy/microwave-cooking-and-nutrition&quot;&gt; (see also e.g. [&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&quot;#ref3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&quot;#ref4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&quot;#ref5&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;]).&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eco&lt;/em&gt;: cooking in the microwave is generally more energy-efficient than cooking using a conventional oven or hob: according to a DEFRA study from 2008 &lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, overall, the microwave oven has the lowest greenhouse gas emissions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Versatile&lt;/em&gt;: you have very accurate control over the heating level and cooking time. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Less messy&lt;/em&gt;: cooking in the microwave requires no fat and the food doesn’t stick to the pot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So give the microwave a try for cooking food. It’s really easy. If you’re unsure, have a look at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/&quot;&gt;my recipes&lt;/a&gt;. I use the microwave in all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;ref1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://randd.defra.gov.uk/Document.aspx?Document=FO0409_8192_FRP.pdf&quot;&gt;Understanding the greenhouse gas (GHG) impacts of food preparation and consumption in the home&lt;/a&gt;  DEFRA Research Project Final Report FO 0409&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;ref2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0963996913001385&quot;&gt;Microwave food processing—A review&lt;/a&gt; S. Chandrasekaran, S. Ramanathan, Tanmay Basak, &lt;em&gt;Food Research International Volume 52, Issue 1, June 2013, Pages 243–261&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;ref3&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0889157506000561&quot;&gt;Nutritional composition of chickpea as affected by microwave cooking and other traditional cooking methods&lt;/a&gt; Saleh A. Alajaji, Tarek A. El-Adawy, &lt;em&gt;Journal of Food Composition and Analysis Volume 19, Issue 8, December 2006, Pages 806–812&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;ref1&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;Anne Lassen, Lars Ovesen, Nutrition &amp;amp; Food Science, Vol. 95 Iss: 4, pp.8 - 10, 1995 http://www.emeraldinsight.com/doi/abs/10.1108/00346659510088654 &quot;&gt;Nutritional effects of microwave cooking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;ref4&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0260877405004462&quot;&gt;Impact of different cooking methods on food quality: Retention of lipophilic vitamins in fresh and frozen vegetables&lt;/a&gt; Simone Bernhardt, Elmar Schlich, &lt;em&gt;Journal of Food Engineering Volume 77, Issue 2, November 2006, Pages 327–333&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!--

http://www.youmeusdesign.com/casestudies/124_002_02/
 --&gt;


        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>The Zen way of cooking</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/zen-cooking/"/>
        <updated>2016-04-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/zen-cooking</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim Vanderbauwhede</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					<email>wimvanderbauwhede@yahoo.co.uk</email>
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/zencookbook_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;There is a famous Zen poem about the right way to make tea (“cha no yu”), and it translates loosely as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--
茶の湯とは、
ただ湯を沸かし
茶を点てて、
飲むばかり
なる本を知るべし
--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To make tea, just boil water, make tea, then you drink it properly.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Zen way of cooking is somewhat similar. Japanese Zen Buddhism has a long tradition of what is called “temple cuisine”, a refined and essentially vegan way of cooking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was living in Japan, near Kyoto, there was a Zen temple close by, the beautiful Manpukuji.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/manpukuji-1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/manpukuji-2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the shop of the Manpukuji temple I bought this cookbook (in Japanese only) about “fucha ryori” (Zen temple cuisine):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/zencookbook.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;sample image&quot; title=&quot;Zen temple cookbook&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is full of delicious-looking pictures of the recipes, like this one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/zencookbook_page.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;sample image&quot; title=&quot;Page from the zen temple cookbook&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is very different from a regular cookbook is the way the recipes are described: typically, there is a list of ingredients but no amounts, and the method of cooking is described but usually no cooking times are given. Clearly, these details are not the essence of Zen cooking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, for every recipe the book mentions if it is for spring, summer, autumn or winter. This connection with the seasons is of great importance in Japan. Also, the the recipes give detailed instructions  related to the way the prepared food looks. The aesthetic aspect is as important as the taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So maybe we can express the Zen way of cooking like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;普茶料理とはただ材料を選び食を作って盛るばかりなる本を知るべし&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To cook the Zen way, just take the right ingredients, prepare the food, then serve it properly.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>The 3 great virtues of a cook: laziness, impatience and hubris</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/three-virtues/"/>
        <updated>2016-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/three-virtues</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim Vanderbauwhede</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					<email>wimvanderbauwhede@yahoo.co.uk</email>
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/shiitake_shichimi_wakame_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;Some of the qualities of a geek boffin are transferable to cooking.&lt;a name=&quot;homepage_banner&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;laziness&quot;&gt;Laziness&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quality that makes you go to great effort to reduce overall energy expenditure. It makes you create recipes that are easy to make with ingredients that are easy to find. Hence, the first great virtue of a cook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impatience&quot;&gt;Impatience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not wanting to spend ages preparing food. This makes you create recipes that are quick to prepare and quick to cook, with minimal cleaning-up. Hence, the second great virtue of a cook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hubris&quot;&gt;Hubris&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quality that makes you create tasty recipes that the whole world will want to cook. Hence, the third great virtue of a cook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This post is inspired by Larry Wall’s views on the virtues of a programmer in “Programming Perl” (2nd ed.) by Tom Christiansen, Randal L. Schwartz, Larry Wall published by O’Reilly, 1996&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>7 tips for making quick &amp; tasty meals</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/seven-tips/"/>
        <updated>2016-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/seven-tips</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim Vanderbauwhede</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					<email>wimvanderbauwhede@yahoo.co.uk</email>
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/dried_tomatoes_bold_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;With these tips, making tasty meals will be a breeze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;build-a-core-set-of-recipesa-namehomepagebannera&quot;&gt;Build a core set of recipes&lt;a name=&quot;homepage_banner&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make a quick meal it is important that you don’t have to think about it. By having a set of ten to twenty favourite recipes, you can quickly make what you like and have a wide variety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-fresh-vegetables-for-taste&quot;&gt;Use fresh vegetables for taste&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is really essential to use fresh vegetables in a meal. Vegetables make the meal balanced; fresh vegetables simply taste so much better than the ones in tins or jars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dont-overcook&quot;&gt;Don’t overcook&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may sound totally obvious, but cook the food for the shortest possible time. Many vegetables don’t need to be cooked at all. All you want is that they are hot and maybe slightly softened. They will taste at their best too. Overcooking your food takes longer and destroys the taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;add-umami&quot;&gt;Add &lt;em&gt;umami&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Umami&lt;/em&gt; is a loanword from the Japanese which can be translated as “pleasant savory taste”, and it is one of the five basic tastes. Even after adding spices, nuts, etc., you may find the food is still not “tasty” enough. That means you need to add some umami. Ingredients that contain a lot of umami are dried tomatoes, dried mushrooms, hard cheese, miso, soy sauce, seaweed, garlic, and also beans (in particular fresh soy beans).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;think-about-texture&quot;&gt;Think about texture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We appreciate food through more than the taste and smell. The way food feels when you eat it — smooth, crunchy, etc. — is equally important. Vegetables are great for texture, this is another reason not to overcook them. For extra crunch you can add seeds or nuts, for more “bite” dried mushrooms are great, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;make-a-one-pot-meal&quot;&gt;Make a one-pot meal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the difficulty with cooking is having to multitask with several pots on the hob. Making a one-pot main meal is much simpler and quicker, because you have only one thing to attend to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-the-microwave&quot;&gt;Use the microwave&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The microwave oven is much underrated for cooking. It has the advantages of preparing food quickly, preserving more of the nutrients, and it is hassle-free: you don’t have to watch it and there is less cleaning-up afterwards too.&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Why quick and tasty cooking</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/welcome/"/>
        <updated>2016-01-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/welcome</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim Vanderbauwhede</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					<email>wimvanderbauwhede@yahoo.co.uk</email>
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/homepage_banner_1600_2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;My aim with Quick and Tasty Cooking is to get more people to cook healthy food and ultimately to write a cookbook and donate the proceeds to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wfp.org/&quot;&gt;UN World Food Programme&lt;/a&gt;. For a publisher to take interest, I need to have many, many followers on Facebook and Twitter. Please help me to achieve this goal by liking my Facebook page or following me on Twitter:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inline-btn&quot;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/fuss_free_food&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-twitter&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pinterest.com/fussfreefood&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-pinterest&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;	
	&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/quickandtasyfood/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-facebook&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&amp;nbsp;
&lt;div class=&quot;fb-like&quot; data-href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/quickandtasyfood/&quot; data-layout=&quot;button&quot; data-action=&quot;like&quot; data-show-faces=&quot;false&quot; data-share=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- /.follow-us --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My recipes are quick (really) and easy, don’t require any gadgets and use few ingredients — all of which you can find in the supermarket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All recipes are my own creation, unless credited. I’ll post a new quick &amp;amp; tasty recipe every week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wim&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>