<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title>Quick &amp; Tasty</title>
    <generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll v4.3.3</generator>
		<icon>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/apple-touch-icon-precomposed.avif</icon>
    <subtitle>Quick and Tasty</subtitle>
    <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2024-02-09T11:12:03+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</id>
    <author>
			<name>Wim</name>
			<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
			
		</author>

    
    <entry>
        <title>The age of bloom</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/in-the-mood-for-love/"/>
        <updated>2024-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/in-the-mood-for-love</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/in-the-mood-for-love_1600x600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;One of my favourite movies is Wong Kar-Wai’s movie “In the mood for love”, from 2000. It’s set in Hong Kong in the early 1960s, almost all scenes are at night and it rains a lot. It’s a tale of love and unfaithfulness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bfidatadigipres.github.io/sight%20and%20sound%20greatest%20films%20of%20all%20time%202022%3Cbr%3E5=/2023/03/06/in-the-mood-for-love/&quot;&gt;Wong Kar-Wai says&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Is it basically a love story about these two characters? Finally I think it’s more than that. It’s about the end of a period. 1966 marks a turning point in Hong Kong’s history. The Cultural Revolution in the mainland had lots of knock-on effects, and forced Hong Kong people to think hard about their future. Many of them had come from China in the late 40s, they’d had nearly 20 years of relative tranquillity, they’d built themselves new lives – and suddenly they began to feel they’d have to move on again. So 1966 is the end of something and the beginning of something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot has been written about this movie, reviews, essays, in -depth analysis of what makes it so special. I want to talk about a novel a and a song that are closely tied to the movie. And about the drawings of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-novel&quot;&gt;A novel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The movie has intertitles at the start and the end:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is a restless moment.
She has kept her head lowered,
to give him a chance to come closer.
But he could not, for lack of courage.
She turns and walks away.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;That era has passed.
He remembers those vanished years.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Nothing that belonged to it exists any more.
As though looking through a dusty window pane,
The past is something he could see, but not touch.
And everything he sees is blurred and indistinct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is adapted from novella “Duidao”  (“Intersection”) by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liu_Yichang&quot;&gt;Liu Yichang&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://bfidatadigipres.github.io/sight%20and%20sound%20greatest%20films%20of%20all%20time%202022%3Cbr%3E5=/2023/03/06/in-the-mood-for-love/&quot;&gt;Wong Kar-Wai says&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The first work by Liu Yichang I read was Duidao. The title is a Chinese translation of tête-bêche, which describes stamps that are printed top to bottom facing each other.
Duidao centres round the intersection of two parallel stories – of an old man and a young girl. One is about memories, the other anticipation. To me, tête-bêche is more than a term for stamps or intersection of stories. It can be the intersection of light and colour, silence and tears. Tête-bêche can also be the intersection of time: for instance, youthful eyes on an ageing face, borrowed words on revisited dreams. Or a novel published in 1972, a movie released in 2000, both intersecting to become a story of the ’60s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her essay &lt;a href=&quot;https://minerva-access.unimelb.edu.au/handle/11343/34511&quot;&gt;“In The Mood for love: intersections of Hong Kong modernity”&lt;/a&gt;, Audrey Yue summarises the novel as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Set in 1970s Hong Kong, Duidao tells the parallel stories of Chunyu Bai, an old reporter from Shanghai who fled to Hong Kong in the 1940s to escape the Japanese Occupation, and Ah Xing, a young single woman who lives with her parents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bai is nostalgic, fuelled by his memories of Shanghai, his youthful liaisons with dancehall girls and his failed marriage. Ah Xing is forward-looking. Always day-dreaming about herself as a famous singer or a movie star, she longs to find love and marry a handsome husband, someone ‘a bit like Ke Junxiong, a bit like Deng Guangrong, a bit like Bruce Lee, and a bit like Alain Delon’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Triggered by songs, old photographs, and magazine covers and posters of movie stars, the two characters’ temporalities are retrospective and projective. In the story, they only meet once sitting next to each other in a crowded cinema.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Everyday practices like walking, commuting, listening to music, watching television and going to the movies highlight their close encounters. These practices construct Hong Kong, already a Chinese migrant enclave and a metropolis dizzy with escalating property prices and swirling in the popular media mix of Taiwanese Mandarin pop songs, Filipino renditions of American Top Ten hits, Hollywood cinema and French film icons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-song&quot;&gt;A song&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title of the movie, 花樣年華, &lt;em&gt;Fa Yeung Nin Wa&lt;/em&gt; in Cantonese transliteration, is taken form a 1940s song &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tR1FCe5XKUo&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hua Yang De Nian Hua&lt;/em&gt; (花樣的年華) “Age of Bloom” by famous 1940s  singer Zhou Xuan&lt;/a&gt;. It is this song that Mr. Chan, on business Japan, requests to be played for his wife’s birthday. It’s a melancholy song talking about a happy past that is no longer, and it can also easily be interpreted as a reference to the Japanese occupation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The song was released after the war, in 1947, as part of  the movie “Sauvignon Blanc”. But there is a reference to a solitary island, and a period of gloom and yearning for the homeland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The period between the start of the Battle of Shanghai in August of 1937 and the outbreak of the Pacific War in late 1941 is known as the Solitary Island Period. During this time, the International Settlement and French Concession in Shanghai were not occupied by the Japanese but the rest of the city was occupied. The film makers who remained worked in these foreign concessions. There is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sixthtone.com/news/1006639&quot;&gt;an interesting article about Zhou Xuan&lt;/a&gt; that provides more context about the Shanghai movie scene in the 1930s and 1940s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The writer of the song, Fan Yanqiao, worked for one of those film companies. Likely he used his recollection of that time as inspiration. (He also wrote the original script for “Sauvignon Blanc”, called “Flowers Bloom In Streets”.) The composer of the song is &lt;a href=&quot;https://nspirement.com/2021/11/28/singing-star-chen-gexin.html&quot;&gt;Chen Gexin&lt;/a&gt;, under the pseudonym Lin Mei. He wrote this song in Hong-Kong during a brief happy period in his life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wong Kar-Wai also made &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GCMz1EGIe0&quot;&gt;a short film, named Hua Yang De Nian Hua&lt;/a&gt;, after the track, consisting of short scenes of movies of that era, with the song as soundtrack. Clearly he considered the song and its background important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tumblr.com/sibeliusxx/641304841794240512/age-of-bloom&quot;&gt;this translation of the song’s lyrics&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Age of bloom, spirits like the Moon&lt;br /&gt;
A crystal mind like ice and snow&lt;br /&gt;
Such a beautiful life, such an adoring couple&lt;br /&gt;
A family so whole and complete&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Suddenly this lone-standing island,&lt;br /&gt;
Is covered by shattered mist and sorrowful rain&lt;br /&gt;
Shattered mist and sorrowful rain&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ah, my beloved homeland&lt;br /&gt;
When can I return to your warm embrace?&lt;br /&gt;
When will the mist and cloud be dispelled&lt;br /&gt;
And release your fogged light? &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Age of bloom, spirits like the Moon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meimeimusic.org/blog/0011&quot;&gt;another one&lt;/a&gt;, with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c9C7tSSxwWQ&quot;&gt;a contemporary performance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are young, like blooming flowers&lt;br /&gt;
We are fresh, like the shining moon&lt;br /&gt;
We are sharp, like ice and snow.&lt;br /&gt;
We have a beautiful life, tender lovers and happy families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But suddenly this lonely island is shrouded in a miserable foggy gloom. A miserable foggy gloom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ah! My dear motherland, when can we return to your arms?&lt;br /&gt;
When will the dark clouds and fog disperse? &lt;br /&gt;
When will we see the light again?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are young, like blooming flowers&lt;br /&gt;
We are fresh, like the shining moon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original lyrics in traditional characters (as were used at the time of its release):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    花樣的年華&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    主唱：周璇&lt;br /&gt;
    作詞：范煙橋　作曲：林枚&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    花樣的年華，月樣的精神，&lt;br /&gt;
    冰雪樣的聰明。&lt;br /&gt;
    美麗的生活，多情的眷屬，&lt;br /&gt;
    圓滿的家庭。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    驀地裡這孤島籠罩著&lt;br /&gt;
    慘霧愁雲，慘霧愁雲。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    啊！可愛的祖國 &lt;br /&gt;
    幾時我能夠投進你的懷抱，&lt;br /&gt;
    能見那霧消雲散，重見你放出光明。&lt;br /&gt;
    花樣的年華，月樣的精神。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and the transcription:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hua yang de nianhua yue yang de jingshen&lt;br /&gt;
Bingxue yang de congming&lt;br /&gt;
Meili de shenghuo duoqing de juanshu&lt;br /&gt;
Yuanman de jiating&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mo di li zhe gudao longzhao zhe &lt;br /&gt;
Can wu chou yu, can wu chou yu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A ke ai de zu guo&lt;br /&gt;
Ji shi wo nenggou kaojin ni de huaibao&lt;br /&gt;
Neng jian na wu xiao yun san&lt;br /&gt;
Chong jian ni fang chu guangming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hua yang de nianhua yue yang de jingshen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-drawings&quot;&gt;The drawings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made two drawings from scenes of the movie, a smaller one in Chinese in and a larger one in Conté pencils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-stair-scene&quot;&gt;The stair scene&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made a drawing of what is probably my favourite scene in Wong Kar-Wai’s movie “In the mood for love”. The protagonists, Su Li-zhen (“Mrs. Chan”) played by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maggie_Cheung&quot;&gt;Maggie Cheung Man-yuk&lt;/a&gt; and Chow Mo-wan played (“Mr. Chow”) by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Leung_Chiu-wai&quot;&gt;Tony Leung Chiu-wai&lt;/a&gt;, pass each other by on a dark, narrow staircase. They steal a glance at each other and the scene is very evocative. All the time I was working on it,  Shigeru Umebayashi’s beautiful music “Yumeji’s Theme”, which accompanies the scene, was playing in my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the drawing on Schoellershammer watercolour paper, 30x40 cm, 250g/m², with [the Chinese ink I wrote about a while ago]https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/inkstick-history/}, and two Chinese brushes. The ink is excellent but the paper and the brushes are not great. As a result, there is a lack of control that I find interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;picture&gt;
&lt;source height=&quot;600&quot; srcset=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/in-the-mood-for-love-stairs.avif&quot; type=&quot;image/avif&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/in-the-mood-for-love-stairs.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A dark, narrow staircase between two walls, poorly lit by a single bare bulb. A woman in a cheongsam dress is ascending with a kettle in on hand, her other hand trailing against the wall. Her profile throws a black, distorted shadow on the wall. A man in a dark suit is descending. When they meet, they steal a glance at one another.&quot; title=&quot;A dark, narrow staircase between two walls, poorly lit by a single bare bulb. A woman in a cheongsam dress is ascending with a kettle in on hand, her other hand trailing against the wall. Her profile throws a black, distorted shadow on the wall. A man in a dark suit is descending. When they meet, they steal a glance at one another.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The drawing of the stairs scene&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-taxi-scene&quot;&gt;The taxi scene&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another, the couple is together in a taxi, after Mr. Chow has told Mrs. Chan of his intention to move to Singapore. I think the expressions on their faces are very evocative of their complex feelings. 
It’s just before we hear Mrs. Chan’s off-screen voice saying, “I don’t want to go home tonight.” That’s the scene I wanted to draw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to create a double portrait of this couple who are, &lt;a href=&quot;https://bfidatadigipres.github.io/sight%20and%20sound%20greatest%20films%20of%20all%20time%202022%3Cbr%3E5=/2023/03/06/in-the-mood-for-love/&quot;&gt;as a BFI critic put it&lt;/a&gt; “ordinary mortals made movie-star beautiful by love”, and I stayed very close to the original shot, apart from cropping it to get both faces in an optimal position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used my preferred rough watercolour paper (Fabriano Artistico, 300 gsm, NOT), about 50 cm x 70 cm. I set up the drawing in ordinary pencil and then added tone with Conté pencils (from HB to 3B). Because the paper has such a rough grain, the pencils can’t fill the hollows in it, and I took care not to smudge the strokes. The effect is therefore not a deep, intense black but something more pointillist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;picture&gt;
&lt;source height=&quot;600&quot; srcset=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/in-the-mood-for-love-taxi.avif&quot; type=&quot;image/avif&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/in-the-mood-for-love-taxi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A black and white pencil drawing of a young Kantonese couple sitting in a taxi. She has her head on his shoulder. Their heads throw strong shadows on the pale ceiling. He is wearing a dark suit, she a qipao. Through the rear window, many points of light are visible.&quot; title=&quot;A black and white pencil drawing of a young Kantonese couple sitting in a taxi. She has her head on his shoulder. Their heads throw strong shadows on the pale ceiling. He is wearing a dark suit, she a qipao. Through the rear window, many points of light are visible.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The drawing of the taxi scene&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The banner is a crop of the still on which the drawing is based.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>The small mystery of the Chinese inkstick</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/inkstick-history/"/>
        <updated>2023-06-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/inkstick-history</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/inkstick-history_1600x600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;I would like to tell a little story. I have always liked drawing, and sometimes I use ink and brush. 
Long ago and far away, in a country over the sea, a fellow PhD student from China made me present of an inkstone. It came in a box with a damasked cloth sleeve which opened like a book. The box itself was covered in bright cerulean fabric and inside it, the stone was cushioned in pink silk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is not of the box that I want to talk, beautiful though it is, nor of the stone itself; nor do I want to talk about the inkstick that was enclosed in that same box. It was decorated with a picture of a bird of paradise on a tree with blossoms, all in gold, and it was so pretty I never could bring myself to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with the box came also three additional inksticks, each in its unassuming but stylish cloth-covered small cardboard box, with a white paper label covered in Chinese characters pasted on the top. I couldn’t read them then, and I did not pay much attention; but I noticed that, though the characters where the same on each label, the labels where nonetheless individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These inksticks are also very pretty, with a rustic river scene on one side and calligraphy on the other. But more on that later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, I was making a brush drawing using one of these inksticks, and I happened to look a bit closer at the other markings. On the top it says “油煙一〇一” and on the narrow side “上海墨廠出品”. That means “lampblack 101” and “made by the Shanghai Ink Factory”. I wanted to know more about the meaning of the “101”. And thereby hangs a tale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-history&quot;&gt;The history&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the start of the Qing dynasty (1636), there lived in Shè Xiàn, Ānhuī province, a master ink maker and artist called Cao Sugong 曹素功 (1615–1689).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the sixth year of the reign of the Kangxi Emperor (1667), he founded the Cao Sugong Ink Factory. Two hundred years later — yet still in the Qing dynasty, in the third year of the reign of the Tongzhi Emperor (1864) — the business moved to Shanghai. It gained a high reputation for the excellence of its ink and won numerous international prizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cao Sugong factory produced four grades of ink: 五石漆烟, 超貢烟, 貢烟, 頂烟, meaning “five minerals (wǔshí) lacquer soot”, “super tribute soot”, “tribute soot”, “top soot”. The grade 五石漆烟 marked the highest quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in 1966, at the start of the Cultural Revolution, one of the most notorious campaigns was the Four Old Things campaign. The Four Old Things were: Old Ideas, Old Culture, Old Customs, and Old Habits (&lt;em&gt;jiù sīxiǎng&lt;/em&gt; 旧思想, &lt;em&gt;jiù wénhuà&lt;/em&gt; 旧文化, &lt;em&gt;jiù fēngsú&lt;/em&gt; 旧风俗, and &lt;em&gt;jiù xíguàn&lt;/em&gt; 旧习惯). Characters like “貢” (tribute), with their feudal associations, became unacceptable, and so the grades were renamed to lampblack 101, 102, 103 and 104. In Chinese, lampblack 101 is written “油煙一〇一”, the marking on the top of my inkstick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the Cao Sugong company was combined with several other ink factories and became the “Shanghai Ink Factory”, “上海墨廠”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Cultural Revolution, in the 1980s, the Shanghai Ink Factory changed its name back to “Cao Sugong” and the use of the old grades was also reinstated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got these inksticks in 1992, long after this change back to the old the branding and grading. That means that they were then probably already quite rare items, as the factory only operated as Shanghai Ink Factory for about 20 years in its long and illustrious history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know for how long these stick were out of production. However, today there are again inksticks sold that look exactly like mine, also labelled “油煙一〇一” (lampblack 101) and “上海墨廠出品” (made by the Shanghai Ink Factory), and these are high-quality items, used by professional ink artists. Like the ones I have, they are not intended for export.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These new “101” inksticks are made by the current incarnation of Cao Sugong, after its fusion with famous brush maker Zhou Huchen 周虎臣. Clearly, this particular product has a very high reputation in China, which makes it worthwhile for the company to produce it again, with the original grading and branding from the Shanghai Ink Factory era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-making&quot;&gt;The making&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did I mention that, when you grind this ink on the inkstone, it produces a very pleasant smell?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making an inkstick requires several steps: the lampblack is refined, mixed with glue and other ingredients. 
To improve the fragrance, lustre and insect resistance of the inksticks, more than 20 kinds of Chinese medicinal herbs are added, along with gold leaf. The ingredients are mixed by pounding the ingredients with an eight-pound hammer and is very tiring work. Lu Jianqing, the now-retired director of Cao Sugong recalls how, as an apprentice, having to do this thousands of times a day, he couldn’t lift his hand the next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are then kneaded by hand, and finally pressed into a wooden mold. This mold is carved with a picture on one side and a related piece of calligraphy on the other. The stick is dried, gold leaf is applied and the decorations are painted on. The process requires four kinds of artists: the ink maker, the carver, the calligrapher and the painter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cao Sugong inksticks come in three standardised weights: 1 &lt;em&gt;liang&lt;/em&gt; (31 g), like the ones I have; 2 &lt;em&gt;liang&lt;/em&gt; and 4 &lt;em&gt;liang&lt;/em&gt;. The small sticks need to be dried in the shade for six to eight months; the largest ones require up to two years of drying. During the drying period, they need to turned by hand every day because otherwise they would bend out of shape. The whole process is still very artisanal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-poetry&quot;&gt;The poetry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The picture on my inkstick shows a bucolic scene along a river.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/inkstick-artwork.avif&quot; alt=&quot;An inkstick resting on a beautiful damasked box. On it, a picture in gold, silver and cream, of a child sitting, with a coolie hat on its back, holding a blue rope tied to the horn of a water buffalo. Only the head of the buffalo is visible, the rest is under water. Two ducks swim next to it.&quot; title=&quot;An inkstick resting on a beautiful damasked box. On it, a picture in gold, silver and cream, of a child sitting, with a coolie hat on its back, holding a blue rope tied to the horn of a water buffalo. Only the head of the buffalo is visible, the rest is under water. Two ducks swim next to it.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The artwork on the inkstick&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also has some beautiful calligraphy. I have always been fascinated by Chinese characters, and one day I hope to study Chinese. Not that it would help me with this text, as it is in ancient Chinese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/inkstick-calligraphy.avif&quot; alt=&quot;An inkstick resting on a beautiful damasked box. On it, calligraphy in gold&quot; title=&quot;An inkstick resting on a beautiful damasked box. On it, calligraphy in gold&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The calligraphy on the inkstick&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The characters read&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;水光春色滿江天&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, I could not find a proper translation, but based on a literal reading of the characters, I interpreted it as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;river and sky, full of spring colours, light on the water&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first line of the poem “江南行”, which means “South across the river”. The poem was written during the Tang dynasty (around 831 CE) by the poet Chen Biao (陈标, or 陳票 in traditional characters). Only twelve of his poems are known to exist, but he must once have been a famous poet, as some of his poems are included in the “Shinpenshū”, a collection of poems compiled by the monks of the Kennin-ji temple in Kyoto in the 15th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, he is not well-known at all, which makes the choice of the poem on the inkstick intriguing. It is likely the influence of the artists and calligraphers of the “Chinese Painting Research Academy” (中国画研究院), created in 1981, who worked closely with the Shanghai Ink Factory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the poem in full (in traditional characters):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;水光春色滿江天，蘋葉風吹荷葉錢。&lt;br /&gt;
香蟻翠旗臨岸市，艷娥紅袖渡江船。&lt;br /&gt;
曉驚白鷺聯翩雪，浪蹙青茭瀲灩煙。&lt;br /&gt;
不怕江洲芳草暮，待將秋興折湖蓮。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fediverse.to/&quot;&gt;Fediverse&lt;/a&gt; if anyone could provide a translation, and the inimitable &lt;a href=&quot;https://rage.love/@ljwrites&quot;&gt;L.J.&lt;/a&gt; rose to the challenge to produce the following amazing poem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;South Across the River&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The water-light and hues of spring&lt;br /&gt;
lap up to vaulting blue&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;While winds brush lily pads weighed down&lt;br /&gt;
with drops like coins aglow.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Blue flags and toxicating dregs&lt;br /&gt;
descend on city shore&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Such luscious sweetness clad in red&lt;br /&gt;
across the river rowed.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Egrets affrighted by the dawn&lt;br /&gt;
flock on and on like snow&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The rolling waves and fodder green&lt;br /&gt;
like swelling smoke o’erflow.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Be not afraid that virtue high&lt;br /&gt;
will quite desert Jiangzhou&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Await the autumn days when we&lt;br /&gt;
will pluck the lotus blow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Translation by &lt;a href=&quot;http://ljwrites.blog/about/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;L. J. Lee&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with suggestions from &lt;a href=&quot;https://deadinsi.de/@zoec&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Zoë Camille&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://icosahedron.website/@cxli&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;cynth&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on that wonderfully poetic note I conclude my story of the inksticks from the Shanghai Ink Factory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-background&quot;&gt;The background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This little story is a patchwork pieced together from a large number of sources brought up by a deep trawl through the net. Here are the most interesting of them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My starting point was the blog of an ink shop in Osaka (in Japanese), which has an article on &lt;a href=&quot;http://diary.sousokou.jp/?eid=319&quot;&gt;the 101 grade&lt;/a&gt; and on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://diary.sousokou.jp/?eid=11&quot;&gt;history of the Shanghai Ink Factory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I found an articles about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tour-beijing.com/china_travel_guide/shanghai_culture/shanghai_time_honored_brand/cao_sugong_ink_store/&quot;&gt;history of the Cao Sugong ink shop&lt;/a&gt; and about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.shine.cn/feature/art-culture/2006120056/&quot;&gt;the making of the inksticks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TkcXTyAGBW4&quot;&gt;a video on Youtube&lt;/a&gt;, with English subtitles, about the way inksticks are made at Cao Sugong. The person in the video, Lu Jianqing, started working at the company in 1978 as an apprentice, and became the director in 1989, so he might very well have been involved in the making of my inksticks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is also an &lt;a href=&quot;https://yannotebook.wordpress.com/2016/09/18/making-chinese-inksticks/&quot;&gt;article with great pictures about a different ink factory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://item.jd.com/1364112170.html&quot;&gt;site selling copies of my inkstick&lt;/a&gt;, there is a nice promo video.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This site has the &lt;a href=&quot;http://m.shangshiwen.com/40398.html&quot;&gt;full text of the poem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Sweet red bean paste on toast</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/anko-toast/"/>
        <updated>2023-04-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/anko-toast</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/anko-toast_1600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;This is a quick variant of the traditional Japanese red bean paste &lt;em&gt;anko&lt;/em&gt; (餡子). One way of serving it is on toast with whipped cream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proper way to make &lt;em&gt;anko&lt;/em&gt; is beautifully shown in the movie &lt;a href=&quot;https://cinemaforall.org.uk/films_type/sweet-bean/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;An&lt;/em&gt; (Sweet Bean)&lt;/a&gt;; there is a good recipe &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.justonecookbook.com/how-to-make-anko-red-bean-paste/&quot;&gt;on JustOneCookbook&lt;/a&gt;. It is similar to making jam. My recipe is much quicker and still delicious. I used blueberry syrup because that’s what I had going, but any sugar syrup will work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegetarian&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegetarian&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#45-minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;45-minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;500 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#400-600kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_2.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two slices of toast:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6 tablespoons of tinned of adzuki beans (about 200 g)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons of sugar syrup (mine is 90 g sugar per 100 ml)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 slices of bread for toasting (in Japan, this read bean paste is served on really thick slices)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;75 ml double cream  (cream with 50% fat)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drain the liquid, wash the beans in a sieve  and let them leak out for a few minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Combine the beans and syrup in a bowl. Crush with a fork, mix well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Microwave for 2 minutes at 360 W.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mix again, let it cool (I used &lt;em&gt;au bain marie&lt;/em&gt; to speed it up).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the &lt;em&gt;anko&lt;/em&gt; is cool enough, whip the cream with an electric mixer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Toast the bread.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spread the bean paste on the toast, add a dollop of whipped cream and enjoy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Pasta with carrots and mung beans</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/pasta-carrots-mung-beans/"/>
        <updated>2023-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/pasta-carrots-mung-beans</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/pasta-carrots-mung-beans_1600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;This is a delicious vegan pasta recipe with some slightly unusual ingredients. The less common ingredients in this recipe are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doenjang&quot;&gt;doenjang&lt;/a&gt;, a Korean-style soybean paste and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doubanjiang&quot;&gt;tobanjan&lt;/a&gt;, a broad bean chilly paste, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jasminehemsley.com/food-blog/2020/1/29/all-about-mung-dal&quot;&gt;mung dal&lt;/a&gt; ,skinned yellow split mung beans that are common in Indian cuisine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegan&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#60-minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;60-minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;750 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#600-800kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_3.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fresh ingredients &amp;amp; groceries
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;400 g carrots, chopped fine&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;100 g celery, chopped fine&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;half a courgette (100 g), chopped fine (*)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;mung dal (150 g or 2/3 cup)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;garlic (to taste; I use one or two cloves)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;ginger (at least 1 cm, chopped fine)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;herbes de Provence&lt;/em&gt; (handful)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;doubanjiang&lt;/em&gt;, Chinese fermented chili bean paste (to taste; I use less than a teaspoon)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;doenjang&lt;/em&gt;, Korean soybean paste (to taste; I use less than a teaspoon)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From the store cupboard
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 can of chopped tomatoes (400 g)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;dried porcini mushrooms (handful) (*)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;dried tomatoes (2 small or 1 large, cut in strips) (*)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;200 g pasta (I use linguine)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ingredients with (*) are optional. Sometimes I use fresh mushrooms instead of dried porcini, and the courgette is optional, it depends on what you have available. I’ve even added parsnips instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you use them, soak the dried mushrooms and dried tomatoes in hot water for about half an hour.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I make this in the microwave.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First cook the carrots, celery, ginger and garlic for about 6-7 minutes on full power (900W).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then add the dal, the mushrooms and tomatoes with their liquid, the canned tomatoes and some boiling water.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cook for a further 3-4 minutes at 900W.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then add the herbs, &lt;em&gt;doubanjiang&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;doenjang&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cook for 15-20 minutes at reduced power (360W), stir occasionally.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meanwhile, cook the pasta on the hob as usual.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I like to top this with walnut pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Midnight in Tokyo Story</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/tokyo-story-midnight/"/>
        <updated>2023-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/tokyo-story-midnight</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/tokyo-story-midnight_1600x600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;I wrote about the Japanese movie Tokyo Story (&lt;em&gt;tōkyō monogatari&lt;/em&gt;, 東京物語) and a poster I drew in &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/tokyo-story/&quot;&gt;an earlier post&lt;/a&gt;. It is a black-and-white movie from 1953 directed by Yasujirō Ozu about an elderly couple who travel to Tokyo to visit their grown-up children. It’s moving and poetic family story, slow-paced and without much overt drama. I very much like the cinematography, with long static shots of very carefully composed frames.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favourite scenes in the movie is a scene in the apartment of the widowed daughter-in-law, Noriko, where the mother, Tomi, bonds with Noriko. The scene is when they’re about to go to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides the articles linked in my earlier post, the 1982 article by Keiko McDonald &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/489426&quot;&gt;“Ozu’s Tokyo Story: Simple Means for Complex Ends”&lt;/a&gt; is one of the best analyses of the movie I’ve read. From that article, here is the description of the preamble to the scene:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The scene opens in a typical Ozu manner with a cut from the empty corridor to the inside of the apartment. The shot of the corridor is accompanied by the bong of a clock somewhere, Ozu’s favorite metaphor, which establishes the temporal setting for the dramatic action to follow. It is midnight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because there are very few indications of clock time in Tokyo Story, the clock chiming midnight is significant, even though the sound in the movie is really faint. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://core.ac.uk/display/229804153&quot;&gt;his article on the importance of time in Tokyo Story&lt;/a&gt;, Tetsuya Kumamoto explains that the length of the shot in the empty corridor is significantly longer than similar shots in the movie (more than 10 seconds, whereas usually it is about 7-8 seconds), and the only reason for this is precisely to provide enough time for the 12 bongs of the clock. At the same time that Tomi is quietly talking with Noriko, as shown in the preceding scene, Shūkichi is getting drunk with his old acquaintances. We get an indication of the time there as well, as he barmaid urges them to go home “because it’s already midnight”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keiko McDonalds commentary on the scene following the empty corridor shot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Two quilt beds have already been made, and Noriko is rubbing Tomi’s shoulder. To Japanese audiences this familiar scene is the very index of domestic harmony illuminating the young’s caring for the aged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on the following scene:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;After Noriko puts the quilt over her, Tomi hesitantly says that, as her mother-in-law, she feels badly that Noriko remains unmarried now that eight years have passed since her husband’s death. Noriko smilingly responds that she does not want to remarry, not because she is loyal to her late husband, but because she is more comfortable living alone. We must read between the lines of this conversation: there, we find a genuine mutual compassion as these two women articulate a kind of resignation in face of the merciless progression of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The movie then cuts back to now closed bar, to complete the symmetry. I think the scene is pivotal in the movie, because it leads to Noriko re-evaluating her life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-drawing&quot;&gt;The drawing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the movie, Tomi is played by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chieko_Higashiyama&quot;&gt;Chieko Higashiyama&lt;/a&gt; and Noriko by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Setsuko_Hara&quot;&gt;Setsuko Hara&lt;/a&gt;. I wanted to create a double portrait of Tomi and Noriko, and I stayed very close to the original shot, apart from cropping it to get both faces in an optimal position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used my preferred rough watercolour paper (Fabriano Artistico, 300 gsm, NOT), about 50 cm x 70 cm. I set up the drawing in ordinary pencil and worked it in Conté pencil (from HB to 3B). I don’t sharpen the Conté pencils to a point. I also used kneaded putty and a piece of soft rag for blending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/tokyo-story-midnight.avif&quot; alt=&quot;A black and white pencil drawing of two Japanese women, one elderly (Tomi) and one younger (Noriko), in a rather dark room with a bright square of light coming through a partly-obscured window. They both wear light-coloured yukata, Tomi&apos;s in a conservative pattern of small blossoms, Noriko&apos;s in a bold pattern of large dark thistle-like flowers. Noriko s rubbing Tomi&apos;s shoulder and smiling faintly.&quot; title=&quot;A black and white pencil drawing of two Japanese women, one elderly (Tomi) and one younger (Noriko), in a rather dark room with a bright square of light coming through a partly-obscured window.  They both wear light-coloured yukata, Tomi&apos;s in a conservative pattern of small blossoms, Noriko&apos;s in a bold pattern of large dark thistle-like flowers. Noriko s rubbing Tomi&apos;s shoulder and smiling faintly.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The drawing of Tomi and Noriko&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The banner is a crop of the still on which the drawing is based.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Tokyo Story</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/tokyo-story/"/>
        <updated>2022-10-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/tokyo-story</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/tokyo-story_1600x600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;Tokyo Story (&lt;em&gt;tōkyō monogatari&lt;/em&gt;, 東京物語) is a probably one of the most famous Japanese films, and definitely one of my favourites. It is a black-and-white movie from 1953 directed by Yasujirō Ozu about an elderly couple who travel to Tokyo to visit their grown-up children. It’s moving and poetic family story, slow-paced and without much overt drama. I very much like the cinematography, with long static shots of very carefully composed frames.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bfi.org.uk/features/tokyo-story-anatomy-classic&quot;&gt;article from the British Film Institute&lt;/a&gt; that provides a nice analysis of the movie and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.filminquiry.com/politicism-tokyo-story/&quot;&gt;this article in FilmInquiry&lt;/a&gt; discusses the politics. The movie was released in 1953 and is quite critical of the Japanese society at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There also is &lt;a href=&quot;https://core.ac.uk/download/pdf/229804153.pdf&quot;&gt;a very interesting article&lt;/a&gt; about the notion of time in this movie (in Japanese, abstract in French), “Recurrent time and irreversible time in  Yasujirō Ozu’s Tokyo Story”. It explains how the parents, living in a traditional small village, experience time differently from the children living in the modern city, and how this is illustrated through the way time is handled in the movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;starting-material&quot;&gt;Starting material&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to make a drawing based on period posters for this movie. So I looked up a number of posters and composed a version with the three key figures of the final part of the movie, the father (Shūkichi), his daughter Kyōko and the widow of his son, Noriko.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the two posters I used:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/tokyomonogatari_01.avif&quot; alt=&quot;.&quot; title=&quot;.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/tokyomonogatari_02.avif&quot; alt=&quot;.&quot; title=&quot;.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Japanese posters for the movie Tokyo Story&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;selecting-the-text&quot;&gt;Selecting the text&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a poster, the text is an essential part of the artwork. I wanted to keep some of the original promotion text but also add some that is taken from the movie itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-promotion-text&quot;&gt;The promotion text&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course I kept the title, I used the lettering as in the first poster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept the original line of one of the posters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;香り高き詩情　美と哀愁の藝術作&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first part means literally “fragrant poetic sentiment”, so maybe  “a strong sense of poetry”; the second part means “a work of art of beauty and sorrow”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slightly modified another line from one of the posters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;一年一作小津安二郎作品&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;became&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;最高の小津安二郎作品&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which means “Yasujirō Ozu’s best work”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-most-memorable-lines&quot;&gt;The most memorable lines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also incorporated what I consider the most memorable exchange in the movie:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me this has always been the most memorable exchange in Tokyo Story. Noriko, the widowed daughter-in-law is talking to Kyoko, 
the younger daughter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;京子：「いやぁねぇ、世の中って……」&lt;br /&gt;
紀子：「そう、いやなことばっかり……」&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The English subtitles translate this as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kyoko: “Isn’t life disappointing?”&lt;br /&gt;
Noriko: “Yes, nothing but disappointment.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“disappointment” is probably too strong though. いや (iya) is a term meaning disagreeable, unpleasant etc.  世の中 “yo no naka” means “world, society”, and the って means something like “what you call … “ or “the so-called …”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the conclusion of a longer exchange in which Noriko explains to Kyoko that it is inevitable that children drift apart once they have their own lives to live. I like this exchange because it summarizes what it means to grow up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stylised this a  bit differently for the drawing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;京子〜嫌なね、世の中って&lt;br /&gt;
紀子〜そう、嫌な事許り&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-evening-bell&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The evening bell&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the movie, a children’s choir sings the song “The evening bell” (&lt;em&gt;yuube no kane&lt;/em&gt;, 夕べの鐘) and I incorporated the lyrics into the poster as well:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;writing-mode: vertical-rl&quot;&gt;
昔の人&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;今や何處&lt;br /&gt;
訪れ来て&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;佇めば&lt;br /&gt;
黄昏ゆく&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;空を辿&lt;br /&gt;
通いて来る&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;鐘の声&lt;br /&gt;
家鳩の&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;羽搏きに&lt;br /&gt;
乱れて消ゆ&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;軒の妻&lt;br /&gt;
緑の風&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;岸を戦ぐ
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only incorporated the lyrics that are sung in the movie, there is a little bit more:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;writing-mode: vertical-rl&quot;&gt;
川のほとり&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;さまよえば&lt;br /&gt;
黄昏ゆく&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;路地を越えて&lt;br /&gt;
おとない来る&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;鐘の声&lt;br /&gt;
牧の童が&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;笛の音に&lt;br /&gt;
消えては行く&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;村はずれ
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not seen any mention of this song in articles about the movie, and yet it is significant, because it describes an evening scene in a small village by a river, the kind of village where the father and daughter live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could not find a translation, I did my best to translate it but the song is from 1908 and besides being poetry, it uses some archaic constructions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the people of yore,  where are they now&lt;br /&gt;
maybe they loiter and  come to visit&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the gathering dusk creeps across the sky&lt;br /&gt;
the sound of the bell coming and going&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;vanishing eaves, disturbed&lt;br /&gt;
by the flapping of pigeon wings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the green wind stirring the bank&lt;br /&gt;
wandering around the river&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;dusk creeps across the paths through the fields&lt;br /&gt;
the sound of the bell comes to visit&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;a shepherd boy with the sound of a flute&lt;br /&gt;
fading away on the edge of the village&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The background to the choice of this song in the movie is interesting. This was a song taught to school children before the war, but after the war, by the time the movie was made, it had been replaced by another song, “Spring breeze”, with the same melody but different lyrics. So why did Ozu choose this particular song? This song is much more serious in tone than Spring Breeze, it has something of a requiem or elegy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://note.com/catlove0404/n/n48e26718d79f&quot;&gt;an interesting story&lt;/a&gt; about the possible reason for this choice. Yasujiro Ozu’s assistant director, Yoshio Tsukamoto, died from leukaemia at the age of 39 shortly before the filming of the movie had started. They had been very close and had been through the war together, in Singapore. They were interned there after the war and when a ship came to repatriate them, there were not enough places. Ozu ceded his place but Tsukamoto stayed with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ozu was deeply affected by Tsukamoto’s death, and this song was his way of expressing his grief in the movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may have been the case but even without this personal background, the choice of the song is perfect for the final scene, cutting between Noriko in the train and Kyōko classroom. There is even a nice connection with the two notions of time: Noriko on the train steaming to Tokyo, looking at the watch signifying the irreversible time, and the temple bell in the song, which epitomises the recurrent time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-drawing&quot;&gt;The drawing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drawing process and the materials I used for this drawing are the same as for the drawings discussed in my previous posts, &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/shinbashi-doori&quot;&gt;“The Blue Dragon of Kiyomizu-dera”&lt;/a&gt; and  &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/seiryuu&quot;&gt;“Summer night in Shinbashi dōri”&lt;/a&gt;. This drawing is on a sheet of watercolour paper of 56 cm × 76 cm (30×22 inches) of Fabriano Artistico  300 g/m² “not”, cold pressed with a rough finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only took one intermediate picture, of the the line drawing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/tokyo-story-poster-pencil.avif&quot; alt=&quot;Pencil sketch, line drawing only.&quot; title=&quot;Pencil sketch, line drawing only.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Pencil sketch with the guide squares&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is the final result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/tokyo-story-poster-final.avif&quot; alt=&quot;A movie poster shown centrally three Japanese people squatting in front of a low wall. On the right is an elderly man with a dark mourning kimono. Next to him, a young woman in a brown-red plain skirt and a yellow blouse with short sleeves; next to here another young woman in a blue plain skirt and a light pink blouse with short sleeves. The man and the woman in the middle stare into the distance; the woman on the right looks at the viewer. The background shows a broad river with a silhouette of a boat, low hills on the further bank. Next to the low wall, behind the man, is a tall stone lantern. There are four rows of Japanese writing above the figures, one in black, one in red and two short ones in black; below the figures on the left are four large red characters; to the right several columns of black text.&quot; title=&quot;A movie poster shown centrally three Japanese people squatting in front of a low wall. On the right is an elderly man with a dark mourning kimono. Next to him, a young woman in a brown-red plain skirt and a yellow blouse with short sleeves; next to here another young woman in a blue plain skirt and a light pink blouse with short sleeves. The man and the woman in the middle stare into the distance; the woman on the right looks at the viewer. The background shows a broad river with a silhouette of a boat, low hills on the further bank. Next to the low wall, behind the man, is a tall stone lantern. There are four rows of Japanese writing above the figures, one in black, one in red and two short ones in black; below the figures on the left are four large red characters; to the right several columns of black text.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The finished watercolour&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hiragana-and-romaji-of-the-text&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;romaji&lt;/em&gt; of the text&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For learners of Japanese, here are the hiragana and romaji for the text on the poster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-first-line&quot;&gt;The first line&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;香り高き詩情　美と哀愁の藝術作&lt;br /&gt;
かおりたかきしじょう　びとあいしゅうのげいじゅつか&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;kaoritakaki shijou bi to aishuu no geijutsuka&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-second-line&quot;&gt;The second line&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;最高の小津安二郎作品&lt;br /&gt;
さいこうのおつやすじろうさくひん&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;saikou no otsu yasujirou sakuhin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-dialogue&quot;&gt;The dialogue&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;京子：「いやぁねぇ、世の中って……」&lt;br /&gt;
紀子：「そう、いやなことばっかり……」&lt;br /&gt;
きょうこ：「いやぁねぇ、よのなかって……」&lt;br /&gt;
のりこ：「そう、いやなことばっかり……」&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Kyouko: iyaa nee, yo no nakatte…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Noriko: sou, iya na koto bakari…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-movies-name&quot;&gt;The movie’s name&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;東京物語&lt;br /&gt;
とうきょうものがたり&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;tōkyō monogatari&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-song&quot;&gt;The song&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ゆうべのかね&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;むかしのひといまいずこ&lt;br /&gt;
おとずれきてたたずめば&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;たぞがれゆくそらをたどり&lt;br /&gt;
かよいてくるかねのおと&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;いえばとのはばたきに&lt;br /&gt;
みだれてきゆのきのつま&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;みどりのかぜきしをそよぐ&lt;br /&gt;
かわのほとりさまよえば&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;たぞがれゆくやろをこえて&lt;br /&gt;
おとないくるかねのおと&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;まきのわらべふえのおと&lt;br /&gt;
きえてはゆくむらはずれ&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;yuube no kane&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;mukashi no hito ima izuko?&lt;br /&gt;
otozure kite tatazumeba&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;tazogare yuku sora wo tadori&lt;br /&gt;
kayoite kuru kane no oto&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;iebato no habataki ni&lt;br /&gt;
midarete kiyu noki no tsuma&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt; 
　&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;midori no kaze kishi wo soyogu&lt;br /&gt;
kawa no hotori samayoeba&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;tazore yuku yaro wo koete&lt;br /&gt;
otonai kuru kane not oto&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;maki no warabe fue no oto ni&lt;br /&gt;
kiete wa yuku murahazure&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The banner picture shows a black-and-white picture of the father and his daughter-in-law in the same pose as on the poster.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>The Blue Dragon of Kiyomizu-dera</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/seiryuu/"/>
        <updated>2022-10-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/seiryuu</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/seiryuu_1600x600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;A watercolour of the Blue Dragon of Kiyomizu-dera during the procession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;kiyomizu-dera&quot;&gt;Kiyomizu-dera&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kiyomizu-dera (清水寺) is a famous temple in eastern Kyoto. It sits on a steep hill and its main hall is built on a high wooden platform that offers great views over the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an expression  &lt;em&gt;kiyomizu no butai kara tobioriru&lt;/em&gt; (清水の舞台から飛び降りる) which translates a “to jump off the stage of the Kiyomizu temple” and means “to make a leap into the dark, to jump in at the deep end”. In the olden days, (presumably rather desperate) people would jump off the platform of the Kannon hall of the temple in the belief that, if they got off scot-free, their wishes would be granted, and if they died they would enter Nirvana. The drop is thirteen metres.&lt;br /&gt;
Records from the Edo era show that 234 people jumped off the platform; 34 of them died. In 1872, the Kyoto city council issued an order forbidding this practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-kannon-with-the-thousand-arms-and-thousand-eyes&quot;&gt;The Kannon with the Thousand Arms and Thousand Eyes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kiyomizu-dera is a Buddhist temple and is dedicated to Kannon (観音, &lt;em&gt;kan-on&lt;/em&gt;), the bodhisattva of infinite compassion. I wrote a previous post about this deity, &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/kannon/&quot;&gt;“The mystery of the giant Kannon statues”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The manifestation of Kannon worshipped in Kiyomizu-dera is the Thousand-armed Kannon (&lt;em&gt;senju kannon&lt;/em&gt;,  千手観音), one of the most popular manifestations: the thousand arms symbolizes Kannon’s ability to embrace and alleviate the suffering of the world. In full it is the “Kannon with a Thousand Arms and a Thousand Eyes”, every hand holds an eye. People prayed to the Senju Kannon to avoid illness, eye problems, and blindness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-blue-dragon&quot;&gt;The Blue Dragon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In traditional Chinese astronomy, there are four mythological creatures that guard the four cardinal directions. They are the Blue Dragon of the East, the Vermilion Bird of the South, the White Tiger of the West, and the Black Tortoise of the North. In Japan these creatures are considered the guardian spirits of cities. So the Blue Dragon (&lt;em&gt;seiryū&lt;/em&gt;, 青龍) protects the city of Kyoto on the east and Kiyomizu-dera is dedicated to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kiyomizu-dera temple legend says that the Kannon is incarnated as the Blue Dragon. The temple is built on the site of the Otowa waterfall (音羽の瀧) and according to the legend, every night the dragon comes flying to drink from the water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-drawing&quot;&gt;The drawing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March and September there is a procession called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kiyomizudera.or.jp/en/visit/seiryu-e/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;seiryū-e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (青龍会), in which a large (18 m long) dragon is paraded through the streets by a host of costumed actors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some years ago, I was staying in Kyoto for a while. I was lucky enough to just happen to pass by when the procession was being held. I made a drawing based on a picture I took.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drawing is mostly a faithful rendition of the photograph, except for the sky and some of the colours (there is more blue in my drawing). Also, if you look closely, you see that the papier-maché head of the dragon is covered in Japanese characters. Because of the shape of the head and also the resolution of the picture, these were quite hard to read, but I could work out that they were taken from Buddhist sutras. So I searched for the text of a sutra and used that for the parts where I could not read the actual characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the dragon is called “blue”, and sometimes “azure” or “cerulean”, the scales of the dragon in the procession are a dark blue-green tint. In Japanese, the word &lt;em&gt;aoi&lt;/em&gt; (青い) means both blue and green, for example a traffic light is &lt;em&gt;aoshingō&lt;/em&gt; (青信号). In my drawing I tried to match the original colour of the scales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have explained my drawing process and the materials I use in a previous post, &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/shinbashi-doori&quot;&gt;“Summer night in Shinbashi dōri”&lt;/a&gt;. This drawing is on a sheet of 56 cm × 38 cm, also known as “half imperial”, of Arches 300 g/m² “not”, i.e. cold pressed with a rough finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are a few intermediate stages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The line drawing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/seiryuu_1.avif&quot; alt=&quot;Pencil sketch, line drawing only.&quot; title=&quot;Pencil sketch, line drawing only.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Pencil sketch with the guide squares and perspective lines&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some colour applied:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/seiryuu_2.avif&quot; alt=&quot;Pencil sketch with some portions coloured in with coloured pencil.&quot; title=&quot;Pencil sketch with some portions coloured in with coloured pencil.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Pencil sketch with some portions coloured in with coloured pencil&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some washing done:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/seiryuu_3.avif&quot; alt=&quot;Pencil sketch with some portions washed.&quot; title=&quot;Pencil sketch with some portions washed.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Pencil sketch with some portions washed&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is the final result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/seiryuu.avif&quot; alt=&quot;The papier mache head and part of the body of a dragon. The head is off-white and densely covered in kanji; the dragon has four tall horns and huge teeth, flared nostrils and a large yellow eye. Background is a traditional Kyoto street.&quot; title=&quot;The papier mache head and part of the body of a dragon. The head is off-white and densely covered in kanji; the dragon has four tall horns and huge teeth, flared nostrils and a large yellow eye. Background is a traditional Kyoto street.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The finished watercolour&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The banner picture shows part of the picture of the dragon on which drawing is based.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Yellow peppers and tofu sticks in Filipino-style creamy sauce</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/vegan-binagoonang/"/>
        <updated>2022-10-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/vegan-binagoonang</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/vegan-binagoonang_1600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;This is a vegan version of a Filipino recipe, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kawalingpinoy.com/binagoongan-baboy-sa-gata/&quot;&gt;Binagoongan Baboy sa Gata&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a variant of &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/veggie-binagoonang-talong/&quot;&gt;my own recipe&lt;/a&gt; with yellow peppers instead of aubergines, and a few other changes in ingredients. The less common ingredients in this recipe are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tofu_skin#Dried&quot;&gt;dried tofu (bean curd) sticks&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doenjang&quot;&gt;doenjang&lt;/a&gt;, a Korean-style soybean paste and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doubanjiang&quot;&gt;tobanjan&lt;/a&gt;, a broad bean chilly paste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegan&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#gluten-free&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;gluten-free&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#30-minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;30-minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;900 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#800-1000kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_4.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fresh ingredients &amp;amp; groceries
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 cm ginger, finely chopped&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 stick celery, finely chopped&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 cloves garlic&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 medium yellow peppers, cut lengthwise into strips&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 can of chopped tomatoes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;50 g tofu sticks&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;50 g creamed coconut&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From the store cupboard
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;a handful of dried &lt;em&gt;shiitake&lt;/em&gt; mushrooms&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/2 cup of cashew nuts, coarsely ground&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/2 teaspoon &lt;em&gt;tobanjan&lt;/em&gt; paste&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon &lt;em&gt;doenjang&lt;/em&gt; paste&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon cooking wine (e.g. &lt;em&gt;mirin&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;shaoxing&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon vinegar&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons rice bran oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cup of rice (preferably jasmine rice)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soak the tofu sticks in very hot water for 30 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soak the &lt;em&gt;shiitake&lt;/em&gt; in very hot water for 30 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Grate the creamed coconut&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meanwhile
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cook the peppers 6 minutes in the microwave at full power (900W).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Drain the cooking liquid into a small bowl. Add the cooking wine, &lt;em&gt;doenjang&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;tobanjan&lt;/em&gt; and stir to dissolve.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Heat the oil in a deep pan. When the oil is hot, add the ginger, celery and garlic and fry for a few minutes over medium heat.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the peppers to the pan and stir fry for a few minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Drain the tofu sticks and cut them into pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the tofu sticks and the ground cashews to the pan and cook until lightly browned.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the dissolved &lt;em&gt;doenjang&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;tobanjan&lt;/em&gt;, tomatoes and vinegar and cook, stirring occasionally, for a few minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add about a cup of hot water to the grated coconut, stir to dissolve and add to the pan&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Simmer for a few minutes over lower heat. Add some of the soaking liquid of the mushrooms if required.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Let it reduce for a few minutes&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Serve with rice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Kitchen</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/kitchen/"/>
        <updated>2022-07-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/kitchen</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/kitchen_1600x600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;I would like to try an explain why Banana Yoshimoto’s novel “Kitchen” is my favourite novel, because I think reading it might make you happy¹. You may think, well, that’s easy, it’s about cooking and food and Japan. But that is true for many Japanese novels; also, when I first read it, I was not as much into Japan or into food as I am today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read this novel first in 1997 or so, in any case a few years after the English translation came out in 1993. I borrowed it from the library in Gent, where I was living at the time. When I moved to Scotland, I bought the paperback and that is when it became my favourite. My edition, the UK edition from faber and faber, 2001, has a very simple cover: just a uniform deep pink with the large Japanese characters 台所, and in a thin, wide-kerning sans-serif font “&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: sans&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;letter-spacing:0.7em;&quot;&gt;kitche&lt;/span&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;”. The word 台所 (&lt;em&gt;daidokoro&lt;/em&gt;) means kitchen in Japanese².&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a small and thin book containing the short novel Kitchen and the novella Moonlight Shadow, 150 pages in total. So what makes Kitchen so special for me? I could of course point to the sales figures (in Japan, it was reprinted sixty times and sold millions of copies; it was translated into more than twenty-five languages) and accolades (several literary prizes), or the many scholarly articles and dissertations that have been written about it (some of which I have read with interest) but I didn’t  know about all that until later. The reason it was translated at all was of course because it was such a best seller in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a book that has always comforted me. The main topics are about dealing with loss and grieving and being alone in the world. Nevertheless, the story is never depressing (it’s also about love). It’s a slice-of-life novel so the plot is not important, and when summarised does amount to very little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what really makes it my favourite is the writing and in particular the imagery used. The English translation made a deep impression on me. I think that what I like is how the protagonist observes the world, nature and people, and puts it into words. There is a lot of images of light and darkness, which I like in particular. It is very poetic, but at the same time casual as well. Banana Yoshimoto’s writing manages to make the most banal and everyday scenes beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The translation by Megan Backus has been variously criticised (for not being true to the original; for being too literal; for being sentimental,… ) and praised (for being true to the original, for being poetic and beautiful). I have now finally read the novel in Japanese, and it was a wonderful experience. Unsurprisingly, I think the Japanese version is better than the translation. Banana Yoshimoto’s writing is very special, and very difficult to translate (even more so than for example Yoko Ogawa, who also writes very beautiful Japanese).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The language in Kitchen is strongly influenced by shoujo manga (Japanese comics for adolescent girls and young adult women), and therefore a combination of very casual language and literary and poetic language; also, Banana Yoshimoto uses many grammatical constructions that don’t translate easily into English. Japanese typically has a topic/comment structure rather than subject-verb-object, but in many cases sentences can be rearranged to match the English structure more closely; Banana Yoshimoto’s writing style makes that harder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, even though it is not flawless (because of course I now notice the flaws), I still love the translated version. I have read other works by Banana Yoshimoto in translation (Lizard, N.P., Goodbye Tsugumi, all translated by Ann Sherif; Asleep, translated by Michael Emmerich); of those, I have read Lizard in Japanese as well. And I would say that in the end it does not really matter: all translations will be different, but in the hands of a competent translator, the voice the original author will be mostly preserved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an experiment, I tried to translate a short passage from Kitchen myself. The context: Mikage, the young woman who is the narrator of the story, is on a work trip and has gone out late to find something to eat because she’s starving. While waiting for her food, she phones her friend Yuichi, who is also on a trip and, it turns out, is also very hungry. When she tastes the delicious food (&lt;em&gt;katsudon&lt;/em&gt;), she decides to order a takeaway meal and take it to him, by taxi — a ride of many hours. When she gets there, in the middle of the night, the &lt;em&gt;ryokan&lt;/em&gt; where Yuichi is staying is closed, so she scales the wall of the building to his room is, a dangerous climb which she only manages with great difficulty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My translation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I dropped my backpack at my side and, lying face-up looking up towards the roof of the ryokan, I gazed at the  bright moon and clouds and got thinking.
(I thought, really, how could I be thinking of this kind of things in such a situation? It was rather a desperate one after all.  But I’d like to be called a philosopher in action.)
People all think that there are many roads and that we can choose them for ourselves. It’s probably closer to say that we dream of the moment of choice.
It was like that for me. But there and then, I knew. I knew so that I could put it clearly into words: although by no means in a fatalistic sense, the road has always been decided.
Every day’s breath, every look,  repeated day after day, is spontaneously decided. And so in my case, before I realised, as if it was the most natural thing in the world, my katsudon and I had to be lying flat in a puddle on a roof in a strange place in the middle of winter, looking up at the night sky.&lt;br /&gt;
—Ah, the moon was so beautiful!&lt;br /&gt;
I got up and knocked on the window of Yuichi’s room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the official translation by Megan Backus:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I shrugged off my pack. Lying there on my back, I looked up at the roof of the inn and, staring at the glowing moon and clouds, I thought, really, we’re all in the same position. (It occurred to me that I had often thought that in similar situations, in moments of utter desperation. I would like to be known as an action philosopher.)
We all believe we can choose our own path from among the many alternatives. But perhaps it’s more accurate to say that we make the choice unconsciously. I think I did – but now I knew it, because now I was able to put it into words. But I don’t mean this in the fatalistic sense; we’re constantly making choices. With the breaths we take every day, with the expression in our eyes, with the daily actions we do over and over, we decide as though by instinct. And so some of us will inevitably find ourselves rolling around in a puddle on some roof in a strange place with a takeout katsudon in the middle of winter, looking up at the night sky, as if it were the most natural thing in the world.&lt;br /&gt;
 Ah, but the moon was lovely.&lt;br /&gt;
 I stood up and knocked on Yuichi’s window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Japanese text:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;
リュックを横に放り出して仰向けに寝てままで旅館の屋根を見上げて、その向こうに見える光る月や雲をみつめて私は思った。（よくもまあその状態でそんなことをかんがえたものだとおもう。やけくそだったのだろう。行動する哲学者と呼んでもらいたい）人はみんな、道はたくさんあって、自分で選ぶことができると思っている。選ぶ瞬間を夢見ている、と言ったほうが近いのかもしれない。私も、そうだった。しかし今、知った。はっきりと言葉にして知ったのだ。決して運命論的な意味ではなくて、道はいつも決まっている。毎日の呼吸が、まなざしが、くりかえす日々が自然と決めてしまうのだ。そして人によってはこうやって、気づくとまるで当然のことのように見知らぬ土地のやねの水たまりのなかで真冬に、カツ丼と共に夜空を見上げて寝ころがらざるをえなくなる。&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;mdash;あぁ、月がとてもきれい。&lt;br /&gt;
私は立ち上がり、雄一の部屋の窓をノックした。
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Romaji:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;RYUKKU wo yoko ni houridashite aomuke ni nete mama de ryokan no yane wo miagete, sono mukou ni mieru hikaru tsuki ya kumo wo mitsumete watashi ha omotta. (Yokumo maa sono joutai de sonna koto wo kangaeta mono da to omou. Yakekuso datta no darou. Koudou suru tetsugakusha to yonde moraitai) hito ha minna, michi ha takusan atte, jibun de erabu koto ga dekiru to omotte iru. Erabu shunkan wo yumemite iru, to itta hou ga chikai no kamoshirenai. Watashi mo, sou datta. Shikashi ima, shitta. Hakkiri to kotoba ni shite shitta no da. Kesshite unmeironteki na imi deha nakute, michi ha itsumo kimatte iru. Mainichi no kokyuu ga, manazashi ga, kurikaesu hibi ga shizen to kimete shimau no da. Soshite hito ni yotte ha kou yatte, kidzuku to maru de touzen no koto no you ni mishiranu dochi no yane no mizutamari no naka de mafuyu ni, katsudon to tomo ni yozora wo miagete nekorogarazaru wo enaku naru.&lt;br /&gt;
—Aa, tsuki ga totemo kirei.&lt;br /&gt;
Watashi ha tachiagari, Yuuichi no heya no mado wo NOKKU shita.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;[¹] unless you are anti-trans, anti-gay or anti-pineapple. Or anti-Japan of course.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;small&gt;[²] The Japanese title is however キッチン &lt;em&gt;KITCHIN&lt;/em&gt;, the English loanword.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The banner picture shows the kind of large pink telephone Mikage used to phone Yuichi.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Summer night in Shinbashi dōri</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/shinbashi-doori/"/>
        <updated>2022-07-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/shinbashi-doori</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/shinbashi-doori_1600x600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;I’ve finished another watercolour, on a sheet of 56 cm × 76 cm ( 30×22 inches) so quite large. The paper is Fabriano Artistico 300 g/m² “not”, cold pressed with a rough finish. The materials I used are my usual combination of plain pencil and Derwent Inktense and Conté Aquarelle watercolour pencils. I started it at the end of March so it took about three months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/shinbashi-doori-framed.avif&quot; alt=&quot;A watercolour of a busy, narrow pedestrian street at night. Lots of shop signs with Japanese characters.&quot; title=&quot;A watercolour of a busy, narrow pedestrian street at night. Lots of shop signs with Japanese characters.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The finished watercolour&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;topic&quot;&gt;Topic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The topic is a night view of an alley in Kyōto, based on picture I took during my stay in 2018. I picked it because I wanted something with a lot of colour and detail, in portrait format. And because I love Kyōto. Working on that drawing takes me straight back there, to the warmth of the summer night, the typical smells, sounds and visual impressions. And just the feeling of being there.&lt;br /&gt;
In Japanese there is a word for this feeling of happy memories, &lt;em&gt;natsukashii&lt;/em&gt; (懐かしい). It’s close to “nostalgic”, but without negative connotations. The dictionary says “fondly-remembered”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making a detailed drawing of a night scene is fun and challenging: because of the limitations of taking night shots with my compact camera without tripod, the original image is not entirely sharp; also, some of the brighter signs are washed out. And of course the details in the darker parts are quite lost. So I try to work out the signs and other missing parts by comparing various pictures and searching on the internet for additional, daytime pictures of that alley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially the &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; (Chinese characters) on the signs are hard. If I would copy them without really understanding the characters, then the strokes would be wrong and that would be obvious to anyone who can read them. So I need to work out which kanji the often very stylised calligraphy represent. Then I can attempt to write them in the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things I like about drawing is that I can change whatever I like. A picture is already a lie, but in a drawing there are so many more ways in which you can alter the reality. Most of what is shown in the drawing was there on the picture. I only lied a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alley is called Shinbashi Dōri (真橋通り). It comes out onto a bridge over the Takasegawa (高瀬川), which is a narrow canal bordered with cherry trees. The bridge is called Shinbashi  (真橋) and the alley takes it name from the bridge.
It’s close to the much more famous Pontochō Alley (先斗町通り) and not far from the Gion Bridge over the Kamo river. The scene in the drawing is observed  from the entrance of the alley from Kawaramachi Dōri (河原町通り), one of the main north-south thoroughfares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shinbashi Dōri runs parallel with Shijō Dōri (四条通り), one of the main roads running east-west. Already in the Heian era (around 800 CE), Kyōto (then called Heian-Kyō) was laid out on a grid pattern with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heian_Palace&quot;&gt;imperial palace facing south after the Chinese fashion&lt;/a&gt; and the main east-west roads counting up from the palace towards the south. The roads were simply numbered from 1 to 9  starting with Ichijō (#1) just to the north of the palace grounds, Nijō (#2) just to the south, then Sanjō (#3), Shijō (#4) and so on and ending at Kujō (#9). If you’ve read the Tale of Genji, you will recall that Genji had a Nijō residence and one of the important women in his life live was called the Rokujō have because her residence was on Rokujō.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, Shijō Dōri is the most well-known as it is a major shopping street and it runs to Gion bridge and the Gion quarter. Amazingly, all of these roads still exist, or at least there are still roads and alleys in Kyōto with those names in roughly the same place as the original ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;drawing-process&quot;&gt;Drawing process&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way I make a drawing like this is quite straightforward: I crop the image to the scene I want, then divide it into squares using guides. I divide the paper in the same number of squares, with pencil and ruler. For detailed parts, I divide the squares into smaller squares. Then I set the drawing up in pencil with the picture on my screen as reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this particular drawing, I also looked at the position of the vanishing point and put in perspective guide lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/s1.avif&quot; alt=&quot;Pencil sketch, line drawing only.&quot; title=&quot;Pencil sketch, line drawing only.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Pencil sketch with the guide squares and perspective lines&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I’m happy with that I will usually do some very rough shading and work out some of the details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/s2.avif&quot; alt=&quot;Pencil sketch with rough shading.&quot; title=&quot;Pencil sketch with rough shading.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Pencil sketch with rough shading&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like using watercolour pencils. You can apply the colour first like ordinary coloured pencils and then wash them. I usually don’t put on all colour before starting to wash. Maybe that would be more systematic but I tend to postpone the parts that I am unsure about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/s3.avif&quot; alt=&quot;Pencil sketch with some portions coloured in with coloured pencil.&quot; title=&quot;Pencil sketch with some portions coloured in with coloured pencil.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Pencil sketch with some portions coloured in with coloured pencil&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colouring in a large drawing like this is much like completing a jigsaw puzzle. Until a certain amount is done it is really hard to say what it will look like, and finding the best way to colour in some small part is also a bit like hunting for the missing pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/s4.avif&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing with some areas washed, some still in pencil lines.&quot; title=&quot;Drawing with some areas washed, some still in pencil lines.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The drawing is taking shape, large portions are now washed to bring out the colour&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rules&quot;&gt;Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a few “rules” for myself when it comes to drawing and watercolours:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;use rough, heavy paper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;don’t sharpen the pencils too often&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;don’t use too fine a brush&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;don’t correct mistakes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Look, that’s why there’s rules, understand?&lt;br /&gt;So that you think before you break ‘em.&lt;br /&gt;– Terry Pratchett, “Thief of time”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The banner picture shows part of the original picture I used for the drawing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Quiet crystallisation</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/memory-police/"/>
        <updated>2022-05-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/memory-police</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/memory-police_1600x600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;“The Memory Police” (&lt;em&gt;hisoyaka na kesshō&lt;/em&gt;, 密やかな結晶) is a novel from 1994 by Yoko Ogawa, one of Japan’s most renowned writers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s set on an island but the community there is otherwise quite similar to mainland Japan. Things disappear from the community’s life, and people forget about them. They don’t simply disappear. For example, when the “perfume” disappears , people pour out their perfume bottles in the river. Then they forget that perfume ever existed. And when “birds” disappear, people set free their caged birds, and totally forget all about birds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book centres on three characters: the narrator (&lt;em&gt;watashi&lt;/em&gt; わたし, “I”), the old man (&lt;em&gt;ojii-san&lt;/em&gt; おじいさん, &lt;em&gt;jii&lt;/em&gt; is old man and &lt;em&gt;o&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;san&lt;/em&gt; are honorifics) and the narrator’s editor, “R” (&lt;em&gt;R-shi&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;shi&lt;/em&gt; 氏 is a formal form of referring to a person, typically someone one is not close with).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started reading near the end of February and it took me three months to read the novel in Japanese, reading a few pages most evenings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would recommend this book because it is very taught-provoking. Although nothing really bad happens explicitly, it is a very sad story. The book has 28 chapters and the real turning point is by the end of Chapter 25. It’s very beautifully written, with a great eye for small details and remarkable control over specificity: early on, the setting of the story seems very generic but as the book progresses, there are more specific Japanese cultural references; towards the end they disappear again. I really like the way the author expresses e.g. unease of a character by describing how he keeps putting his feet into his slippers and pulling them back out, or the details about the type of shoe that makes a specific sound, so you can tell the wearer is a young woman, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the title in Japanese &lt;em&gt;hisoyaka&lt;/em&gt; means quiet, still, surreptitious; &lt;em&gt;kesshou&lt;/em&gt; means crystal or crystallisation but also fruits of labour etc. So it  is “Quiet crystallisation”. (The French title is “Cristallisation secrète”.) According to the afterword, the Yoko Ogawa was thinking of “crystallised” memories we carry inside us. The English title puts the focus on the Memory Police themselves but they are not the focus of the novel. The problem with the English title is that it leads the reader to expect some totalitarian political novel, which it is not. The memory police serve as a cause for fear because of their control of the population, but that is not the point at all. To my mind, the novel is really about the acceptance of loss. Loss of memories, loss of many good things in life, loss of loved ones, loss of abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- I have been considering the implication of the existence of the Memory Police in the novel (which in Japanese is simply called the　Secret Police, _himitsu keisatsu_ 秘密警察). There seems to be no reason why they should exist. Then I realised that there does not need to be a reason beyond their purpose: those in power have realised that a given situation can be exploited to gain additional control over the population, and created the system to exert that control. That the situation does not require this system is entirely irrelevant. The purpose is control. --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;issues-of-translation-from-japanese&quot;&gt;Issues of translation from Japanese&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am increasingly interested in issues of translation from Japanese.  Reading a Japanese novel does not require full translation, because I don’t need to turn a Japanese sentence into an English  one (or a Dutch one, as that is my native tongue) to understand it. I’ve written a few blog posts on &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/reading-murakami/&quot;&gt;reading Japanese&lt;/a&gt;, especially &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/learning-japanese-reading-murakami/&quot;&gt;as a learner&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while reading this novel I did think a lot about how it could be translated. What is peculiar in this novel is that there are hardly any typically Japanese elements. It could be set anywhere. Mentions of food are very unspecific; people drink coffee, black tea or cocoa and sometimes wine. Even terms that could have been specific such as the mention of an altar to the sea gods in an old ferry, are not: the word used is &lt;em&gt;umi no kamisama no saidan&lt;/em&gt; 海の神様の祭壇 rather than the more common Shinto term &lt;em&gt;watatzumi no kamidana&lt;/em&gt; 海神の神棚. 
There are the typically Japanese politeness levels and honorary pre- and suffixes, but if I were to translate it, I would not try to emulate them. Especially the old man is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; polite, and always refers to the narrator as &lt;em&gt;ojousama&lt;/em&gt; お嬢様, a very formal way of saying “Miss”.
The word used for clothes is  &lt;em&gt;youfuku&lt;/em&gt; 洋服, Western clothes, but I feel that is purely for the benefit of the Japanese audience, so I would just translate it as “clothes”.
The climate is definitely not Scotland but not specifically Japan either, nor is the vegetation that is mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is carefully unspecific, at least in the initial chapters. It made me wonder if there was any benefit at all in reading it in Japanese. The translation is excellent, it was shortlisted for the Booker Prize 2020. And yet, I find the Japanese very beautiful and I think impossible to convey entirely in translation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The translator, Stephen Snyder, &lt;a href=&quot;https://shelfmediagroup.com/interview/interview-stephen-snyder-translator-for-the-memory-police-by-yoko-ogawa/&quot;&gt;says in an interview&lt;/a&gt;: “Yoko Ogawa’s prose in Japanese is extraordinarily beautiful, so it’s always a challenge to try to find a way to capture even a vague sense of that beauty in English.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I just like reading Japanese, slowly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While reading I noted down some typical Japanese cultural elements that caught my eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Indented sentences are quotes. English quotes in italics are from the translation by Stephen Snyder, other translations are mine.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;roses&quot;&gt;Roses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For about the first quarter of the novel, there are no Japan-specific references, but then, in Chapter 6, with the disappearance of the roses, there was one after all: primary school kids with &lt;em&gt;randoseru&lt;/em&gt; ランドセル , firm-sided school backpacks made of leather. A less specific word would have been 学生鞄 &lt;em&gt;gakusei kaban&lt;/em&gt; (school bag). The word &lt;em&gt;randoseru&lt;/em&gt; derives from the Dutch “ransel”; they are very typical for Japanese schoolkids. Still, when I was in primary school in Flanders, I had one too, with a slightly different shape, wider and less deep; we just called it “boekentas” (book bag). I loved the sound the clasps made. And when you ran with it on, the books and pens etc would rattle inside, which is exactly what the writer describes as well:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The children took off running along the river, their backpacks rattling behind them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;子供たちはランドセルを鳴らしながら、流れを追いかけていった。&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;kodomotachi ha RANDOSERU wo narashinagara, nagare wo oikakete itta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;With rattling school bags, the kids went chasing the flow.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And another, perhaps less obvious, cultural reference, occurs at the start of Chapter 7:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At the base of the bridge next to my laundry platform stood an elegantly dressed woman. &lt;br /&gt; “What lovely roses,” I told her.&lt;br /&gt;This was the first thing that came to mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;洗濯場にかかる橋のたもとにも、お金持ち風の婦人が一人、たたずんでいた。&lt;br /&gt;「気品のあるバラですね」わたしは言った。&lt;br /&gt;それでふと頭に浮かんだ修飾語を、そのまま口にしたのだった&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;sentakujo ni kakaru hashi no tamoto ni mo, okanemochi fuu no fujin ga hitori, tatazunde ita.&lt;br /&gt;“kihin no aru bara desu ne” watashi ha itta.&lt;br /&gt;sore de futo atama ni ukanda shoushokugo wo, sono mama kuchi ni shita no datta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “What lovely roses” in Japanese is “&lt;em&gt;kihin no aru bara desu ne&lt;/em&gt;” (what elegant roses), and the narrator comments on her random choice of “&lt;em&gt;kihin no aru&lt;/em&gt;”  with the term &lt;em&gt;shoushokugo&lt;/em&gt; 修飾語 which is the general grammatical term for “modifier” (she is after all a novelist). That is because it is an adjectival sentence rather than an adjective (“roses that have elegance”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Once her work was done, she turned and, without a glance at the stream, gave me the sort of graceful bow typical of people of her class and left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;すべての作業が終わると婦人は、川の流れを目で追い掛けようともせず、上流階級の人独特のゆったりとしたお辞儀をして、わたしから離れていった。&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;subete no sagyou ga owaru to fujin ha, kawa no nagare wo me de oikake you to mo sezu, jouryuukaikyuu no hito dokutoku no yuttari shita ojigi wo shite, watashi kara hanarete itta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “graceful bow” is a &lt;em&gt;jiki&lt;/em&gt; 辞儀, a bow accompanying a greeting, rather than &lt;em&gt;rei&lt;/em&gt; 礼, a bow to thank someone. The narrator uses the words &lt;em&gt;jouryuukaikyuu no hito&lt;/em&gt; 上流階級の人 (upper class person) and &lt;em&gt;yuttari to shita&lt;/em&gt; ゆったりとした (easy, leisurely) bow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iriko&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Iriko&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Chapter 8, where R visits the narrator’s mother’s workshop in the basement, the narrator recalls her mother eating &lt;em&gt;iriko&lt;/em&gt; イリコ (also written 炒り子). This is quite specific: the term is only used in the West of Japan (and also in Hawaii, because of immigrants from Western Japan). It refers to Japanese anchovy fry  (&lt;em&gt;kataguchi-iwashi&lt;/em&gt;, 片口鰯), boiled in brine and then dried. In the rest of Japan they are called &lt;em&gt;niboshi&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;jako&lt;/em&gt;. The writer was born in Okayama, Okayama Prefecture in Kansai, so that is probably why she uses the word &lt;em&gt;iriko&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;niboshi&lt;/em&gt;. To translate it in a culturally context-free way, you could of course just say dried anchovies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“My mother always kept dried sardines wrapped in newspaper on the desk in her studio, and she would snack on them as she worked.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;「母は仕事場の机に、いつも新聞紙にくるんだイリコを置いていたんです。それをムシャムシャ食べながら仕事をしていたの。」&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;haha ha shigotoba no tsukue ni, itsumo shinbungami ni kurunda IRIKO wo oite itandesu. sore wo MUSHAMUSHA tabenagara shigoto wo shite ita no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-secret-police-does-not-take-prisoners&quot;&gt;The Secret Police does not take prisoners&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Chapter 13, the narrator is at the head office of the secret police and talking to a kind of receptionist. She says 「差し入れ」 (&lt;em&gt;“sashiire”&lt;/em&gt;) and the person she’s talking to says 「さしいれ？」(&lt;em&gt;“sashiire?”&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word 差し入れ (sashi-ire) has the following meanings:
(1) Insertion, letter drop.
(2) Things sent to a prisoner.
(3) Supply of provisions, refreshments, etc. to someone carrying out a task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the novel the meaning is clearly “Things sent to a prisoner”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subtext is that the receptionist pretends not to understand this word (because of course the secret police does not take &lt;em&gt;prisoners&lt;/em&gt;).
The use of &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt; for this word normally written in &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; makes that very clear, but is difficult to bring across in translation: use of italics or quotes do not have quite the same effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I have a package I’d like to have delivered to an acquaintance…” My voice trailed off, echoing from the ceiling before being lost in the vastness of the hall.&lt;br /&gt;
    “Package?” He paused, twirling his pen in his fingers, and repeated the word as though trying to recall the meaning of some rarely used philosophical term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kanji-and-the-latin-alphabet&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kanji&lt;/em&gt; and the Latin alphabet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second chapter of the novel, the narrator refers to her father’s documents about birds with containing “”鳥”という 字” (&lt;em&gt;“tori” to iu ji&lt;/em&gt;). You can translate that as “the word ‘bird’, but  although &lt;em&gt;ji&lt;/em&gt;  can mean “word”, it usually means “character” and is anyhow more specific than &lt;em&gt;kotoba&lt;/em&gt; (word).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When they came upon something they considered dangerous—in other words, anything that contained the word “bird”—they threw the item unceremoniously on the floor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;危険とみなされたものはーーつまりどこかに一つでも”鳥”という字がみつかったものはーーどんどん床に放り投げられていった。&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;kiken to minasareta mono ha – tsumari nanika hitotsu demo “tori” to iu ji ga mitsukatta mono ha – dondon yuka ni　hourinagerarete itta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the third chapter there is a scene of the narrator writing a novel, and she describes the typical &lt;em&gt;genkouyoushi&lt;/em&gt; 原稿用紙,  i.e “paper for manuscripts”, Japanese writing paper lined with a square grid, one square per character. Of course as a translator you could just say “writing paper”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in Chapter 14 there is a scene where the narrator, still in the HQ of the secret police, mentions specifically that someone is writing using the alphabet (&lt;em&gt;arufabetto&lt;/em&gt; アルファベット ):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;His papers were thickly covered with numbers and letters in a script I did not understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;書類には意味のよく分らない数字やアルファベットが、びっしり書き込んであった。&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;shorui ni ha imi no yoku wakaranai suuji ya ARUFABETTO ga, bisshiri kakikonde atta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I would have translated the earlier kanji-specific terms in a generic way, then I would have to say&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The forms were densely filled in with numbers and letters the meaning of which I didn&apos;t understand very well&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whereas if I had been specific about the earlier writing being in kanji, I could translate&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The forms were densely filled in with numbers and  characters in the latin alphabet, the meaning of which I didn&apos;t understand very well&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does not matter much of course, but in the latter case the story would be more clearly set in Japan than in the former.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;onomatopoeic-and-mimetic-words&quot;&gt;Onomatopoeic and mimetic words&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an aside, Japanese has many words with the structure like the word &lt;em&gt;bisshiri&lt;/em&gt; びっしり (densely written) used in that sentence: four &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt; characters, the second a small &lt;em&gt;tsu&lt;/em&gt; っ which indicates a glottal stop, and the last one &lt;em&gt;ri&lt;/em&gt; り. For example, &lt;em&gt;bikkuri&lt;/em&gt;　(surprised, frightened), &lt;em&gt;tappuri&lt;/em&gt; (plentiful), &lt;em&gt;sappari&lt;/em&gt; (feeling refreshed) etc.　Someone at made an attempt to enumerate them and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www1.kcn.ne.jp/~bamba/tips/XxXX.html&quot;&gt;counted 158 of them&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Institute for Japanese Language and Linguistics says that 103 of these words with pattern AっBり are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.ninjal.ac.jp/Onomatope/column/nihongo_2.html&quot;&gt;onomatopoeic and mimetic words&lt;/a&gt;. Japanese has about two thousand of these onomatopoeic and mimetic words; there are many forms but the most common is ABAB (like &lt;em&gt;wakuwaku&lt;/em&gt; わくわく, nervous, trembling, excited; or &lt;em&gt;mushamusha&lt;/em&gt; ムシャムシャ, munching); the pattern ABり (like &lt;em&gt;shikiri&lt;/em&gt; しきり, frequent, continual) is also quite common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yoko Ogawa makes liberal use of such words and it is one of the aspects that is hard to convey in translation, especially the mimetic words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- Nothing in Chapters 9, 10 , 11, 12? --&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;baumkuchen&quot;&gt;Baumkuchen&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of Chapter 13 is a very specific Japanese cultural reference, the mention of &lt;em&gt;baumukuuhen&lt;/em&gt; バウムクーヘン, “Baumkuchen”. This is a kind of cake of German origin that looks like a cross-section of a tree trunk with a hole in the middle, as it is baked on a spit. It is very popular in Japan. I used to buy them in the &lt;em&gt;konbini&lt;/em&gt; to have with my coffee. And it is specifically popular as a gift to guests at weddings, which is exactly the case in the novel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“My parents had come home from the wedding, but neither of them seemed to realize that I’d slept the entire day. They were animated and wanted me to taste the cake they had brought home from the reception.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;「両親が結婚式から帰ってきたんです。二人ともわたしが眠り続けていたことに、気づきもしませんでした。さあ、お土産のバウムクーヘンを食べましょうなんて、うきうきしているだけなんです」&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“ryoushin ga kekkonshiki kara kaette kitandesu. futari tomo watashi ga nemuritsdzukete ita koto ni, kidzuki mo shimasen deshita. saa, omiyage no BAUMUKUUHEN wo tabemashou nante, ukiuki shite iru data nandesu”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If as a translator I wanted to avoid the cultural reference I could replace it by “wedding cake”, and that would at least work in Anglo-Saxon countries. In other countries where guests don’t get to take a piece of cake home (like in Flanders), the text gives me a way out because it refers to the Baumkuchen as &lt;em&gt;omiyage&lt;/em&gt; (お土産, local specialty or souvenir bought as a gift while travelling) so I could simply call it “the local speciality cake” or something similar.　&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the whole, if I were to translate this novel, I think I would prefer to keep the few Japanese cultural references as they are. It would fit better with other culturally specific elements such as the politeness levels, which it would be rather a shame to remove entirely in translation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;loanwords&quot;&gt;Loanwords&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Japanese has a lot of loanwords that are written in &lt;em&gt;katakana&lt;/em&gt;. Most of them are from American English, to the extent that it is a running joke that you can speak Japanese with only &lt;em&gt;katakana&lt;/em&gt;-English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am generally more interested in the &lt;em&gt;katakana&lt;/em&gt; loanwords that are not from English. In this novel there are quite a few. I already mentioned &lt;em&gt;randoseru&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;baumukuuhen&lt;/em&gt;. Other examples are &lt;em&gt;mesu&lt;/em&gt; メス from Dutch “mes” – Japanese meaning “scalpel”, Dutch meaning knife; &lt;em&gt;kokku&lt;/em&gt; コック from Dutch “kok”, “cook”; &lt;em&gt;karute&lt;/em&gt; カルテ from German &lt;em&gt;Karte&lt;/em&gt; – Japanese meaning “clinical record”, German meaning “card”; and &lt;em&gt;noruma&lt;/em&gt; ノルマ from Russian “norma” – Japanese meaning “quota”, Russian meaning “norm”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like such words because they relate to Japan’s history, for example Japan imported the German medical system in the 19th century; the Baumkuchen were created by a German baker, an ex-prisoner-of-war, for the Hiroshima Prefectural Commercial Exhibition in 1919. The Dutch words are even older as they were one of the few nations allowed to trade with Japan in the Tokugawa era (early 1600s), together with the Portuguese from which amongst others パン “pan”, bread was loaned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the novel, the bread is usually ロールパ &lt;em&gt;roorupan&lt;/em&gt; which means “breadroll”, the &lt;em&gt;rooru&lt;/em&gt; (roll) borrowed from English, or &lt;em&gt;furansupan&lt;/em&gt; フランスパン “French bread”. In common Japanese, the most common word is &lt;em&gt;shokupan&lt;/em&gt; 食パン which is typically a white square loaf; &lt;em&gt;shoku&lt;/em&gt; just means “food”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An English loanword that is interesting from a translation perspective is ショートケーキ &lt;em&gt;shootokeeki&lt;/em&gt;, “shortcake”, because this is a typical American cake also popular in Japan. If I were translate this novel into Dutch with Japanese cultural references I would leave it as “shortcake”; but it’s a type of cake not so well known in Flanders so otherwise I would probably use “gâteau” as that is a similar cake for a Flemish audience. (And yes, that is a loanword from French into Flemish.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- That section from Ch 13 is not in the online book?  --&gt;
&lt;!-- Nothning in 15? --&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cherry-blossoms&quot;&gt;Cherry blossoms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there was still any doubt about the Japanese setting of the novel, the following sentence in Chapter 16 puts an end to that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Even if we couldn’t recall the exact date, I knew that his came around every year just as the cherry blossoms were budding out. I was quite certain that time was fast approaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;日付けは思い出せなくても、毎年桜がわずかに開き始める季節だったことは確かで、
そろそろそういう時期が近づいてきたという予感は間違いなくするのだった。&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;nittsuke ha omoidasenakute, mainen sakura ga wazuka ni hirakihajimeru kisetsu datta koto ha tashika de, sorosoro sou iu jiki ga chikadzuite kita tou iu yokan ha machigainaku suru no datta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;Even though I couldn&apos;t remember the date anymore, it was certainly around the time when every year the cherry blossoms just started to open, and I had the unmistakeable premonition that that season was soon drawing near.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;sakura&lt;/em&gt;, cherry blossoms, are quintessentially Japanese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;music-box&quot;&gt;Music box&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Chapter 16, another nice loanword appears, again from Dutch: &lt;em&gt;orugooru&lt;/em&gt; オルゴール  from “orgel”, meaning music box. The word “orgel” literally means organ. The mechanism for music boxes were initially based on the barrel organ, “draaiorgel” in Dutch. According to Kotobank, the first mention in Japanese is in a publication from 1750.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scene where this &lt;em&gt;orugooru&lt;/em&gt; is introduced is one of my favourite scenes in the novel. Such a nice description of the emotions that listening to the melody played by a music box evokes. It is all the more poignant because the narrotor and the old man have no memory of music boxes anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the two Japanese words kept in the English translation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It’s not really magic,” R said. “It’s an orugooru.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;「魔術だなて大げさなものじゃありません。これはオルゴールです」R氏が言った。&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“majutsu da nante oogesa na mono ja arimasen. kore ha ORUGOORU desu” R-shi ga itta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yamato-and-wa&quot;&gt;Yamato and &lt;em&gt;wa&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Chapter 19, there is an explicit reference to Japan:  &lt;em&gt;washitsu&lt;/em&gt; 和室, Japanese-style room. The character 和 (&lt;em&gt;wa&lt;/em&gt;) means both harmony, peace and Japan, Japanese-style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Needless to say, I offered them the Japanese-style room on the first floor, as far as possible from the hidden room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;もちろんわたしは一階の和室ーー隠し部屋から一番遠い部屋ーーを提供してあげた。&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;mochiron watashi ha ikkai no washitsu – kakushiheya kara ichiban tooi heya – wo teikyou ageta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story behind the use of this character to mean Japan is quite interesting. Long ago, Japan was called Yamato. Originally, that was a region in what is now Nara prefecture, where the first capital was. Eventually it came to mean all of Japan. (Later it came to be called Nihon (日本) but that’s another story; as is why it’s called “Japan” in English.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the 3th century CE,  the Japanese adopted the Chinese writing system and until the 7th century, “Yamato” was written 倭,  the character the Chinese had been using for a long time to refer to the inhabitants of the  Japanese islands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I explained earlier, most kanji have two types of readings, “onyomi”, which is based on the Japanese rendition of the ancient Chinese pronunciation of a character, and kunyomi, which is the native Japanese reading. The kunyomi for 倭　is &lt;em&gt;yamato&lt;/em&gt;; the onyomi is &lt;em&gt;wa&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then at the start of the Nara period, in 713 CE, the empress Genmei decreed that Yamato (and in fact all important place names) should be written with two “auspicious characters”. Therefore 倭 was prefixed with the character 大, “great”. So it became 大倭,  pronounced in full Ooyamato but usually just Yamato.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, for reasons lost in time, later in the Nara period, 倭 became replaced with 和 which has the same onyomi (&lt;em&gt;wa&lt;/em&gt;), but also means “peace, harmony”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both writings coexisted for a long time but eventually 大和 became the preferred writing. And so now 和 &lt;em&gt;wa&lt;/em&gt; is used to mean “Japanese”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;writing-practice&quot;&gt;Writing practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Chapter 20, the narrator writes out a series of characters. The sequence she writes is the first two rows of the standard organisation for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hiragana#Writing_system&quot;&gt;the Japanese syllabary&lt;/a&gt;, a table with ten rows and five columns, one colum for each vowel sound and one row for each starting consonant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To warm up my fingers, I tried writing a, i, u, e, o. Then, taking care to match the size of the characters to the lines on the paper, I continued with ka, ki, ku, ke, ko.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;指慣らしのために最初、あ、い、う、え、お、と書いて見る。ますめと字の大きさのバランスを確かめながら、か、き、く、け、こと続ける。&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;yubinarashi no tame ni sasho, a, i, u, e, o to kaite miru. masume to ji no ookisa no BARANSU wo tashikamenagara, ka, ki, ku, ke, ko to tsudzukeru.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word &lt;em&gt;masume&lt;/em&gt; means a square on Japanese manuscript paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-childrens-game-and-candy&quot;&gt;A childrens’ game and candy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the later chapters, there are more specifically Japanese references, for example in Chapter 22, there is a mention of おはじき &lt;em&gt;ohajiki&lt;/em&gt;, a traditional Japanese children’s game similar to marbles, played with coin-shaped pieces made of coloured glass or plastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So I sounded out the children’s songs my nurse had taught me or the tune we had used to count for tiddlywinks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;仕方ないで、昔ばあやさんが歌ってくれた子守歌や、おはじきの数え歌をただただしく吹いた。&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;shikatanai de, mukashi baayasan ga utatte kureta komoriuta ya, ohajiki no kazoeuta wo tadatadashiku fuita.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a mention of　&lt;em&gt;ramune&lt;/em&gt; ラムネ, fizzy soda candy, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.morinaga.co.jp/ramune/&quot;&gt;typical Japanese type of candy&lt;/a&gt;. This is the only other place in the novel where the translator has kept a Japanese word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Is it medicine?” I asked. &lt;br /&gt; “No, it’s called &lt;em&gt;ramune&lt;/em&gt;. I’m impressed that your mother tried to preserve something as ordinary as this.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;「何かの薬かしら」わたしは言った。&lt;br /&gt;
「いいや。ラムネだよ。君のお母さんはこんなささやかな物まで、大事に取っていたんだね」&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“nanika no kusuri kashira” watashi ha itta.&lt;br /&gt;“iiya. RAMUNE da yo. kimi no okaasan ha konna sasayaka no mono made, daiji ni totteitanda ne”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And further:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It’s a lemon-flavored candy. When we were children, all the stores sold them and there were countless &lt;em&gt;ramune&lt;/em&gt; on the island, but now there are only these few left here.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;「砂糖菓子さ。子供の頃はお店にいくらでも売っていた。島中には数えきれないくらいのラムネがあった。でも今残っているのは、ここにある数粒だけだ」&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“satoukashi sa. kodomo no goro ha omise ni ikurademo utteita. touchuu ni ha kazoekirenaikurai no RAMUNE ga atta. demo ima nokotte iru no ha, koko ni aru suutsubu dake da”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Japanese word &lt;em&gt;satoukashi&lt;/em&gt; 砂糖菓子 means simply “sugar candy”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;trains&quot;&gt;Trains&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 23 features a train journey. Train is normally  &lt;em&gt;densha&lt;/em&gt; 電車 which literally means “electric vehicle”, but the novel always uses &lt;em&gt;kisha&lt;/em&gt; 汽車 “train, esp. long distance, but originally steam train” (&lt;em&gt;ki&lt;/em&gt; means steam). And as it mentions a whistle, I think it is actually a steam train.&lt;br /&gt;
The other word used is  &lt;em&gt;ressha&lt;/em&gt; 列車 the term for “train” used by the railway companies; &lt;em&gt;retsu&lt;/em&gt; means “file”, so it is literally a file of cars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are mentions of several types trains:  &lt;em&gt;kyuukou&lt;/em&gt; 急行 “express” and  &lt;em&gt;tokkyuu&lt;/em&gt; 特急 “limited express” (faster than an express) and also of the  &lt;em&gt;kaisatsuguchi&lt;/em&gt; 改札口, ticket gates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trains are of course universal but this terminology is quite specific to the Japanese railway system. Also, for me personally, it evokes memories of taking the train in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-hands-of-the-old-man-made-many-things&quot;&gt;The hands of the old man made many things&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Chapter 24 there is a beautiful description of the hands of the old man, with a list of objects his hands had made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have always loved his hands, from the time I was a little girl. They could make almost anything: a toy box, a plastic model, a cage for a rhinoceros beetle, a beanbag, a desk lamp, a bicycle seat cover, smoked fish, an apple cake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;子供の頃から、わたしはおじいさんの手が大好きだった。みんなで一緒に出掛ける時は、いつでもおじいさんと手をつないだ。それはおもちゃ箱や、自動車のプラモデルや、カブト虫の飼育箱や、お手玉や、電気スタンドや、自転車のサドルカバーや、魚の燻製や、リンゴケーキや、とにかく何でも作り出すことができる。&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;kodomo no goro kara, watashi ha ojiisan no te ga suki datta. minna de issho ni dekakeru toki ha, itsudemo ojiisan no te wo tusnaida. sore ha omochabako, jidousha no PURAMODERU ya, KABUTOmushi no shiikubako ya, otedama ya, deki SUTANDO ya, jitensha no SADORUKABAA ya, sakana no kunsei ya, RINGOKEEKI ya, tonikaku nandemo tsukuridasu koto ga dekiru.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these are very typical: カブト虫の飼育箱 &lt;em&gt;kabutomushi no shiikubako&lt;/em&gt;,  a cage for rearing a Japanese rhinoceros beetle;　お手玉 &lt;em&gt;otedama&lt;/em&gt;  (translated above as “beanbag”) are &lt;a href=&quot;https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%81%8A%E6%89%8B%E7%8E%89&quot;&gt;balls of colourful fabric filled with rice or beans&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a small phrase left untranslated:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;みんなで一緒に出掛ける時は、いつでもおじいさんと手をつないだ。&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;minna de issho ni dekakeru toki ha, itsudemo ojiisan no te wo tusnaida&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;no-italic&quot;&gt;When we all went out together, I was always holding the old man&apos;s hand.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t work so well in English because for the narrator, &lt;em&gt;ojiisan&lt;/em&gt; is a term of endearment, and “the old man” does not carry that connotation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, there are very few explicit Japanese cultural references in the original novel, only about one for every two chapters. It’s interesting to see that the English translation keeps enough of them that the Japanese setting of the novel is still clear to the attentive reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The banner picture shows green tea Baumkuchen in a shop in Kyoto.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Parsnip pizza</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/parsnip-pizza/"/>
        <updated>2021-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/parsnip-pizza</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/parsnip-pizza_1600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;This is a traditional thin-crust pizza with a non-traditional topping: parsnips seasoned with tomato purée, tobanjan and garlic oil. It is easy to make but takes some time as the dough has to rise for two hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fermented broad bean paste (called &lt;em&gt;doubanjiang&lt;/em&gt; in Chinese, &lt;em&gt;tobanjan&lt;/em&gt; in Japanese) is a key ingredient, as it adds both umami and spicyness to the parsnips. Make sure to check the ingredients as there are many types of chilli bean paste and a lot of them are not vegetarian. The Chinese characters are 豆瓣酱. If it says 辛豆瓣酱 then it will be very spicy. The brand I got is Pearl River Bridge Chilli Bean Paste.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What I call tomato purée is called tomato paste in the US.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegetarian&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegetarian&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;600 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#400-600kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_2.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for the base
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;130 g white flour (I use half “00” pasta flour and half bread flour)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;80 ml water&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;7 g dried yeast&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 g salt&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for the toppings
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 pack (250 g) of mozarella slices&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;200 g parsnips&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;100 g chestnut mushrooms&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;a handful of dried funghi porcini&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;50 g grated parmezan or grana padano&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons pine nuts&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon tomato purée&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon garlic oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/2 teaspoon tobanjan&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;making-the-dough&quot;&gt;Making the dough&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put all ingredients in a pot and mix them, then knead until you have a smooth dough.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let the dough rest, covered, for one hour.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knead the though gently for a second time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let it rest, covered, for another hour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;the-toppings&quot;&gt;The toppings&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soak the porcini mushrooms for 30 minutes in freshly boiled water.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wash and peel the parsnips and slice them as thinly as possibly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cook the parsnips in the microwave at 900 W for 3 minutes 30 seconds.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put the cooking liquid in a broad, shallow bowl and add the tomato puree, garlic oil and tobanjan. Mix into a smooth paste.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the cooked parsnips and mix so they are evenly covered with the seasoning.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Slice the mushrooms as thinly as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;making-the-pizza&quot;&gt;Making the pizza&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I make a rectangular pizza on a baking tray covered with baking paper.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I don’t use a rolling pin but flatten the dough by pushing with my fingers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Preheat the oven at 250 ºC.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the pizza base is ready, cover it with the mozarella slices, parsnips and mushrooms.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have a hot air oven so I bake the pizza for 5 minutes, then turn, then bake it for another 5 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take the pizza out of the oven.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the porcini mushrooms, pine kernels and grated hard cheese.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put the pizza back in the oven and bake for another 3 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Aubergine salad</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/aubergine-salad/"/>
        <updated>2021-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/aubergine-salad</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/aubergine-salad_1600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;This is a nice summery salad of aubergines, chick peas and fresh mushrooms, served with Japanese rice in a separate bowl. It’s very simple, the secret is in the dressing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegan&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#gluten-free&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;gluten-free&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#30-minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;30-minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;600 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#400-600kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_2.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Main ingredients
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tin of chick peas&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;100 g fresh mushrooms&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;300 g aubergines&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cup Japanese rice&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ingredients for the dressing:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon chopped ginger&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon tomato puree&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon tobanjan (chilli bean sauce)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon vinegar&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon soy sauce&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon yuzu juice&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon garlic oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;3 tablespoons pumpkin seeds ground in a mortar&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the cooking liquid from the aubergines&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/basics/#toc0&quot;&gt;Cook the rice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wash the chick peas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wash and dice the aubergines and cook them for 12 minutes in the microwave at 900 W.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Slice the mushrooms.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put the chick peas, cooked aubergines and mushrooms in a bowl and add the dressing. Mix well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Serve the rice in a separate bowl.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>The mystery of the giant Kannon statues</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/kannon/"/>
        <updated>2021-05-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/kannon</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/kannon_1600x600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;Some time ago I stumbled across an intriguing random fact: of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_tallest_statues&quot;&gt;fifty tallest statues in the world&lt;/a&gt;, fourteen are of the Buddha but eighteen are of a being called &lt;em&gt;Kannon&lt;/em&gt; in Japanese (&lt;em&gt;Guanyin&lt;/em&gt; in Chinese). Thirteen of these tallest statues are in Japan and twelve of these are  Kannon statues (the other is a statue of the Buddha).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So who is this Kannon, and why are some many of the tall statues of it, in particular in Japan?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, there is little mystery in the tall statues themselves. They are almost invariably built either as tourist attractions or as war memorials. What is more interesting though is why so many of them represent the Kannon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;buddha-and-bodhisattva&quot;&gt;Buddha and Bodhisattva&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buddhism originated in India sometime between the sixth and fourth century BCE, and spread to Japan via China in the first half of the sixth century CE. By that time, it had already developed a long tradition and forked into several branches. There are three major  schools of Buddhism: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.namchak.org/community/blog/three-different-paths-theravada-mahayana-and-vajrayana/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Theravada&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Mahāyāna&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Vajrayana&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general in Buddhism, a &lt;em&gt;bodhisattva&lt;/em&gt; (a sentient being, &lt;em&gt;sattva&lt;/em&gt; , that develops enlightenment, &lt;em&gt;bodhi&lt;/em&gt;) is any person who is on the path towards Buddhahood. Specifically in Mahāyāna Buddhism, a bodhisattva refers to anyone who has developed a mind that strives toward awakening (attaining Buddhahood), empathy, and compassion for the benefit of all sentient beings. (This is known as &lt;em&gt;bodhicitta&lt;/em&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;kannon&quot;&gt;Kannon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Japanese, &lt;em&gt;bodhisattva&lt;/em&gt; are know as &lt;em&gt;bosatsu&lt;/em&gt; (菩薩). One &lt;em&gt;bosatsu&lt;/em&gt; that is especially popular is &lt;em&gt;Kannon&lt;/em&gt; (観音). The word is a contraction of &lt;em&gt;Kanzeon&lt;/em&gt; (観世音), which in its turn is the most commonly used translation of the bodhisattva known in Sanskrit as &lt;em&gt;Avalokiteśvara&lt;/em&gt;. Kannon is the bodhisattva associated with compassion. The name means “[The One Who] Perceives (観) the Sounds (音) of the World (世).”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sanskrit term was originally &lt;em&gt;Avalokitasvara&lt;/em&gt; with the ending &lt;em&gt;svara&lt;/em&gt; (“sound, noise”), which means “sound perceiver”, literally “he who looks down upon sound” (i.e., the cries of sentient beings who need his help).  Over time, the name changed to Avalokiteśvara. The ending &lt;em&gt;īśvara&lt;/em&gt; means “lord”, so the meaning became “lord who gazes down (at the world)”, but &lt;em&gt;kannon&lt;/em&gt; retains the original meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bodhisattva is also referred to as Padmapāṇi (“Holder of the Lotus”) or Lokeśvara (“Lord of the World”). In Tibetan, Avalokiteśvara is known as Chenrézig and the Dalai Lama is considered the reincarnation of Chenrézig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, Kannon is the bodhisattva of infinite compassion who gazes down at the human world,
hears all the cries of suffering, and works tirelessly to help those who call upon its name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gender of Kannon is rather vague (I will explain that below) so in what follows I will use the pronouns “they/them” to refer to Kannon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;buddhism-in-japan&quot;&gt;Buddhism in Japan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of Japan, Japanese Buddhism is usually associated with Zen Buddhism, but there are many different Buddhist sects in Japan, and Zen sects are actually a minority.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tofugu.com/japan/japanese-buddhism/&quot;&gt;This Tofugu article&lt;/a&gt; gives a good overview. The dominant form of Buddhism in Japan is Mahāyāna: of the main thirteen sects, eleven are Mahāyāna, including the three Zen sects; only the Ritsu (Theravāda) and Shingon (Vajrayana) sects are not Mahāyāna.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Mahāyāna (and Vajrayana) Buddhism, several Buddhas are venerated that are not found in early Buddhism or in Theravada Buddhism. They are considered to be living in other realms, known as “Pure Lands” (&lt;em&gt;Jōdo&lt;/em&gt; 浄土), and are sometimes called “celestial Buddhas” as they are not of this earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important of these is Amitābha (&lt;em&gt;Amida&lt;/em&gt; 阿弥陀, “Buddha of Infinite Light”). This is the principal deity of worship for the Pure Land Buddhist sect and sects that derive from this tradition. Kannon is a spiritual emanation of Amida Buddha and therefore occupies a major place in the pantheon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kannon is mentioned in numerous Mahāyāna sutra (religious texts), but especially in Chapter 25 of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://buddhasutra.com/files/lotus_sutra.htm&quot;&gt;Lotus Sutra&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Hokekyō&lt;/em&gt; 法華経). Because they are the bodhisattva of  of infinite compassion, they became the favourite deity.
Today, Kannon worship is very widespread and essentially non-denominational. Their statues are everywhere, and there are hundreds of pilgrimage routes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gender&quot;&gt;Gender&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://buddhasutra.com/files/lotus_sutra.htm&quot;&gt;Lotus Sutra&lt;/a&gt; describes Avalokiteśvara (Kannon) as a bodhisattva who can take the form of any type of god, any type of Buddha, as well as any gender, adult or child, human or non-human being, in order to teach the Dharma to sentient beings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avalokiteśvara was originally depicted as a male bodhisattva and sometimes even has a light moustache. Although this depiction still exists, in modern times Kannon is more often depicted as a woman or as an  androgynous figure. According to the doctrines of the Mahāyāna sūtras themselves, it does not matter whether Kannon is male, female, or genderless, as the ultimate reality is in emptiness (&lt;em&gt;kū&lt;/em&gt; 空, śūnyatā).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;manifestations&quot;&gt;Manifestations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A total of 33 different manifestations of Kannon are described in Chapter 25 of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://buddhasutra.com/files/lotus_sutra.htm&quot;&gt;Lotus Sutra&lt;/a&gt; depending on whatever a living being needs to be saved. One might think that 33 different forms would be plenty. However, when we look at the Kannon statues, we find that some are indeed part of these 33:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Byakue Kannon (白衣観音, White-robed Kannon), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aisf.or.jp/~jaanus/deta/b/byakuekannon.htm&quot;&gt;“A persistent femininity clings to this kannon even though the figure is shown as a male.”&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/ryozen_kannon_kyoto.avif&quot; alt=&quot;A white statue of a seated kannon.&quot; title=&quot;A white statue of a seated kannon.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Ryōzen Kannon 霊山観音 of Kyoto, a Byakue Kannon.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Guze (救世 , salvation or Shou 聖, holy), a male Kannon. The most famous Guze Kannon statue can be found in the Hōryū-ji Temple (法隆寺) in Nara. It was made in the image of prince Shōtoku Taishi (聖徳太子), the first great patron of Buddhism in Japan, in the early 7th Century. Many statues are copies of this one.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gyouran (魚籃, Kannon carrying a fish basket), a female Kannon. There is an &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.mindvalley.com/fish-basket/&quot;&gt;interesting story about this kannon&lt;/a&gt; (and &lt;a href=&quot;http://buddhasutra.com/stories/origin_fish_basket_holding_guanyin.htm&quot;&gt;the same story as a comic&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ideal.accelerate-ed.com/pub/a/em/-/lo/cebf7683-740a-4f67-8ba8-921ac4fd4cb2/p/40ed4d52-d4aa-467d-8ef9-37bc4279321b&quot;&gt;another nice one&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are also some that are not part of the 33 canonical ones:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jibō Kannon (慈母, loving mother), a female Kannon holding a baby, patron of motherhood ans children (&lt;em&gt;koyasu&lt;/em&gt; 子安), and both protect the souls of aborted or stillborn children (&lt;em&gt;mizuko&lt;/em&gt; 水子). Despite not being in the canon, this is a very popular Kannon.
    &lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/aizu_jibo_daikannon.avif&quot; alt=&quot;A white statue of a standing kannon.&quot; title=&quot;A white statue of a standing kannon.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Jibō Daikannon of Aizu.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Heiwa Kannon (平和 eternal piece), usually male or androgynous, to to pray for world peace and commemorate the war dead. Most of these were built in the 1950s but an interesting example from 1997 is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://impressionsofeastasia.com/2013/04/16/the-unfortunate-history-of-the-whiplash-kannon-and-heiwakannon-ji/&quot;&gt;Awaji Heiwa Kannon&lt;/a&gt;. Some of the Kannon dedicated to world piece are Byakue, like the Ryōzen Kannon above and the Ofuna Kannon in Kamakura.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maria Kannon (マリア観音, Virgin Mary), a female Kannon. Christianity was banned in Japan during the Tokugawa Era (1615-1867). In the 17th century, the Japanese crypto-Christians created statues of the Virgin Mary disguised as Kannon. These effigies, called Maria Kannon, looked like Jibō Kannon but they were venerated by the Christians silently praying to Mother Mary. Many of the statues had a Christian icon hidden inside the body or in the artwork.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I consulted many references for this post but these are the most noteworthy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_tallest_statues&quot;&gt;“List of tallest statues”, Wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E5%B7%A8%E5%A4%A7%E4%BB%8F&quot;&gt;「巨大仏」Wikipedia page on large Buddha and Kannon statues, in Japanese&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.namchak.org/community/blog/three-different-paths-theravada-mahayana-and-vajrayana/&quot;&gt;“Three different paths: Theravada, Mahāyāna, and Vajrayana”, Lama Tsomo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tofugu.com/japan/japanese-buddhism/&quot;&gt;“The Real Japanese Monk’s Guide To Buddhism In Japan”, Mami Suzuki&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.onmarkproductions.com/html/kannon.shtml&quot;&gt;“Kannon Notebook”, Mark Schumacher&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://impressionsofeastasia.com/2013/04/16/the-unfortunate-history-of-the-whiplash-kannon-and-heiwakannon-ji/&quot;&gt;“The unfortunate history of the “Whiplash Kannon” and Heiwakannon-ji”, Austin Smith&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aisf.or.jp/~jaanus/deta/b/byakuekannon.htm&quot;&gt;“Byakue Kannon 白衣観音”, Japanese Architecture and Art Net Users System&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://knight.as.cornell.edu/kannon-figure-bodhisattva-japanese-buddhism-steven-gump&quot;&gt;“Kannon: Figure of the Bodhisattva in Japanese Buddhism “, Steven Gump&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://buddhasutra.com/files/lotus_sutra.htm&quot;&gt;“The Lotus Sutra”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.mindvalley.com/fish-basket/&quot;&gt;“The Buddhist Legend Of The Fish Basket”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://buddhasutra.com/stories/origin_fish_basket_holding_guanyin.htm&quot;&gt;“The Origin Of Fish Basket Holding Guan Yin” (comic) &lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ideal.accelerate-ed.com/pub/a/em/-/lo/cebf7683-740a-4f67-8ba8-921ac4fd4cb2/p/40ed4d52-d4aa-467d-8ef9-37bc4279321b&quot;&gt;“The Fish Basket Goddess: A Tale from Ancient China”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The banner picture is a detail of the Ryozen Kannon (霊山観音) in Kyoto.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Four portraits</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/umimachi-diary/"/>
        <updated>2021-04-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/umimachi-diary</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/umimachi-diary_1600x600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;I made a series of four portraits based on a scene from the 2015 movie “海街 diary” (&lt;em&gt;umimachi diary&lt;/em&gt;) by Hirokazu Kore-Eda, called “Our Little Sister” in English. The movie is based on a manga from 2007 of the same name by Akimi Yoshida (吉田秋生) &lt;a href=&quot;https://flowers.shogakukan.co.jp/work/317/&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. The title means “diary of a seaside town”.  The seaside town in the story is Kamakura  (鎌倉市), an ancient capital of Japan on the Pacific coast. The banner picture shows a view over the town which I took in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/umimachi-diary-manga.avif&quot; alt=&quot;A drawing of four girls, a group of three and a younger one facing them.&quot; title=&quot;A drawing of four girls, a group of three and a younger one facing them.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Illustration by Akimi Yoshida for the first chapter of her manga Umimachi Diary&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The manga and film tell the story of four sisters: after the funeral of their estranged father, the three Koda sisters Sachi, Yoshino and Chika invite their younger half-sister Suzu to come and live with them at the old family home they share in Kamakura. The film covers a year in Suzu’s life and the portraits are from a scene in summer at the end of that year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film is not so much about the sisters as about how things change with the passage of time, and that passage of time is beautifully suggested in the manga as well as in the movie through subtle references to the seasons. The story starts out in late summer (late August or early September) with the sound of the cicadas: the manga’s first chapter is called  &lt;em&gt;semijigure no yamu koro&lt;/em&gt; (蝉時雨のやむ頃) which means “the time when the chorus of the cicadas stops” (&lt;em&gt;semi&lt;/em&gt; means cicada and &lt;em&gt;jigure&lt;/em&gt; is literally “rain shower”). Suzu moves in with the sisters after the traditional &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.japanese-wiki-corpus.org/Buddhism/Chuin.html&quot;&gt;Buddhist 49-day period of mourning (&lt;em&gt;chuin&lt;/em&gt;, 中陰)&lt;/a&gt; for her father’s death, so by then it is early autumn. A bit later, when she joins the local soccer team, the colourful maple leaves (&lt;em&gt;kouyou&lt;/em&gt;, 紅葉) show us it’s late autumn, and later yet the sisters are huddled around the &lt;em&gt;kotatsu&lt;/em&gt; (a low table with an electric heater attached underneath) in the deep of winter. Then the cherry blossoms (&lt;em&gt;sakurabana&lt;/em&gt;, 桜花) herald spring, and the hydrangeas mark the rainy season (&lt;em&gt;tsuyu&lt;/em&gt;, 梅雨). At the end of this, the sisters pick the green plums from the plum tree in the garden to make plum wine, and then summer comes, with the fireworks (&lt;em&gt;hanabi&lt;/em&gt;, 花火).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scene I have chosen for the portraits is when the sisters are having their own fireworks in their garden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/scene-for-portraits.avif&quot; alt=&quot;Four young women in yukata, holding sparklers.&quot; title=&quot;Four young women in yukata, holding sparklers.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The senkō hanabi scene from the movie &quot;Our Little Sister&quot;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like it because they are all absorbed in the sparklers; because of the yukatas (summer kimonos) they are wearing for the occasion, which give the scene a timeless quality and provide interesting graphical patterns; and because of the reflection of the light from the sparklers on their faces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sparklers are called &lt;em&gt;senkō hanabi&lt;/em&gt; (線香花火, literally “incense-stick fireworks”). They date back to the Edo period (17th century) and are quite sophisticated:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Well manufactured senkō hanabi are renowned for having 5 phases in the course of its life: birth, infancy, youth, middle age, and old age. In the birth phase, the firework composition burns to leave a wire-like cinder. In the infancy phase, the cinder gradually shrinks and produces a fireball that increases in brilliancy. The youth phase then displays large pine needle shaped sparks that project from the surface of the fireball. Next, in the middle age phase, many small sparks are emitted from the fireball. Then finally, energy fades in the old age phase as the sparks die down and become willow-like.” &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/268805446_Japanese_Fireworks_Hanabi_The_Ephemeral_Nature_and_Symbolism&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That same paper &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/268805446_Japanese_Fireworks_Hanabi_The_Ephemeral_Nature_and_Symbolism&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; makes the following observation on watching &lt;em&gt;senkō hanabi&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Watching senkō hanabi is like a meditation, mesmerising and calming, allowing thoughts and earthly worries to be temporarily cast aside. Although senkō hanabi only lasts approximately 20 seconds, its brief existence manages to express the sentiment and emotion of an entire life. As the senkō hanabi briefly transitions through each phase, comparisons can accordingly be drawn to the various transitions of one’s own life. The observer is reminded of the rapid change and development in birth and infancy; the vivacious energy of youth; refinement in middle age; and finally, withering in old age. Moreover, the irregular nature of the sparks stresses the randomness and uncertainty of life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my portraits the senkō hanabi is not visible but I wanted to capture the meditative atmosphere of the scene. When I make a portrait I want it to be as close to the photograph I start from but at the same time to reflect the subject’s character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used the &lt;em&gt;senkō hanabi&lt;/em&gt; scene to make four individual portraits. The reference picture is quite small, however: if it was printed each part corresponding to a portrait would measure about 5 cm x 7 cm. The drawings are on paper of 38 cm x 56 cm. Scaling up from such a small photograph is one of the challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore,  I like to use cold pressed watercolour paper, in this case Arches 300 g/m². This kind of paper has a very coarse grain. It contributes a lot to the texture of the final work, but on the other hand, the coarse grain imposes a limit on the precision with which details can be drawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I prefer to use Conté pencils, because they have a much richer, blacker tint than ordinary pencils. But they have a thick, brittle lead that can’t be sharpened to a fine point. Also, Conté pencil strokes can’t be erased. So once they have been drawn they are part of the drawing, right or not. Because of all this, the final outcome of the drawing is not entirely under my control, and I like it that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first portrait, that of Yoshino, I used only Conté pencil and Faber-Castell Graphite Aquarelle pencils, and I washed the drawing to get a deeper black. I was not entirely happy with it, mostly because of the texture of the hair and the background, although the highlights on the face had turned out the way I wanted them and I was pleased with the ginkho pattern on the yukata as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/p0-yoshino.avif&quot; alt=&quot;A pencil portrait of a Japanese woman in profile, wearing a yukata with a stylised ginkho leaf pattern. The scene is quite dark, the face has some highlights from an invisible light source placed in front and below the character. The background is a sketchy rendering of vegetation.&quot; title=&quot;A pencil portrait of a Japanese woman in profile, wearing a yukata with a stylised ginkho leaf pattern. The scene is quite dark, the face has some highlights from an invisible light source placed in front and below the character. The background is a sketchy rendering of vegetation.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;First portrait of Yoshino&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the portrait of Sachi, I used essentially the same approach but I decided to add a touch of blue colour to the &lt;em&gt;yukata&lt;/em&gt; and use it for highlights as well. I used a Derwent Inktense watercolour pencil for this. Compared to other watercolour pencils, these give a much more intense colour. I rendered the background differently, more abstracted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/p2-sachi.avif&quot; alt=&quot;A Conté pencil portrait of a Japanese woman in three-quarter, looking down at something in front of her. She is wearing a yukata with a stylised bamboo leaf, maple leaf and flower pattern. The scene is quite dark, the face has some highlights from an invisible light source placed in front and below the character. The background is a blurry blobs. The pattern of the yukata is tinted in blue watercolour.&quot; title=&quot;A Conté pencil portrait of a Japanese woman in three-quarter, looking down at something in front of her. She is wearing a yukata with a stylised bamboo leaf, maple leaf and flower pattern. The scene is quite dark, the face has some highlights from an invisible light source placed in front and below the character. The background is a blurry blobs. The pattern of the yukata is tinted in blue watercolour.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Portrait of Sachi&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the portrait of Suzu, I used pale pink and blue for the pattern of the yukata, and a slightly more magenta-like colour for the obi (sash), for highlights on the face and for the hairband.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/p3-suzu.avif&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing of a young Japanese girl in a yukata with stylised motif of stalks with large leaves, tinted with blue and dark pink watercolour. The person is crouching and looking down at something in front of her. Her hair is tied up on top with a pink hairband. The legs are not visible.&quot; title=&quot;Drawing of a young Japanese girl in a yukata with stylised motif of stalks with large leaves, tinted with blue and dark pink watercolour. The person is crouching and looking down at something in front of her. Her hair is tied up on top with a pink hairband. The legs are not visible.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Portrait of Suzu&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final portrait was that of Chika, and it was a bit more challenging because it is very dark and also more cropped than I wanted it for my composition, so I had to extend the right part of it. I again used the same blue with just a few accents of the pink. It is the most abstracted of the four portraits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/p4-chika.avif&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing of a torso at a three-quarters angle of a young Japanese girl in a yukata with stylised motif of flowers. The yukata is tinted blue with watercolour, the flowers are white with a pink accent. The person is looking down at something in front of her. Her hair is tied up on top with a hair elastic with two white ponpons with some pink. The background is dark.&quot; title=&quot;Drawing of a torso at a three-quarters angle of a young Japanese girl in a yukata with stylised motif of flowers. The yukata is tinted blue with watercolour, the flowers are white with a pink accent. The person is looking down at something in front of her. Her hair is tied up on top with a hair elastic with two white ponpons with some pink. The background is dark.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Portrait of Chika&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When these three portraits were done, I was no longer satisfied with the first one of Yoshino so I redid it. The composition is different, with the figure much larger, and I changed the position of the torso so that more of the yukata is visible. I used the same Derwent Inktense blue as for the other portraits on the yukata, and the same style of background treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/p1-yoshino.avif&quot; alt=&quot;A Conté pencil portrait of a Japanese woman in profile, wearing a yukata with a stylised ginkho leaf pattern in blue. The scene is quite dark, the face has some highlights from an invisible light source placed in front and below the character. The background is a sketchy rendering of vegetation.&quot; title=&quot;A Conté pencil portrait of a Japanese woman in profile, wearing a yukata with a stylised ginkho leaf pattern in blue. The scene is quite dark, the face has some highlights from an invisible light source placed in front and below the character. The background is a sketchy rendering of vegetation.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Final portrait of Yoshino&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[1] &lt;a href=&quot;https://flowers.shogakukan.co.jp/work/317/&quot;&gt;Offical web page of the manga Umimachi diary (in Japanese)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[2] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/268805446_Japanese_Fireworks_Hanabi_The_Ephemeral_Nature_and_Symbolism&quot;&gt;Japanese Fireworks (Hanabi): The Ephemeral Nature and Symbolism”, Damien Liu-Brennan, Mio Bryce, The International Journal of the Arts in Society, Volume 4, Number 5, 2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Per Tiziana</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/per-tiziana/"/>
        <updated>2021-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/per-tiziana</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/per-tiziana_1600x600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;Eidon wrote a beautiful short piece called &lt;a href=&quot;https://noblogo.org/eidon/per-tiziana&quot;&gt;“per Tiziana”&lt;/a&gt;, with two different arrangements. Listening to these two quite different versions, I wondered if I could make a third arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is again a twin post, the other version is &lt;a href=&quot;https://noblogo.org/eidon/per-tiziana-take-ii&quot;&gt;on Eidon’s blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eidon-says&quot;&gt;Eidon says:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 200%&quot;&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Conjure&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is an interesting word. It comes from Latin, from “&lt;em&gt;cum iurare&lt;/em&gt;”, which can be translated back as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etymonline.com/word/conjure&quot;&gt;“command on oath” (late 13c.) or “summon by a sacred name” (c. 1300)&lt;/a&gt;. Indeed, my experience with composing music is often one of inverted conjuring. Inverted because I do not conjure anything – it is &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; that am commanded, in fact; and the sacred name, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://noblogo.org/i-miei-piccoli-grundgestalt/buddismo-esoterico-e-grundgestalt&quot;&gt;kotodama&lt;/a&gt; if you like that puts me in motion and turns me into its servant, is the music theme that visits me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is what happened with “Per Tiziana” too. Its theme came to me and made me swear that I would serve her well. In practice, this meant that, for days and days and days, the theme of “Per Tiziana” stayed with me all the time. Although I was doing other things, the background (and often the foreground) thoughts were “per Tiziana”. In retrospective, rather than composing it, I was trying to remember it – reconstruct it…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multiple times I tried to put it down and found myself thinking: “That’s not it”.  When I finally got it (to some extent) right, I found that its decoration with other voices would take me much less than I had expected. Flute, vibraphone, alto sax, cellos, pizzicato strings, timpani, drums, and electric guitar were my initial choices. You can listen to the result &lt;a href=&quot;https://eidon.bandcamp.com/track/per-tiziana&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
I also produced &lt;a href=&quot;https://eidon.bandcamp.com/track/per-tiziana-piano-version&quot;&gt;a second take&lt;/a&gt;, only based on piano, timpani, and drums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes I was happy with the result! I thought to myself, “This is the track that best represents me thus far”. So much so that, even after the finishing touches, I found myself still “conjured” by this track: I could still not think of anything else but her…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But dear friend Wim came to my rescue and released me from my oath! He had liked “Per Tiziana” and told me that he had a new instrumentation in mind. I was very happy of this – Wim has a special gift for instrumentations, and that was also a way to sign my contract off with that piece, in a sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh my god, by any chance did I pass on the conjuring?! I’ve just realized that! Ouch, not so nice of me…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so Wim took over. For some reason, I had expected an instrumentation with classical music instruments, though Wim truly surprised me with something radically different.  And I liked it very, very much! The new manifestation truly resonated with me, and I’m very happy of this wonderful present that Wim had for me. Thank you very much, Wim ^__^&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When listening to the new instrumentation I realized that I wanted to have an extra final note to the piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope one day we may truly write a piece together from beginning to end: maybe a new piece for our &lt;a href=&quot;https://funkwhale.it/library/artists/116/&quot;&gt;Wim and Eidon&lt;/a&gt; album!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wim-says&quot;&gt;Wim says:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 200%&quot;&gt;“My&lt;/span&gt; original idea was to try and merge both of Eidon’s versions into something new. But when I listened very carefully to both versions, I realised that wouldn’t work. Each in its own way was already complete. So I had to try and create an entirely different arrangement.
I started from the original arrangement which as Eidon explained has six voices: vibraphone, two cellos, electric guitar, timpani and drums. Eidon kindly provided the &lt;a href=&quot;https://musescore.org/&quot;&gt;MuseScore&lt;/a&gt; files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Eidon has guessed, my first attempt was an orchestral version, because I am comfortable with that: strings, cellos, bass, a clarinet for the main melody, orchestral percussion. It was easy to do and the result sounds nice enough but it did to my ears not really “work”. One issue is the note duration and range which are not a perfect fit for the string instruments. The other is more fundamental: the complex drum pattern in the second part of the piece simply does not work with a symphonic arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This got me to think about the percussion. Because it is a repetitive pattern, I wondered if it would sound good on a drum machine. For some reason – I guess by association with the band 808 State – I thought specifically of the Roland TR-808. That lead to the idea of using old synthesisers for the other voices as well. I experimented with a few and at a certain point I literally laughed out loud because the combination I hit upon worked so beautifully!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shared a first cut with Eidon and he suggested to bring out one of the voices more. I had also commented on the note duration and he explained that the initial instrument he had chosen was a vibraphone that had large preset values for sustain/reverb. I also was not satisfied with my choice of instrument for the timpani voice, and the volume of the drumset voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My final arrangement is as follows: polysynth for the lead voice, synth bass 1 and 3, Moog pad, Roland Brightness from &lt;a href=&quot;http://rkhive.com&quot;&gt;RKHive&lt;/a&gt; for the timpani and the TR-808 drum machine. I changed made the last note in each phrase of the main melody longer and simplified the electric guitar score a bit so that it sounded more natural for the Moog pad. I kept the percussion volume relatively low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eidon did a final tweak, adding an extra note to complete the piece, and we’re both very happy with the result. I really enjoy making these alternative arrangements of Eidon’s work, so really it is I who should thank him for creating these wonderful pieces.
“&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the finished track. We hope you like it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;audio controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;source src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/audio/per-tiziana-eidon-wim.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mpeg&quot; /&gt;
Your browser does not support the audio element.
&lt;/audio&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The track is also available:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on &lt;a href=&quot;https://funkwhale.it/library/tracks/1384/&quot;&gt;Funkwhale&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on &lt;a href=&quot;https://peertube.uno/videos/watch/6998c033-0ee9-40d7-9152-bcee31d760bb&quot;&gt;Peertube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/Bck3zyDNq6o&quot;&gt;Youtube&lt;/a&gt;
&amp;lt;!–&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-scripts allow-popups&quot; src=&quot;https://peertube.uno/videos/embed/6998c033-0ee9-40d7-9152-bcee31d760bb&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Bck3zyDNq6o&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;–&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Ukifune</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/ukifune/"/>
        <updated>2021-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/ukifune</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/ukifune_1600x600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LfeKeQ2fhmA&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ukifune&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (浮舟) is a song from 2002 by the Japanese band &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GO!GO!7188&quot;&gt;GO!GO!7188&lt;/a&gt; and one of my all-time favourites. It is a song about broken love, with very poetic lyrics inspired by story from very long ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;春の匂いも芽吹く花も
立ちすくむあたしに君を連れてはこない&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;haru no nioi mo mefuku hana mo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;tachisukumu atashi ni kimi wo tsurete wa konai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When spring comes, I’ll still be frozen and the scents and budding flowers won’t bring you back to me.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;夏が来る頃は明け方の雨
静かに寄り添って　かけら拾い集める&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;natsu ga kuru koro wa akegata no ame&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;shizuka ni yorisotte kakera hiroiatsumeru&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When summer comes, the rain at dawn.&lt;br /&gt; 
Snuggling quietly, I gather up the fragments”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;秋が過ぎたらきっとあたしは
のびた黒い髪を切り落としてしまう&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;aki ga sugitara kitto atashi wa&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;nobita kuroi kami wo kiriotoshite shimau&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When autumn is gone I’m sure I will&lt;br /&gt; 
finally cut off my long black hair.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;愛しい人よ離れ顔なんて　3日もすりゃすぐに忘れてしまった
ただ染みついて消えないのは煙草の匂い&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;itoshii hito yo hanare kao nante mikka mo surya sugu ni wasurete shimatta&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;tada somitsuite kienai no wa tabako no nioi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Darling, you’ve been gone only three days and already I have totally forgotten your face.&lt;br /&gt;
All that remains is the ever-lingering smell of your cigarettes.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;君を待つ日々は足りない　切ない　鳴り止まない
不協和音が響き合って&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;kimi wo matsu hibi wa tarinai setsunai nariyamanai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;fukyouwaon ga hibikiatte&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Waiting for you day after day —&lt;br /&gt; 
it’s futile — heartrending — incessantly ringing —&lt;br /&gt;
a crashing dissonance.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;それがあたしの枯れない　溶けない　鳴り止まない
孤独の唄　来来来…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;sore ga atashi no karenai tokenai nariyamanai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;kodoku no uta rai rai rai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That is my unwithering, unthawing, incessantly ringing&lt;br /&gt;
song of solitude.&lt;br /&gt;
Come, come, come!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;かすかな別れを漂わすこともなく
足音は突然　絶切れた
あぁ悲しくも美しき白い冬&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;kasuka no wakare wo tadayowasu koto mo naku&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;ashioto wa totsuzen tachikireta&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;aa kanashiku utsukushiki shiroi fuyu&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Without even a faint hint of parting —&lt;br /&gt;
The sound of footsteps suddenly cut off.&lt;br /&gt;
Ah, the sad and beautiful white winter.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;会えるものならば他に何も望まない
降り積もるは　あの日も雪&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;aeru mono naraba hoka ni nanimo nozomanai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;furitsumoru wa ano hi mo yuki&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If I could only meet you I would not wish for anything else.&lt;br /&gt;
The snow was falling thickly that day.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;君を待つ日々は足りない　切ない　鳴り止まない
不協和音が響き合って
それがあたしの枯れない　溶けない　鳴り止まない
孤独の唄　来来来…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;kimi wo matsu hibi wa tarinai setsunai nariyamanai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;fukyouwaon ga hibikiatte&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;sore ga atashi no karenai tokenai nariyamanai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;kodoku no uta rai rai rai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Waiting for you day after day —&lt;br /&gt; 
it’s futile — heartrending — incessantly ringing —&lt;br /&gt;
a crashing dissonance.&lt;br /&gt;
That is my unwithering, unthawing, incessantly ringing&lt;br /&gt;
song of solitude.&lt;br /&gt;
Come, come, come!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title of the song, “Ukifune”, is the name of a character in the “Tale of Genji” (&lt;em&gt;Genji monogatari&lt;/em&gt;,源氏物語), a masterpiece of Japanese literature from the early 11th century (Heian period), written by the noblewoman and lady-in-waiting Murasaki Shikibu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word &lt;em&gt;ukifune&lt;/em&gt; (浮舟) is the title of the chapter where the story starts. It can be translated as “A Drifting Boat”. As is common in the Tale of Genji, the name of the chapter is used as a nickname for the character. In this case, the title and the character’s name were based on a poem she wrote in which she calls herself “a drifting boat” to express her uncertainty and inner turmoil:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;橘の小島の色は変はらじをこの浮舟ぞ行方知られぬ&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tachibana no&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;kojima no iro ha&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;kawaraji wo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;kono ukifune zo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;yukue chirarenu&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The enduring hue of the Isle of Orange Trees may well never change, yet there is no knowing now where this drifting boat is bound”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The poem is written in winter, with all the land around Uji deeply covered in snow. With her suitor, they have gone out on the Uji river in small boat and moored at the Isle of Orange Trees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the story, when she finds herself caught between two powerful suitors, and it seems that whichever one she choses it will end badly, Ukifune tries to drown herself in the Uji river. She fails and becomes a nun. In the Heian period, when noble women became nuns, they would cut off their very long hair. And in the tale, it is indeed autumn by the time Ukifune becomes a nun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The song has many other classical references, such as the use of 〜き adjectives (美しき) and the &lt;em&gt;on&lt;/em&gt; reading (i.e. the reading derived from the original Chinese proncunciation of the character) &lt;em&gt;rai&lt;/em&gt; of 来 (“come”) used as refrain: &lt;em&gt;rai rai rai&lt;/em&gt;. The word for “song”, &lt;em&gt;uta&lt;/em&gt;, is usually written as 歌 but here as 唄, this more specifically refers to songs accompanied my &lt;em&gt;shamisen&lt;/em&gt;, the traditional three-stringed lute. The song’s mode and melody reflects those traditional songs. It is often said that GO!GO!7188’s music is influenced by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enka&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;enka&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; musical genre, but for this song it is probably more correct to say that it is influenced by the traditional music that gave rise to &lt;em&gt;enka&lt;/em&gt;. And although lost love and loneliness are typical &lt;em&gt;enka&lt;/em&gt; themes, they are universal themes that are also very common themes in the &lt;em&gt;Tale of Genji&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The song starts with a huge reverberating chord, reminiscent of the sound of a &lt;em&gt;biwa&lt;/em&gt; (琵琶), a traditional type of lute that in the Heian period was played at the Imperial court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then follow three verses that repeat the same melody (A) in crescendo. The first word of each verse is a season: spring 春, summer 夏 and autumn 秋.
Then a two new melodies (B/C) are introduced, and a new lyrical theme: the verses address the departed lover. This is followed by the refrain, the single character 来 &lt;em&gt;rai&lt;/em&gt; (“come”) repeated over and over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then follows and instrumental version of A, followed by a dissonant part reflecting the dissonance in the lyrics.
After this interlude comes a verse in melody B that is the heart of the song, the moment when the lover left. Its final word is “winter” 冬.
The following verse in melody C ends in “snow” 雪 and blends into a repetition of the first verse in melody C and the refrain D: the single syllable &lt;em&gt;ki&lt;/em&gt; is both use as the last syllable of the verse, the &lt;em&gt;ki&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;yuki&lt;/em&gt; (“snow”) and the first syllable of the next verse, &lt;em&gt;kimi&lt;/em&gt; (“you”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The references to the seasons in the song reflect the important role the seasons play in traditional Japanese culture. The Tale of Genji is full of allusions to the seasons, season-specific rituals and poetry. Traditional Japanese poetry (&lt;em&gt;waka&lt;/em&gt;) is also often inspired by the seasons, I discussed some of them in my article &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/my-own-private-japan&quot;&gt;“The Beautiful Japan of the Mind”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The banner picture of this article is the statue of Ukifune in Uji, near Kyoto, where the story is set. It is a picture I took during a visit in the summer of 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a live version of the song, recorded at Nihon Budokan in 2005.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;audio controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;source src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/audio/ukifune.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mpeg&quot; /&gt;
Your browser does not support the audio element.
&lt;/audio&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>The Beautiful Japan of the Mind</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/my-own-private-japan/"/>
        <updated>2021-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/my-own-private-japan</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/my-own-private-japan_1600x600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;Yasunari Kawabata  (川端康成) was the first Japanese novelist to receive the Nobel prize in Literature. I had read his novel “The Master of Go” (名人) and recently I listened to the BBC dramatised version of “A thousand cranes” (千羽鶴). This led me to look up his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/literature/1968/kawabata/lecture/&quot;&gt;Nobel lecture&lt;/a&gt; “Japan, the Beautiful and Myself” and it made a great impression on me, in particular his discussion of poems by Zen Buddhist monks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The English translation by the eminent &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Seidensticker&quot;&gt;Edward Seidensticker&lt;/a&gt; is excellent, but inevitably some features of the original get lost in translation. This is why I prefer to attempt to read the original Japanese text. 
The Nobel Prize site provides a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/literature/1968/kawabata/25542-yasunari-kawabata-nobel-lecture-1968/&quot;&gt;Japanese version of the lecture&lt;/a&gt; but unfortunately it is a series of images of handwritten text. The handwriting is incredibly regular but the images have such a low resolution that the text is very hard to read. Because of the poor quality, to read it I first created &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/kawabata-nobel-lecture/&quot;&gt;a readable version of the Japanese text&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been two other Japanese Nobel laureates, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/literature/1994/oe/lecture/&quot;&gt;Kenzaburo Oe&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/literature/2017/ishiguro/25124-kazuo-ishiguro-nobel-lecture-2017/&quot;&gt;Kazuo Ishiguro&lt;/a&gt; (who was born in Japan but moved to the UK at the age of five).  Both these authors wrote and delivered their lectures in English, so there is no original Japanese version. Kenzaburo Oe discusses Yasunari Kawabata’s lecture in his own Nobel lecture, titled “Japan, The Ambiguous, and Myself”, a clear reference to the title of Kawabata’s lecture:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Kawabata Yasunari, the first Japanese writer who stood on this platform as a winner of the Nobel Prize for Literature, delivered a lecture entitled Japan, the Beautiful, and Myself. It was at once very beautiful and vague. I have used the English word vague as an equivalent of that word in Japanese &lt;em&gt;aimaina&lt;/em&gt;. This Japanese adjective could have several alternatives for its English translation. The kind of vagueness that Kawabata adopted deliberately is implied in the title itself of his lecture. It can be transliterated as ‘myself of beautiful Japan’. The vagueness of the whole title derives from the Japanese particle ‘&lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;’ (literally ‘of’) linking ‘Myself’ and ‘Beautiful Japan’.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The vagueness of the title leaves room for various interpretations of its implications. It can imply ‘myself as a part of beautiful Japan’, the particle ‘&lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;’ indicating the relationship of the noun following it to the noun preceding it as one of possession, belonging or attachment. It can also imply ‘beautiful Japan and myself’, the particle in this case linking the two nouns in apposition, as indeed they are in the English title of Kawabata’s lecture translated by one of the most eminent American specialists of Japanese literature. He translates ‘Japan, the beautiful and myself’. In this expert translation the traduttore (translator) is not in the least a traditore (betrayer).”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will come back to Oe’s views on Kawabata’s lecture later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/literature/2017/ishiguro/25124-kazuo-ishiguro-nobel-lecture-2017/&quot;&gt;Nobel lecture by Kazuo Ishiguro&lt;/a&gt; is also very much worth reading. I like in particular his description of his realisation that “his” Japan is a mental construct:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I was starting to accept that ‘my’ Japan perhaps didn’t much correspond to any place I could go to on a plane; that the way of life of which my parents talked, that I remembered from my early childhood, had largely vanished during the 1960s and 1970s; that in any case, the Japan that existed in my head might always have been an emotional construct put together by a child out of memory, imagination and speculation. And perhaps most significantly, I’d come to realise that with each year I grew older, this Japan of mine — this precious place I’d grown up with — was getting fainter and fainter.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always been convinced that any place we visit, or a place where we come from but no longer live, is essentially a place “of the mind”, and that is why everyone’s experience of visiting the same place is so different. Our minds best retain the memories that made the strongest impressions on us, and what these are is different for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been to Japan several times, twice for visits of several months. During these visits I’ve worked with researchers at the Disaster Prevention Research Institute of Kyoto University, and explored the temples and shrines of Kyoto. Kawabata’s views and ideas resonate with me because they are close to my “Japan of the mind”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;source-text-and-translation&quot;&gt;Source text and translation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spelling&quot;&gt;Spelling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kawabata was born in 1899 and received the Nobel prize in 1968. This means that he learned to write in the period between 1900 and 1946 when the usage of &lt;em&gt;kana&lt;/em&gt; was &lt;a href=&quot;http://spellingsociety.org/uploaded_journals/j19-journal.pdf&quot;&gt;based on historical principles&lt;/a&gt;, i.e. they reflected the historical pronunciation rather than the actual one. For example, the verb &lt;em&gt;iru&lt;/em&gt; “to be” was written in &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt; as ゐる (&lt;em&gt;wiru&lt;/em&gt;) rather than いる (&lt;em&gt;iru&lt;/em&gt;). The noun &lt;em&gt;kao&lt;/em&gt; “face” was written かほ (&lt;em&gt;kaho&lt;/em&gt;) rather than かお (&lt;em&gt;kao&lt;/em&gt;). In general, many &lt;em&gt;kana&lt;/em&gt; writings used the “h”+vowel (&lt;em&gt;ha&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; etc.) and “w”+vowel (&lt;em&gt;wo&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;em&gt;wi&lt;/em&gt; etc.) were in modern Japanese only the vowel is used; for some words, what is now &lt;em&gt;ka&lt;/em&gt; was &lt;em&gt;kwa&lt;/em&gt;, written くわ. Other difference were the spelling やう (&lt;em&gt;yau&lt;/em&gt;) instead of よう(&lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;), せう(&lt;em&gt;seu&lt;/em&gt;) instead of  しょう (&lt;em&gt;shou&lt;/em&gt;) and similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1946 the &lt;em&gt;kana&lt;/em&gt; spelling was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Japanese_script_reform&quot;&gt;reformed&lt;/a&gt; into the simpler, pronunciation-orientated spelling that is still the standard in modern Japanese. Many &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; were also simplified.
Nevertheless, Kawabata’s Nobel lecture is largely written in the old spelling, and uses some of the old-style kanji (旧漢字, &lt;em&gt;kyuukanji&lt;/em&gt;). This gives the text a peculiar old-fashioned character that is not obvious from the translation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note for example the spelling of 言へる (now 言える) and してゐます (now しています) in one of the first sentences in the essay, a commentary on a poem by the Zen poet Myoe:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;明恵のこの歌には、歌物語と言へるぼどの、長く詳しい詞書きがあって、歌のこころを明らかにしてゐます。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Myoe no kono uta ni wa, utamonogatari to iheru hodo no, nagakukuwashii kotobagaki ga atte, uta no kokoro wo akiraka ni shitewimasu.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-limits-of-translation&quot;&gt;The limits of translation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Kenzaburo Oe pointed out above, exact translation is impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, Kawabata comments that the explanatory note (&lt;em&gt;kotobagaki&lt;/em&gt;, 詞書き ) by Myoe on this own poem is so long and detailed that it could be said to be an &lt;em&gt;utamonogatari&lt;/em&gt;(歌物語, meaning a “short Heian period tale in the form of a poem”), a level of detail not present in the translation which simply says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The second poem bears an unusually detailed account of its origins, such as to be an explanation of the heart of its meaning”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the essay, many poems are quoted, most of them by Buddhist monks. The translator, Edward Seidensticker, received help from a Buddhist scholar (Jikai Fujiyoshi,藤吉慈海) for the quotations and references. They had to translate them in a great rush as Kawabata was still writing his lecture in his hotel on the morning that he had to deliver it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the original Japanese text, the old poems are written in classical Japanese (&lt;em&gt;kobun&lt;/em&gt;, 古文) which is a very different language from modern Japanese, with different grammar and vocabulary. As it is impossible to render this in English, we get a modern translation instead. To a Japanese reader, the poems therefore have an entirely different feeling, probably similar to what an English reader experiences with the original &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/43521/beowulf-old-english-version&quot;&gt;Beowulf&lt;/a&gt;, or a Dutch speaker reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dbnl.org/tekst/_kar001kare01_01/_kar001kare01_01_0001.php&quot;&gt;Karel ende Elegast&lt;/a&gt;. This is of course not essential to the message of the lecture but it illustrates the difficulties facing the translator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;zen-buddhism-and-poetry&quot;&gt;Zen Buddhism and poetry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the poems quoted are &lt;em&gt;tanka&lt;/em&gt;, (短歌 meaning “short poem”), a poem consisting of 31 mora in  five units, usually following a 5-7-5-7-7 pattern of mora per unit. For example, the first poem (written here a unit per line to show the structure) is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;春は花&lt;br /&gt;
夏ほととぎす&lt;br /&gt;
秋は月&lt;br /&gt;
冬雪ざえて&lt;br /&gt;
冷しかりけり&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“In the spring, cherry blossoms, in the summer the cuckoo.&lt;br /&gt;
In autumn the moon, and in winter the snow, clear, cold.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and the second one&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;雲を出でて&lt;br /&gt;
我にとちなふ&lt;br /&gt;
冬の月&lt;br /&gt;
風や身にしむ&lt;br /&gt;
雪や冷めたき&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The winter moon comes from the clouds to keep me company.&lt;br /&gt;
The wind is piercing, the snow is cold.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I find most interesting is Kawabata’s observation on this second poem. Myoe provided the following note about his inspiration for this poem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“When the hour of the midnight vigil came, I ceased meditation and descended from the hall on the peak to the lower quarters, and as I did so the moon came from the clouds and set the snow to glowing. The moon was my companion, and not even the wolf howling in the valley brought fear. “&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kawabata says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“My reason for choosing [this poem] has to do with its remarkable gentleness and compassion. Winter moon, going behind the clouds and coming forth again, making bright my footsteps as I go to the meditation hall and descend again, making me unafraid of the wolf: does not the wind sink into you, does not the snow, are you not cold? I choose the poem as a poem of warm, deep, delicate compassion, a poem that has in it the deep quiet of the Japanese spirit.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kawabata further discusses a particular poem that is very easy to understand, but nevertheless loses a lot in translation, because the visual effect and structure are untranslatable:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;あかあかやあかあかあかやあかあかやあかあかあかやあかあかや月&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;aka aka ya&lt;br /&gt;
aka aka aka ya&lt;br /&gt;
aka aka ya&lt;br /&gt;
aka aka aka ya&lt;br /&gt;
aka aka ya tsuki&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that even this poem is a &lt;em&gt;tanka&lt;/em&gt;! The translation is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Bright, bright, and bright, bright, bright, and bright, bright.&lt;br /&gt;
Bright and bright, bright, and bright, bright moon.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kawabata observes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Seeing the moon, he becomes the moon, the moon seen by him becomes him. He sinks into nature, becomes one with nature. The light of the “clear heart” of the priest, seated in the meditation hall in the darkness before the dawn, becomes for the dawn moon its own light.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zen monks like Dogen and Myoe spent a lot of their time in meditation. As a result, they were able to live as much in the present as possible and to have as little sense of self as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dogen and Myoe lived in the 13th century. The final poem I want to highlight is the deathbed poem of the priest Ryokan who lived much later (1758-1831):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;形見として何か残さん舂は花山ほととぎす秋はもみぢ葉&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“What shall be my legacy? The blossoms of spring,&lt;br /&gt;
The cuckoo in the hills, the leaves of autumn.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kawabata says&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“In this poem, as in Dogen’s, the commonest of figures and the commonest of words are strung together without hesitation — no, to particular effect, rather — and so they transmit the very essence of Japan.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and further&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Ryokan pursued literature and belief in the benign spirit summarized in the Buddhist phrase “a smiling face and gentle words”. In his last poem he offered nothing as a legacy. He but hoped that after his death nature would remain beautiful. That could be his bequest.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The phrase “a smiling face and gentle words” is a “four-kanji idiom” (&lt;em&gt;yojijukugo&lt;/em&gt;,四字熟語), pronounced as &lt;em&gt;wagan aigo&lt;/em&gt;. Its origin is from a Buddhist text called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.acmuller.net/bud-canon/sutra_of_immeasurable_life.html#div-9&quot;&gt;“The Sutra of Immeasurable Life”&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“With an expression of tenderness in his face and with kindness in his speech, he spoke to others in consonance with their inner thoughts.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It carries the connotation that &lt;a href=&quot;https://crd.ndl.go.jp/reference/modules/d3ndlcrdentry/index.php?page=ref_view&amp;amp;id=1000061578&quot;&gt;the bodhisattva speaks gentle words to guide people&lt;/a&gt;. The web site of the Honganji temple in Kyoto has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hongwanji.or.jp/mioshie/words/000916.html&quot;&gt;a nice explanation (in Japanese)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-did-kawabata-include-these-poems-in-his-lecture&quot;&gt;Why did Kawabata include these poems in his lecture?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/literature/1994/oe/lecture/&quot;&gt;his own Nobel lecture&lt;/a&gt;, Kenzaburo Oe expresses his views on the use of classical poetry in Kawabata’s lecture:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Even as a twentieth-century writer Kawabata depicts his state of mind in terms of the poems written by medieval Zen monks. &lt;em&gt;Most of these poems are concerned with the linguistic impossibility of telling truth.&lt;/em&gt;  According to such poems words are confined within their closed shells. The readers can not expect that words will ever come out of these poems and get through to us. One can never understand or feel sympathetic towards these Zen poems except by giving oneself up and willingly penetrating into the closed shells of those words.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Why did Kawabata boldly decide to read those extremely esoteric poems in Japanese before the audience in Stockholm? I look back almost with nostalgia upon the straightforward bravery which he attained towards the end of his distinguished career and with which he made such a confession of his faith. Kawabata had been an artistic pilgrim for decades during which he produced a host of masterpieces. After those years of his pilgrimage, only by making a confession as to how he was fascinated by such inaccessible Japanese poems that baffle any attempt fully to understand them, was he able to talk about ‘Japan, the Beautiful, and Myself’, that is, about the world in which he lived and the literature which he created.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Daffodils</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/daffodils/"/>
        <updated>2020-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/daffodils</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/daffodils_1600x600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;A whimsical fedi music collaboration between Eidon and Wim. This is a twin post, the other version is &lt;a href=&quot;https://noblogo.org/eidon/daffodils&quot;&gt;on Eidon’s blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the finished track. We hope you like it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;audio controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;source src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/audio/Daffodils-integration-retimed.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mpeg&quot; /&gt;
Your browser does not support the audio element.
&lt;/audio&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eidon-says&quot;&gt;Eidon says:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 200%&quot;&gt;“It &lt;/span&gt;
all started from the title, really. “Daffodils”. Nice word, which reminds of many things – an Arcadia of beautiful flowers and their scent, or Wordsworth’s famous poem, for instance. Among the many spurious thoughts that such a word could evoke, there was one that triggered the resolve to create a piece of music from it: the presence of letters that can be interpreted as note names, together with others that can not. Of the many possible mappings, this one was chosen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/Theme.avif&quot; alt=&quot;A piece of musical score showing the theme of Daffodils.&quot; title=&quot;A piece of musical score showing the theme of Daffodils.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The theme of &quot;Daddodils&quot;: ‘D’, ‘A’, ‘F’, ‘F’, rest, ‘D’, rest, rest, (rest)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where ‘real’ notes where used when a music counterpart existed, and `imaginary’ (inaudible) notes otherwise. The singular form led to 8 quavers and an easy 4/4 metre. The result was found sufficiently interesting and worth pursuing, and a composition was started from there. Three voices, initially appointed two two electric guitars and electric bass, with the theme exposed and repeated by the first guitar, soon joined by the cortege of its companions, all moving in an ostinato slow-pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In retrospective, it is possible that, from the very beginning, it all was leading to Wordsworth’s poem – the choice of the tempo, for instance. Whatever the actual case, at some point it became clear that the connection with “I Wandered Lonely As A Cloud” had to be made explicit. At first we thought to only sing the poem’s final verses; and then Wim had the great idea to recite the whole poem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The track was created with &lt;a href=&quot;http://tuxguitar.com.ar/&quot;&gt;TuxGuitar&lt;/a&gt;, a nice tabulature editor whose notes input interfaces include guitar fretboards. So yes all the instruments you can hear in Daffodils have been composed… on guitar ^_^. Some of the sounds were produced via the Timbres Of Heaven soundfont, while for others we used MuseScore, after importing MIDI files exported from TuxGuitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/Tux.avif&quot; alt=&quot;TuxGuitar UI.&quot; title=&quot;The TuxGuitar UI.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The TuxGuitar UI&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://musescore.org/&quot;&gt;MuseScore&lt;/a&gt; is much more powerful than TuxGuitar. It allows to orchestrate voices from multiple soundfonts at the same time, for instance, and to export the voices as separate audio files. Once the voices have been chosen and isolated, we used Audacity to orchestrate them together. The original TuxGuitar voices were then mixed with MuseScore voices from the Sonatina Symphonic Orchestra,  and the Nice Keys Suite soundfonts, plus that of a Steinway piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.audacityteam.org/&quot;&gt;Audacity&lt;/a&gt; is perhaps not the best tool one could use, though it has certain valuable features. One such feature is so-called Envelope Tool: with it, it is possible to finely control the volume of each voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/Audax.avif&quot; alt=&quot;Audacity UI for the Envelope Tool.&quot; title=&quot;Audacity UI for the Envelope Tool.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Each voice is wrapped in a “control envelope”, which changes the volume of the track proportionally to the ‘height’ of the envelope.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allows fade-ins and fade-outs, and thus can simulate the entrance and exit of instruments. This has been used extensively in Daffodils!
“&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wim-says&quot;&gt;Wim says:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 200%&quot;&gt;“Eidon &lt;/span&gt;
wrote this great track “Daffodils” as he explained above, and he sent me a draft and asked if I could recite the verses from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/45521/i-wandered-lonely-as-a-cloud&quot;&gt;Wordsworth’s poem&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t know what he thought my voice would contribute to the work, maybe he wanted a Flemish-Scottish accent?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eidon had in mind that I would recite the final two verses only:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And then my heart with pleasure fills,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;And dances with the daffodils.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I misunderstood him, and I recited the entire poem. That turned out to be serendipitous, as we are both happy with the final result. But I’m running ahead of myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used my laptop’s built-in mic as that is all I have. The audio quality is acceptable but far from great, so from the start I had this idea that I wanted to apply some distorting effects to the voice. I thought it might work well with the track which is quite modern and rather different from what a more conventional composer might associate with the image of daffodils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d never done this before, so it was an interesting experiment. I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.audacityteam.org/&quot;&gt;Audacity&lt;/a&gt; for the recording and for all processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recorded the audio in two takes, and combined the best parts. There is nothing to say about the recording: I just read the poem out loud, at a pace that seemed natural to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First I improved the audio quality. I knew from past experience that a good way to do it is to apply the following effects:
• Noise Reduction with default settings
• Equalisation (Graphic EQ) with the “Bass Boost” preset
• &lt;a href=&quot;https://manual.audacityteam.org/man/compressor.html&quot;&gt;Compressor&lt;/a&gt; with default settings
• &lt;a href=&quot;https://manual.audacityteam.org/man/reverb.html&quot;&gt;Reverb&lt;/a&gt; with the “Vocal I” preset&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then also doubled the voice, with a very slight shift between the tracks, so there is no perceptible echo but the sounds is a little bit fuller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially I had wanted to use only the vocoder. But Audacity’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://manual.audacityteam.org/man/vocoder.html&quot;&gt;Vocoder effect&lt;/a&gt; is not quite what I had in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The default setting for the Vocoder results in a rather tame distortion. My settings are&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;    Distance: 50.0
    Output choice: Both channels
    Number of vocoder bands: 60
    Amplitude of original audio (percent): 100.0
    Amplitude of white noise (percent): 0.0
    Amplitude of Radar Needles (percent): 50.0
    Frequency of Radar Needles (Hz): 80.0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is a bit like speaking through a tube, with added radar needles, a series of short pulses which give a robotic effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://manual.audacityteam.org/man/phaser.html&quot;&gt;Phaser&lt;/a&gt; could introduce some interesting distortions. Again, the default effect is quite tame. I used the following setting, on a separate copy of the voice track:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;    Stages: 20
    Dry/Wet: 180
    LFO Frequency (Hz): 0.6
    LFO Start Phase (deg.): 50.0
    Depth: 120
    Feedback (%): 75
    Output gain (dB): -3.0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is a space-like oscillator sound overlaying the speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was still not happy with the result so I added another copy of the voice track Reverb using the “Church Hall” preset, which gives a huge echoing sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I combined these three tracks with the original one, taking care that I did not entirely drown out the recitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then combined this track with Eidon’s music. I tweaked the pauses between the verses to match the music and tweaked the volume of the voice here and there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final verses are repeated three times, because somehow I thought that fit with the music.
“&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eidon-says-1&quot;&gt;Eidon says:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 200%&quot;&gt;“No &lt;/span&gt;
greater bias than the authors’ opinion, maybe, though we are quite pleased with the results. Music and verse dance together, and hearts with pleasure fill. Therefore, it is likely that this first move into musical/poetical co-creation shall be followed by new experiments soon!
“&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The track is available on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://open.tube/videos/watch/e26710c0-8813-4691-b4e6-ef0e36e49848&quot;&gt;OpenTube&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://peertube.uno/videos/embed/f746036d-76ec-48fa-bce0-8caf85b68195&quot;&gt;PeerTube.uno&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://funkwhale.it/library/tracks/826/&quot;&gt;Funkwhale.it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our album “Daffodils and Other Flowers” is available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://funkwhale.it/library/albums/184/&quot;&gt;Funkwhale.it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;330&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://funkwhale.it/front/embed.html?&amp;amp;type=album&amp;amp;id=184&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Daffodils” and “Daffodils and Other Flowers” is © 2020 Eidon and Wim. https://octodon.social/@wim_v12e, Eidon@tutanota.com.&lt;br /&gt;This work is licensed under a &lt;a rel=&quot;license&quot; href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;license&quot; href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Creative Commons Licence&quot; style=&quot;border-width:0&quot; src=&quot;https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-sa/4.0/88x31.avif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>The True Pure Land</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/shinshu-prayer/"/>
        <updated>2020-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/shinshu-prayer</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/shinshu-prayer_1600x600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;I am currently reading the original Japanese version of “Tokyo Ueno Station” by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miri_Yu&quot;&gt;Yu Miri&lt;/a&gt;,『JR上野駅公園口』. It’s a very nice but difficult novel, I may write more about it later. After I wrote the &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/four-wisdoms&quot;&gt;article on the Buddhist prayer “The Four Wisdoms”&lt;/a&gt;, I came across a passage in the novel that describes a Buddhist funeral and it contains a prayer used by the  Jōdo Shinshū (浄土真宗, “The True Essence of the Pure Land Teaching”),  known as Shinshū in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-prayer&quot;&gt;The prayer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prayer in the book is written in archaic Japanese with old forms of &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; and grammar and uncommon words:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;writing-mode: vertical-rl&quot;&gt;
弘誓ノチカラヲカフラズハ&lt;br /&gt;
イジレノトキニカ娑婆ヲイデン&lt;br /&gt;
佛恩フカクオモヒツ、&lt;br /&gt;
ツ子ニ弥陀ヲ念ズベシ&lt;br /&gt;
娑婆永劫ノ苦ヲステ、&lt;br /&gt;
浄土无爲ヲ期スルコト&lt;br /&gt;
本師釋迦ノチカラナリ&lt;br /&gt;
長時ニ慈恩ヲ報ズベシ
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-puzzle&quot;&gt;The puzzle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could not understand the poem, but I was curious about its meaning so I tried to find out. First of all, here is a list of the special &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt;, words and constructions that I did not understand:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;弘誓 (ぐぜい, &lt;em&gt;guzei&lt;/em&gt;): &lt;a href=&quot;http://bschawaii.org/shindharmanet/bloom/ab-writings/salvation/&quot;&gt;Buddha’s universal vow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;娑婆 (しゃば, &lt;em&gt;shaba&lt;/em&gt;): The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sah%C4%81&quot;&gt;Sahā world&lt;/a&gt;, the mundane world.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;佛: an older form of 仏 (&lt;em&gt;butsu&lt;/em&gt;), Buddha&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;仏恩 (ブツオン、ぶっとん, &lt;em&gt;button&lt;/em&gt;): Buddha’s blessings, the grace of Buddha’s compassion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;弥陀 (みだ,&lt;em&gt;mida&lt;/em&gt;): Amitabha (a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/topic/Buddhism/Celestial-buddhas-and-bodhisattvas&quot;&gt;celestial Buddha&lt;/a&gt;, the principal buddha in Pure Land Buddhism)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;永劫 (えいごう, here pronounced &lt;em&gt;yōgō&lt;/em&gt;): Eternity, perpetuity. 劫 (&lt;em&gt;kō&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;gō&lt;/em&gt;) means &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kalpa_%28aeon%29&quot;&gt;kalpa&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;浄土 (じょうど, &lt;em&gt;jōdo&lt;/em&gt;): Lit. “pure land”, esp. the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/topic/Sukhavati&quot;&gt;Western Pure Land&lt;/a&gt; paradise of Amitabha.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;无爲: old kanji for 無為 &lt;em&gt;mui&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oxfordreference.com/view/10.1093/oi/authority.20110810104405611&quot;&gt;asaṃskṛta&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;the ‘unconditioned’, a term referring to anything that transcends conditioned (saṃskṛta) existence in the state of saṃsāra.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;期スル (ごする,&lt;em&gt;go suru&lt;/em&gt;): to live&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;本師 (ホンシ,&lt;em&gt;honshin&lt;/em&gt;): Lit. “fundamental guru”, i.e. Buddha&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;釋: an older form of 釈, lit. &lt;em&gt;shaka&lt;/em&gt;, short for &lt;em&gt;Shakamuni&lt;/em&gt; (釈迦牟尼), the historical Buddha.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;慈恩 (じおん_jion_): deep compassion, benevolence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ナリ: なり (&lt;em&gt;nari&lt;/em&gt;) is the classical version of である, “to be”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ベシ: べし (&lt;em&gt;beshi&lt;/em&gt;) is the classical version of べき, “something one ought to do”. In the prayer, 念 ずべし means 念 ずるべき,”should pray”, and 報 ずべし means 報 ずるべき, “should inform”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these terms and the &lt;em&gt;furigana&lt;/em&gt; in the novel, I could do a transcription in &lt;em&gt;romaji&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;guzei no chikara wo kafurazuba&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;idzure no toki ni ka shaba wo iden&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;button fukaku omohitsu,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;tsune ni mida wo nen zubeshi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;shaba yōgo no ku wo sute,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;jōdo mui wo go suru koto&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;honshi shaka no chikara nari&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;jōji ni jion wo hō zubeshi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So at least I can now pronounce the prayer, and I get a rough idea of the meaning. But of course I wanted to know the details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-origin&quot;&gt;The origin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By searching for snippets rewritten with modern &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt;, I found that the prayer is taken from a book of hymns called &lt;em&gt;Kōsō Wasan&lt;/em&gt; (『高僧和讃』, the “Japanese Hymns of Praise of the Virtuous Priest”), a collection of hymns written by the founder of the sect, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.learnreligions.com/shinran-449983&quot;&gt;Shinran (親鸞)&lt;/a&gt;, who lived between 1173 and 1263 and was a remarkable person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, these are the two final hymns from “Twenty-six Hymns based on the Writings of Master Shan-tao”. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chinabuddhismencyclopedia.com/en/index.php?title=Shan-tao&quot;&gt;Shan-tao&lt;/a&gt; is one of the seven masters (patriarchs) of Shinshū. He lived from 613 to 681 and is generally credited for popularizing the &lt;em&gt;nembutsu&lt;/em&gt; as the reciting of Amida’s name (see below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-meaning&quot;&gt;The meaning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complete works of Shinran in English translation are available &lt;a href=&quot;http://shinranworks.com/&quot;&gt;on line&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://shinranworks.com/hymns-in-japanese/hymns-of-the-pure-land-masters/shan-tao/&quot;&gt;translation of the two hymns&lt;/a&gt; taken from there is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Had we not received the power of the universal Vow,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;When can we part from this Saha world?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Reflecting deeply on the Buddha’s benevolence,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Let us think on Amida always.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Casting off long kalpas of painful existence in this world of Saha,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;We live in expectation of the Pure Land, the uncreated;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;That is the power of our teacher, Shakyamuni;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Let us respond always in gratitude for his compassion and benevolence.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pure Land Buddhism holds that there is a kind of Paradise called the Pure Land, and once one is there it is easier to reach Nirvana. Shinran advocated to trust to the power of Amitābha (&lt;em&gt;Amida&lt;/em&gt;), as made manifest in his Universal Vow, to attain enlightenment. The main Jōdo Shinshū practice is called &lt;em&gt;nembutsu&lt;/em&gt;, “Mindfulness of the Buddha”. The nembutsu is simply reciting the phrase &lt;em&gt;Namu Amida Butsu&lt;/em&gt; (“I take refuge in Amitābha Buddha”, written 南無阿弥陀佛). For more information see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.shinbuddhism.info/kw86.htm&quot;&gt;the detailed discussion of the meaning of the hymns&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-conclusion&quot;&gt;The conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is yet another example of how reading Japanese remains a difficult but very stimulating activity for me: there are lots of riddles to be solved. In translation, most of the mystery disappears. And every time I look into such a little mystery, I learn lots of new things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The banner picture is of the Nishi Hongan-ji (本願寺, Temple of the Primal Vow)) in Kyōto, the largest of all the Jōdo Shinshū branches.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>The four wisdoms</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/four-wisdoms/"/>
        <updated>2020-10-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/four-wisdoms</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/four-wisdoms_1600x600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;A friend asked me about if I knew a Japanese Buddhist prayer suitable for a funeral. I knew that at funerals and memorial services, the monks chant Buddhist text in &lt;em&gt;bongo&lt;/em&gt; (梵語), a Japanese transliteration of Sanskrit. The practice is known as &lt;em&gt;shōmyō&lt;/em&gt; (声明) and a text that is often chanted is called &lt;em&gt;shichi&lt;/em&gt; (四智), “the Four Wisdoms”, or &lt;em&gt;shichibongo&lt;/em&gt; (四智梵語) in full.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-four-wisdoms-text-in-japanese&quot;&gt;The Four Wisdoms text in Japanese&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, &lt;em&gt;shōmyō&lt;/em&gt; texts are written using specific and quite unusual Chinese characters, but they are used purely for their phonetic value, not for their meaning. Here is the text in full, from the site of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.buzan.or.jp/index-1-1.html&quot;&gt;Buzan sect&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.philtar.ac.uk/encyclopedia/easia/shingon.html&quot;&gt;Shingon Buddhism&lt;/a&gt;. It also has a recording of the chanting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/shingon_kongoukai.avif&quot; alt=&quot;Chinese characters written left-to-right, top-to-bottom, columns of irregular length&quot; title=&quot;Chinese characters written left-to-right, top-to-bottom, columns of irregular length&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Four Wisdoms in kanji and hiragana, from the site of the Buzan sect&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same text with only very minor differences is used also by the sects of &lt;a href=&quot;https://tendaiuk.com/tendai-buddhism/&quot;&gt;Tendai Buddhism&lt;/a&gt;, but I focus here on Shingon only for convenience. The word &lt;em&gt;shingon&lt;/em&gt; (真言, lit. “True Words”) is the translation of the Sanskrit word Mantra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-the-japanese-text-to-the-original-sanskrit&quot;&gt;From the Japanese text to the original Sanskrit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found the &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;katakana&lt;/em&gt; for this text in &lt;a href=&quot;https://tais.repo.nii.ac.jp/?action=repository_action_common_download&amp;amp;item_id=450&amp;amp;item_no=1&amp;amp;attribute_id=22&amp;amp;file_no=1&quot;&gt;a Japanese academic paper on the meaning of the &lt;em&gt;shichibongo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;四智梵語&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
オム　バザラ　サトバ　ソギャラカ&lt;br /&gt;
唵　　嚩日囉　薩怛嚩　蘇蘗　囉賀&lt;br /&gt;
バザラ　アラタンノウ　マドタラン&lt;br /&gt;
嚩日囉　囉　怛　曩　　摩覩怛覧&lt;br /&gt;
バザラ　タラマ　キャヤタイ&lt;br /&gt;
嚩日囉　達　麽　誐　夜那&lt;br /&gt;
バザラ　キャラマ　キャロ　ハムバ&lt;br /&gt;
嚩日囉　羯　　磨　迦　嚕　婆　縛&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This transliterates in &lt;em&gt;romaji&lt;/em&gt; as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;shichibongo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;om bazara-satoba sogyaraka&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;bazara-aratannou madotaran&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;bazara-tarama kyayatai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;bazara-kyarama kyaro hamba&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same paper also gave the original Sanskrit phrasing, transliterated in the roman alphabet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;oṃ vajrasattva samgrahād&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;vajraratnam anuttaraṃ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;vajradharma gāyanair&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;vajrakarma karo bhava&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-does-the-sanskrit-text-say&quot;&gt;What does the Sanskrit text say?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sanskrit version allowed me to search for a translation. I found one in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.routledgehandbooks.com/doi/10.4324/9781315172354.ch3&quot;&gt;a book on Japanese music&lt;/a&gt; that discussed &lt;em&gt;shōmyō&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oṃ.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Receiving the blessing of the wisdom of Vajra-sattva,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;we obtain the ultimate vajra-ratna.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;By chanting the vajra-dharma,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;we may attain the vajra-karma of enlightenment.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not familiar with esoteric Buddhism so I found this translation hard to understand. I therefore looked a bit further into this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-background-on-esoteric-buddhism&quot;&gt;Some background on esoteric Buddhism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we need to know about &lt;em&gt;Vajrayana&lt;/em&gt;, also know as Esoteric  Buddhism, the Buddhist tradition of which Shingon Buddhism is a branch. According to the according to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/topic/Vajrayana&quot;&gt;Encyclopaedia Britannica&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vajrayana, (Sanskrit: “Diamond Vehicle” or “Thunderbolt Vehicle”) form of Tantric Buddhism that developed in India and neighbouring countries, notably Tibet. Vajrayana, in the history of Buddhism, marks the transition from Mahayana speculative thought to the enactment of Buddhist ideas in individual life. The term vajra (Sanskrit: “diamond” or “thunderbolt” ) is used to signify the absolutely real and indestructible in a human being, as opposed to the fictions an individual entertains about himself and his nature; yana is the spiritual pursuit of the ultimately valuable and indestructible.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/topic/Buddhism/Vajrayana-Tantric-or-Esoteric-Buddhism&quot;&gt;further&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vajrayana first emerged in various parts of India and Sri Lanka. The esoteric nature of Tantric doctrine and practice makes identifying the origins of the Vajrayana school difficult, but some Buddhist traditions associate them with Nagarjuna and Asanga and therefore suggest that Vajrayana began to develop quietly in the 2nd or 4th century CE. Vajrayana was prominent in India and Tibet, and a form of it spread to China and then to Japan, where it became associated with the Tendai and Shingon schools.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, we need to know about the concept of the &lt;em&gt;mandala&lt;/em&gt;. Again according to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/topic/mandala-diagram&quot;&gt;Encyclopaedia Britannica&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mandala, (Sanskrit: “circle”) in Hindu and Buddhist Tantrism, a symbolic diagram used in the performance of sacred rites and as an instrument of meditation. The mandala is basically a representation of the universe, a consecrated area that serves as a receptacle for the gods and as a collection point of universal forces.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-mandala-of-the-diamond-realm&quot;&gt;The Mandala of the Diamond Realm&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shingon Buddhism makes frequent use of two &lt;em&gt;mandalas&lt;/em&gt;, the Mandala of the Womb Realm and the Mandala of the Diamond Realm (Kongōkai Mandala, 金剛界 曼荼羅). &lt;em&gt;kongō&lt;/em&gt; (金剛) means “diamond” or “adamant, and is a translation of the Sanskrit “vajra”. These realms and their composition are based on an esoteric Buddhist sutra called the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.shingon.org/teachings/ShingonMikkyo/KongochoKyo.html&quot;&gt;Vajrasekhara Sutra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Diamond Realm (金剛界 Kongōkai) is a metaphysical space inhabited by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thezengateway.com/teachings/the-five-wisdom-buddhas-vairocana&quot;&gt;Five Wisdom Buddhas&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Shingon Buddhism, there is a group of deities, known as the Vajra Bodhisattva. The “Four Wisdoms” refers to the four Vajra Bodhisattva that surround &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.shingon.org/teachings/ShingonMikkyo/Dainichi.html&quot;&gt;Dainichi Nyorai&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.onmarkproductions.com/html/mandala-guidebook.html&quot;&gt;Shiin-e (四印会) section&lt;/a&gt; of the Kongōkai Mandala.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/Kongokai-shiin-e.avif&quot; alt=&quot;Detail of the Kongōkai Mandala showing five seated Buddha-like figures arranges in a cross, within a circle&quot; title=&quot;Detail of the Kongōkai Mandala showing five seated Buddha-like figures arranges in a cross, within a circle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Shiin-e (四印会) and ichiin-e (一印会) sections of the Kongōkai Mandala, Heian period, 9th century (Tōji Temple, Kyōto, National Treasure) (https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Kongokai.avif)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dainichi Nyorai (大日如来) is the Buddha in the highest form of existence, dharmakaya, &lt;em&gt;hosshin&lt;/em&gt; (法身) in Japanese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;finally-back-to-the-four-wisdoms&quot;&gt;Finally, back to the Four Wisdoms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus the Four Wisdoms of the text refer to these four Vajra Bodhisattva:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kongōsatta 金剛薩埵 ( Vajra-sattva, “diamond being”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kongōhō 金剛宝 ( Vajra-ratna, “diamond treasure”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kongōhō 金剛法 ( Vajra-dharma, “diamond law”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kongōgyō 金剛業 ( Vadra-karma, “diamond action” ).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the explanation on the site of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.buzan.or.jp/index-1-1.html&quot;&gt;Buzan sect&lt;/a&gt;, these four bodhisattva are identified with the four wisdom buddha surrounding Dainichi Nyorai in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thezengateway.com/teachings/the-five-wisdom-buddhas-vairocana&quot;&gt;Five Wisdom Buddhas&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Four Wisdoms represents the wisdom of the four Wisdom Buddhas, and by making offerings to each other, the Four Wisdoms represent the entire mandala of Vajrayana, with Dainichi Nyorai in the center.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/902px-Kongokai.avif&quot; alt=&quot;The Kongōkai Mandala, consisting of nine panels, three by three. Eight of them are  showing five seated Buddha-like figures arranges in a cross, within a circle. The middle panel in the top row shows a single larger seated Buddha-like figure.&quot; title=&quot;The Kongōkai Mandala, consisting of nine panels, three by three. Eight of them are  showing five seated Buddha-like figures arranges in a cross, within a circle. The middle panel in the top row shows a single larger seated Buddha-like figure.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Kongōkai Mandala, Heian period, 9th century (Tōji Temple, Kyōto, National Treasure) (https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Kongokai.avif)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The banner picture is of the Great Buddha of Kamakura.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Frozen yoghurt with dates</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/frozen-yoghurt/"/>
        <updated>2020-07-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/frozen-yoghurt</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/frozen-yoghurt_1600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;This is a simple and low-tech recipe for frozen yoghurt with just two ingredients. It uses dates as a natural source of sugar. The amounts are for two portions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;250 g Greek style yoghurt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50 g Medjool dates, pitted and chopped&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon candied orange peel (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put the yoghurt, dates and orange peel in a freezer-safe container and stir.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For the lazy way, place the mixture in the fridge for a few hours or overnight (so the dates will dissolve) and stir; for the quick way, blend the mixture.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put the container in the freezer for 20 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stir the mixture well. Make sure to loosen ice forming on the walls of the container and to mix it in.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Repeat the freezing and stirring until you get the desired consistency. For soft ice texture this will take about four more cycles, for a more solid texture about seven.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>About reading Murakami as a way to learn Japanese</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/learning-japanese-reading-murakami/"/>
        <updated>2020-07-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/learning-japanese-reading-murakami</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/learning-japanese-reading-murakami_1600x600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in my previous posts (&lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/reading-murakami/&quot;&gt;Reading Murakami in Japanese&lt;/a&gt;,
   &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/more-on-learning-japanese/&quot;&gt;Some tips for reading Japanese as a learner&lt;/a&gt;,
   &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/learning-japanese/&quot;&gt;My journey of learning Japanese&lt;/a&gt;), I started reading Murakami Haruki’s “1Q84” in Japanese in October 2014. The paperback version consists of 6 volumes (2 for each Book), 2,057 pages in total. At the end of June 2020, I finally finished the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had started learning Japanese in early 2011 in preparation for a research trip. Unfortunately because of the tsunami and the nuclear disaster the trip didn’t go ahead. But I did go to Japan for two months in the summer of 2012 and again in the summer of 2014. So I had been learning Japanese for about four years and had four months of a more or less immersive experience before I started on the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I had been learning Japanese  in a rather haphazard, not very systematic way, because I felt it was more fun that way. Nevertheless, I had put in a considerable amount of time and effort.
I took some group lessons but they did not continue beyond the very basics. Then I took one-to-one lessons with a Japanese teacher, which was a much better way to learn. The lessons focused on conversation and grammar but we didn’t cover kanji. I started learning kanji using several apps. The one I’ve been using most consistently is Memrise, to study the meanings of the Jouyou kanji. I don’t like mnemonics-based methods like Heisig’s, and I’ve paid the price for that, because apparently with that method you can learn all readings and meanings for all 2,136 Jouyou kanji in a few months. Whereas all these years later, I still have to practise every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what did I learn through reading Murakami? Despite &lt;a href=&quot;http://selftaughtjapanese.com/2016/07/08/what-its-like-reading-haruki-murakami-novels-in-their-original-japanese/&quot;&gt;what others may say&lt;/a&gt;, I learned that reading Murakami is hard. Initially, a page took me more than half an hour. Now, after six years, it takes me about five minutes, but that is still much lower than my English reading speed: reading the same passage in English only takes a minute. Arguably Murakami’s writing style is comparatively straightforward, and personally I had (even) more difficulty reading Banana Yoshimoto’s “Tokage” than 1Q84, but that doesn’t mean that I found Murakami easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I determined, despite that or because of it, not to give up. I kept going, a few pages at a time. Eventually I got there.
I found that reading with a dictionary and looking up the readings and meanings of any character or word I didn’t know is not only wonderfully engaging but also really works as a way to learn Japanese. My reading skills have improved dramatically, and so have my vocabulary and my grasp of grammar. As a result, my writing, listing and speaking skills have also improved. So on the whole, I would recommend reading a Japanese novel as a way of learning Japanese, if you are not in a hurry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I also learned I still have so much to learn. I still don’t know all readings for the Jouyou kanji, and keep forgetting the meanings. I still struggle with conversation (although that may partly be as a result of my tendency of overcomplicating things and wanting to be too precise) and with handwriting. I started handwriting practice in 2018. It requires a better understanding of the structure of the kanji, but it is fun and my recall is improving. I still have a long way to go before I’ll be able to write all Jouyou kanji.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have written down some of my observations before: &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/reading-murakami/&quot;&gt;Reading Murakami in Japanese&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/more-on-learning-japanese/&quot;&gt;Some tips for reading Japanese as a learner&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/learning-japanese/&quot;&gt;My journey of learning Japanese&lt;/a&gt;. One specific thing I started noticing only when reading the last two volumes of 1Q84 is that, when I see a word and I think I can’t pronounce it, often it turns out I can after all, if I just make a little more effort, a kind of mental jump into the unknown. There is a wonderful Japanese expression for this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kiyomizu no butai kara tobioriru&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;清水の舞台から飛び降りる&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(きよみずのぶたいからとびおりる)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which literally translates as “to jump off the platform of the Kiyomizu-dera temple”, but means “to make a leap into the dark”. (The platform of the beautiful and ancient Kiyomizu-dera temple in Kyoto offers great views but is also twelve metres high, so jumping off it may not be a good idea.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recall is sometimes more about daring rather than about remembering: rather than going for conscious recall, trust your unconscious mind to pick the right reading. You actually remember more than you think you remember.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;coda-the-novel-itself&quot;&gt;Coda: the novel itself&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may wonder: having spent nearly six years reading it, do I think it is a good book? I do. It was certainly for the most part entertaining and interesting. I have written three posts about various remarkable points in the book (&lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/repetition-in-1Q84/&quot;&gt;Repetition in Murakami’s 1Q84&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/1Q84-kuukisanagi/&quot;&gt;Why the ‘Little People’ say ‘Ho ho’&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/cold-or-not/&quot;&gt;Cold or not: a riddle in Murakami’s 1Q84&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are there aspects I don’t like? Yes. The ending leaves me wanting to know what happened to the other characters. Also, there is a bit too much repetition, which I think is a consequence of the book being published in three parts, and in every part Murakami (or his publisher) has felt it necessary to provide sufficient background on what happened before so that each part can be read on its own. There are some parts that I found a bit slow, because I was impatient to get back to the plot, but usually even these parts were actually quite interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, will I ever re-read it? Maybe, if my Japanese reading speed ever gets close to my English one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The banner picture is the dragon-shaped spout of the water basin at the entrance of the Kiyomizu-dera temple in Kyoto&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Brownies with dates and walnuts</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/brownies/"/>
        <updated>2020-06-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/brownies</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/brownies_1600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;This is a simple and quick recipe for delicious brownies with very few ingredients. It uses dates as a natural source of sugar. The rich high-cocoa content chocolate makes butter unnecessary so they happen to be vegan. The amounts are for two brownies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50 g dark chocolate (70% cocoa)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;25 g extra dark chocolate (85% cocoa)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50 g Medjool dates, pitted and chopped&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50 self-rising white wheat flour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5 tablespoons tepid water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;12 g walnuts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon candied orange peel (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heat the chocolate au bain marie, ideally at 35 °C.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the chocolate has melted, gradually add the flour, mixing thoroughly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add 2 tablespoons of water, mix well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then add the dates and the organge peel, mix well while adding in the rest of the water. The mixture must be moist and stick together.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then add the walnuts. You can also simply push the walnuts into the dough just before baking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put the mixture in small ramekins lined with aluminium foil.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Preheat the oven on 160 °C and bake for 25 minutes at 160 °C.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leave to cool in the ramekins.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Cold or not: a riddle in Murakami&apos;s 1Q84</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/cold-or-not/"/>
        <updated>2020-06-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/cold-or-not</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/cold-or-not_1600x600.avif&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/reading-murakami&quot;&gt;mentioned before&lt;/a&gt;, I have been slowly reading Haruki Murakami’s novel 1Q84 in Japanese. Like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/23/magazine/the-fierce-imagination-of-haruki-murakami.html&quot;&gt;all his novels&lt;/a&gt;, this novel is many things. For this article I want to view it as a reflection on morality. Almost all of the characters have to make complex moral choices based on incomplete or incorrect information. One such character is Tamaru, a bodyguard and security expert in the service of a rich old widow who has embarked on a personal crusade against domestic violence. He is at the same time a very cultured person and a consummate professional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this article is really about a something that puzzled me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one of the final chapters (Chapter 25 of Book 3), just before he has to make a very hard moral choice, Tamaru recounts an interesting story about the famous Swiss psychologist Carl Gustav Jung. He explains how Jung lived in a large house in Zürich, but wanted a place to think and work in solitude. So he built a place which he called the “Tower”, in Bollingen near the shore of the Zürich lake. He built it with his own hands from stones from a local quarry, and had to join the guild become a licensed stone mason to be allowed to do so. It was an austere place, without gas, electricity or running water. On the lintel above the entrance, Jung engraved a phrase which in Japanese reads:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;冷たくても、冷たくなくても、神はここにいる&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tsumetakutemo, tsumetakunakutemo, kami wa koko ni iru&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the English translation by Philip Gabriel, this runs “Cold or Not, God Is Present”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This phrase is also the title of the chapter, and I think that because of this story about Jung, this chapter might very well be the key chapter of the entire novel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was intrigued by the phrase and started to read up on Jung, to try and find out more about this story. It turns out that the story as told by Tamaru is not entirely accurate: Jung did indeed build the tower with his own hands. He started building it in 1923, when he was 48, and worked on it and reshaped it for most of the rest of his life &lt;a href=&quot;https://thefirstgates.com/2014/01/02/jungs-tower-simplicity-and-the-inner-life/&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. And he did put an inscription above the entrance of the original tower. It is the same inscription that was first engraved over the entrance of his house in Küsnacht &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jungatlanta.com/articles/summer14-two-houses.pdf&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the words as mentioned by Tamaru are different from the inscription. The original inscription is in Latin and reads “Vocatus atque non vocatus deus aderit”, which translates as “Bidden or unbidden, the god will be present”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The origin of this phrase is interesting: the Latin phrase is from the Adagia, a collection of sayings from ancient sources collected by Erasmus. The actual source is the  “History of the Peloponnesian War”, written around 400 BC by the Athenian historian and general Thucydides. In it, he recounts how the Spartans asked the Oracle of Apollo in Delphi if it would go well with them if they went to war with Athens. The oracle answered that if they put all their strength into the war, victory would be theirs, and that “the god himself would be there, whether invoked or uninvoked” &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.harvardreview.org/content/culled-and-not-culled-the-poet-will-be-there/#return-link-5&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jung himself knew this background, and he commented “It says: yes, the god will be on the spot, but in what form and to what purpose? I have put the inscription there to remind my patients and myself: Timor dei initium sapientiae.” (Fear of God is the start of wisdom) &lt;a href=&quot;http://carljungdepthpsychology.blogspot.com/2017/03/carl-jung-it-is-delphic-oracle-though.html&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. Jung’s view on religion was that people need a God because a person needs to recognise a higher authority than the ego. Without a God, a person will make a God out of something else. So there will be a God in people’s lives, whether they want it or not, for good or for worse. Hence the choice of the phrase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the original phrase is different from Tamaru’s quote, either Tamaru has it wrong, or in the parallel universe of 1Q84, the inscription is different. That is of course very well possible: as the novel makes clear, 1Q84 is superficially the same as 1984 but differs from it in many subtle ways; Tamaru being a person who is very precise in his mental habits, it is not so likely that he would not have checked the translation of a phrase which he considers so important. In fact, he comments that “There’s some deep allusion here, something difficult to interpret.”. So I am assuming that in the 1Q84 universe, the inscription is different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am of course not the first one to point this out &lt;a href=&quot;http://hyoshiok.hatenablog.com/entry/20130617/p1&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;, and several people have surmised that this is a pun on cold/called, [&lt;a href=&quot;https://chazzw.wordpress.com/2011/11/13/more-of-the-things-you-learn-in-books/&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&quot;https://citronimus.de/haruki-murakami-1q84/&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;] because a possible English translation of the Latin phrase is “Called or uncalled, God is present”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As explained above, this is only one possible translation – “vocatus” could be translated as “bidden” or “summoned” as well, and “the god” is more accurate than “God” – and somehow I find this theory not satisfactory.
At first sight, the cold/called theory may seem to be corroborated because Tamaru mentions that the Catholic orphanage where he grew up was always cold, even in summer. However, in Japanese, Tamaru there uses the word “samui” (寒い) which means that it felt cold to him, whereas in the phrase he uses the word “tsumetai” (冷たい), which means that something is cold. Because of his experience in that cruel place, he also says that as far as he is concerned, if God existed, He could not be said to be kind at all. The Japanese adjective shinsetsu (親切,しんせつ) which he uses means “kind,” but is used to describe the character of someone based on their actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am therefore inclined to interpret the “tsumetai” as “emotionally cold, unfeeling, indifferent”. In other words, God is here, but we don’t know if he is indifferent or not. That is to my mind also closer to Jung’s own interpretation of the Latin phrase, and yet different of course, as might be expected in 1Q84.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think it is a coincidence that Murakami introduces Jung at the end of this novel. Arguably, the actions of many of the characters match Jung’s views on good and evil. For example Ushikawa, who is the protagonist of the chapter, and quite a creep, is at some point shown his dark side (&lt;a href=&quot;http://compassreview.org/summer03/6.html&quot;&gt;what Jung calls the Shadow&lt;/a&gt;) but decides to embrace it instead of reject it. 
 And it is not a stretch to view the Little People as a kind of collective god: they have no individuality but collectively they have supernatural powers. They are also clearly not bound by human morals, and are (not unlike the Greek gods) quite indifferent to the fate of humans. And they speak through a human, i.e. a prophet, or an oracle. Considering that Jung developed the theory of the collective unconscious, and the notion of archetypes, having a collective god seems fitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The banner picture of this article is the cover of the 2nd volume of Book 3 in the Japanese paperback. In Japanese, “1Q84” and “1984” are both pronounced as “ichi-kew-hachi-yon”, that’s why this is written underneath the title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cover illustration for each volume is a detail of &lt;a href=&quot;https://archief.ntr.nl/tuinderlusten/en.html&quot;&gt;“The Garden of Earthly Delights” by Jheronimus Bosch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;a href=&quot;https://thefirstgates.com/2014/01/02/jungs-tower-simplicity-and-the-inner-life/&quot;&gt;Jung’s Tower: simplicity and the inner life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jungatlanta.com/articles/summer14-two-houses.pdf&quot;&gt;A Tale  of Two  Houses: Küsnacht and Bollingen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.harvardreview.org/content/culled-and-not-culled-the-poet-will-be-there/#return-link-5&quot;&gt;Culled and Not Culled, the Poet Will Be There&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4] &lt;a href=&quot;http://carljungdepthpsychology.blogspot.com/2017/03/carl-jung-it-is-delphic-oracle-though.html&quot;&gt; Carl Jung: It is a Delphic oracle though.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5] &lt;a href=&quot;http://hyoshiok.hatenablog.com/entry/20130617/p1&quot;&gt;冷たくても、冷たくなくても、神はここにいるの謎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6] &lt;a href=&quot;https://chazzw.wordpress.com/2011/11/13/more-of-the-things-you-learn-in-books/&quot;&gt;More…of The Things You Learn in Books&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7] &lt;a href=&quot;https://citronimus.de/haruki-murakami-1q84/&quot;&gt;Haruki Murakami: 1Q84 (in German)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8] &lt;a href=&quot;http://compassreview.org/summer03/6.html&quot;&gt;Jung and the moral self&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>