<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title>Quick and Tasty - Get Cooking!</title>
    <generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
		<icon>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/apple-touch-icon-precomposed.png</icon>
    <subtitle>Quick and Tasty</subtitle>
    <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2019-03-31T19:33:23+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</id>
    <author>
			<name>Wim</name>
			<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
			
		</author>

    
    <entry>
        <title>Orzo with celeriac, mixed mushrooms and tofu sticks</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/orzo-celeriac-mushrooms-tofu-sticks/"/>
        <updated>2019-03-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/orzo-celeriac-mushrooms-tofu-sticks</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/orzo-celeriac-mushrooms-tofu-sticks_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;Orzo is durum wheat pasta shaped like grains of barley (called &lt;em&gt;orzo&lt;/em&gt; in Italian). In this recipe it is combined with celeriac and mixed mushrooms (oyster, shiitake, eryngii). The less common ingredient is &lt;a href=&quot;https://shop.waiyeehong.com/food-ingredients/dried-products/dried-beancurd-seaweed/dried-beancurd-sticks-tofu-bamboo-2?language=tw&quot;&gt;dried tofu (bean curd) sticks&lt;/a&gt;. For the seasoning I also used &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/nabe-yellow-peppers-celeriac-shiitake-tofu/index.html&quot;&gt;fermented broad bean paste (tobanjan)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegan&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#30-minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;30-minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;725 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#600-800kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_3.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fresh ingredients &amp;amp; groceries
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;400 g celeriac&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;150-200 g mixed mushrooms&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 cm ginger, finely chopped&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 clove garlic&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;70 g dried tofu sticks&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From the store cupboard
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cup of orzo&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;3 dried tomatoes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/2 teaspoon &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt; paste&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/2 teaspoon &lt;em&gt;tobanjan&lt;/em&gt; (broad bean paste)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon tomato puree&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon mirin&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons sesame seeds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon sunflower seeds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon pine kernels&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/2 teaspoon ground coriander&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/2 teaspoon soy sauce&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soak the tofu sticks in very hot water for 30 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wash and peel the celeriac and chop it into small pieces (~ 1 cm).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If desired, wash the mushrooms, and chop them into small pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bring 2 l water for the orzo to the boil, with the dried tomatoes, and cook the orzo for 4 minutes over high heat. Switch off the hob and leave it for 8 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take out the dried tomatoes and chop them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meanwhile
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cook the celeriac for 5 minutes in the microwave at full power (900W).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Drain the cooking liquid of the celeriac in a small bowl and mix in the tomato puree, &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;tobanjan&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;mirin&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Drain the tofu sticks and cut them into pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Heat the oil in a deep pan. When the oil is hot, add the ginger, garlic, sesame seeds and sunflower seeds and fry for a few minutes over medium heat.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the mushrooms and fry over medium heat until they just start to brown.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the coriander and the soy sauce to the pan.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the celeriac and tofu sticks to the pan and cook until lightly browned.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Turn the heat very low.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the tomato puree mixture and the dried tomatoes to the pan&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Drain the orzo and add it to the pan.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Season pepper to taste.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Getting started with vegan cooking</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/balanced-vegan-meals/"/>
        <updated>2019-03-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/balanced-vegan-meals</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/balanced-vegan-meals_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;h2 id=&quot;going-vegan&quot;&gt;Going vegan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have recently decided or are considering to become vegan, it’s important to get off to a good start. Going vegan is great but there are some common pitfals if you come from a omnivorous diet. Just cutting out all non-plant-based food might leave you feeling dissatisfied, and craving some of your old food. If your vegan meals are not nutritiously balanced, this will also affect your health. Both are common reasons why people give up on a vegan diet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that making balanced and tasty vegan meals is quite easy. You could of course just make &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegan&quot;&gt;one of my recipes&lt;/a&gt;, but if you want to make your own, here are a few simple guidelines, &lt;a href=&quot;#resources&quot;&gt;supported by expert nutritional advice&lt;/a&gt;. But let’s first have a look at the fundamentals of a healthy diet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fundamentals-of-a-healthy-diet&quot;&gt;Fundamentals of a healthy diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A healthy diet should provide your body with the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Proteins&lt;/em&gt;, for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protein_(nutrient)&quot;&gt;growth and maintenance&lt;/a&gt;. Our bodies do not use the proteins we eat directly, but break them down into amino acids.  There are nine essential amino acids which we must obtain from our diet to prevent &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protein%E2%80%93energy_malnutrition&quot;&gt;protein-energy malnutrition&lt;/a&gt;. Making sure our meals contain sufficient amounts of these is easy, there are several foods such as beans and pulses that are “complete proteins” which provide all essential amino acids.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vitamins and minerals&lt;/em&gt; , &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nhs.uk/conditions/vitamins-and-minerals/&quot;&gt;nutrients our bodies need in small amounts to work properly and stay healthy&lt;/a&gt;. From this angle, there is not much difference between a vegan diet and other diets, with the exception of vitamin B12. As there are no plant-based sources, this needs to be taken as a supplement.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Essential fatty acids&lt;/em&gt; , needed for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/B9780702054013000278&quot;&gt;many physiological processes&lt;/a&gt;, including maintenance of cell membrane structure and skin integrity. There are only two of them, omega-3 and omega-6 fatty acids. Again, they are easy to add to your diet: several types of nuts, seeds and vegetable oils are good sources.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Carbohydrates&lt;/em&gt;, for energy and to aid digestion. Although recently “carbs” got a bad reputation, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bupa.co.uk/health-information/nutrition-diet/carbohydrates&quot;&gt;they are really essential for a healthy diet&lt;/a&gt;. There are three main types of carbohydrates: sugar,  starch, and fibre. For a healthy diet we need all of them, in the right amounts. The main sources are typical starchy foods like rice, pasta and potatoes. The less refined the food, the better as a source of fibre.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not really neccessary to have all components for every meal though, as long as your diet on the whole provides them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;simple-guidelines&quot;&gt;Simple guidelines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That may seem like a lot to take in. So how do you make sure you get all these on a daily basis? I use as a very simple rule that my meals should have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A source of protein. Based on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protein_Digestibility_Corrected_Amino_Acid_Score&quot;&gt;“Protein Digestibility Corrected Amino Acid Score”&lt;/a&gt;, the best sources are tofu, soy beans, chick peas and black beans, but other types of beans or pulses are good too. I use about 100 g per person per meal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A source of starchy carbohydrates, such as rice, pasta and other grain-based foods, or potatoes and similar root vegetables. For rice or pasta I use about 100 g per person per meal, for potatoes about 250g.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A source of fresh vegetables, whatever you like, but as much variety as possible.  These provide you with vitamins and some of the minerals, as well as some carbohydrates and protein. I use about 200 g per person per meal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some nuts or seeds, like pumkin seeds, sunflower seeds or walnuts. These are great sources of omega fatty acids and minerals. Just a handful is enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these guidelines, you can be confident your vegan meals are balanced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes&quot;&gt;Quick &amp;amp; Tasty recipes&lt;/a&gt; follow this pattern. Why not get started with some of my favourites:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Very quick and easy to make: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/murakami-2/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;soba&lt;/em&gt; noodles with &lt;em&gt;edamame&lt;/em&gt; soy beans.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Very simple: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/carrots-potatoes-chickpeas/&quot;&gt;a stir-fry  of carrots, potatoes and chickpeas.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A bit more special: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/butternut-squash-pear-blackeyed-beans/&quot;&gt;a stir-fry of butternut squash, pear and black-eyed beans with brown rice.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nhs.uk/live-well/eat-well/the-vegan-diet/&quot;&gt;NHS advice on vegan diet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://med.libretexts.org/Bookshelves/Nutrition/Book%3A_An_Introduction_to_Nutrition_(Zimmerman)&quot;&gt;An Introduction to Nutrition (Zimmerman), a free textbook from the LibreTexts library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hsph.harvard.edu/nutritionsource/&quot;&gt;Harvard School of Public Health’s “Nutrition Source”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Why the &#39;Little People&#39; say &#39;Ho ho&#39;</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/1Q84-kuukisanagi/"/>
        <updated>2019-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/1Q84-kuukisanagi</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/1Q84-kuukisanagi_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/learning-japanese/&quot;&gt;previous posts&lt;/a&gt;, I have been reading Haruki Murakami’s 1Q84 in Japanese (very slowly). After reading some reviews I wrote &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/repetition-in-1Q84&quot;&gt;a blog post&lt;/a&gt; on why some of the characters frequently repeat one another, something critics didn’t like. Another thing several critics din’t like is the Little People saying “Ho ho”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s have a look at this “Ho ho”. But first, in case you didn’t read the book, a quick setting of the scene may help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;air-chrysalys&quot;&gt;Air Chrysalys&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1Q84, there is a “book in the book” called “Air Chrysalys” (&lt;em&gt;kuukisanagi&lt;/em&gt;, 空気さなぎ). This book is a kind of fairytale told from the perspective of a ten-year-old girl who lives in a rural commune. As punishment for letting an old mountain goat die, she gets locked up in a shed with the dead goat for a period of ten days&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One night, the “Little People”&lt;sup&gt;**&lt;/sup&gt; appear from the mouth of the dead goat. This scene starts with one of my favourite descriptions in the Japanese text:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;あたりが暗くなると、死んだ山羊の目が星明かりを受けてきらりと光った。&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;atari ga kuraku naru to, shinda yagi no me ga hoshiakari wo ukete kirari to hikatta.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the English translation by Jay Rubin, this reads:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When darkness falls, the dead goat’s eye sparkles in the starlight.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Japanese sentence sparkles a bit more because &lt;em&gt;kirari to&lt;/em&gt; means “with a momentary flash of light” and &lt;em&gt;hikatta&lt;/em&gt; means shine or glitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Murakami puts the reader nicely on the wrong foot, because when six small figures emerge from the goat’s mouth, the little girl thinks “This is like Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs, but there is one missing”. The “Little People” read her thoughts and when she counts again there are seven of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with the girl they start to make an “air chrysalys” by pulling white threads out of thin air and weaving a kind of cocoon from them. While doing so, they talk to the girl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ho-ho-says-the-keeper-of-the-beat&quot;&gt;“Ho ho,” says the keeper of the beat&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Little People don’t have names or personalities and indeed it is impossible to keep them apart or even describe them in detail, but they have distinct voices. Usually, each of them speaks a short sentence in turn.
There is a recurrent pattern where one of them, in translation called the “keeper of the beat”, says “Ho ho”, and the others chorus “Ho ho”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;｢ほうほう｣はやし役のリトル・ピープルがはやした &lt;br /&gt;
｢ほうほう｣残りの六人が声を合わせた &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“houhou” hayashiyaku no RITORU PIIPURU ga hayashita&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;“houhou” nokori no rokunin ga koe wo awaseta&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Japanese text, the “keeper of the beat” is called &lt;em&gt;hayashiyaku&lt;/em&gt; (はやし役) and calls out &lt;em&gt;houhou&lt;/em&gt; (ほうほう). This matters because if this “Ho ho” was merely an interjection or exclamation, it would likely be written &lt;em&gt;hoohoo&lt;/em&gt; (ほぉほぉ or ほおほお). So we can assume that &lt;em&gt;houhou&lt;/em&gt; has a meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Japanese has many homonyms and this is no exception. There are several possible ways to write &lt;em&gt;houhou&lt;/em&gt;, in &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; (Chinese characters), each with a different meaning. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kotobank.jp/word/%E3%81%BB%E3%81%86%E3%81%BB%E3%81%86-628513#E7.B2.BE.E9.81.B8.E7.89.88.20.E6.97.A5.E6.9C.AC.E5.9B.BD.E8.AA.9E.E5.A4.A7.E8.BE.9E.E5.85.B8&quot;&gt;Kotobank&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;houhou&lt;/em&gt; (ほうほう) means&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;① 物を投げたりたたいたりする音、またはそのさまを表わす語。ぽんぽん。&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The sound of repeatedly throwing or striking something, or a word to representing it”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the kanji writings of &lt;em&gt;houhou&lt;/em&gt; (ほうほう) is 彭々), which makes the meaning more clear because the character 彭 means “the sound of a drum”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because Murakami wrote the word in hiragana, we can’t be entirely sure, but the meanings of the other kanji writings (這々 perplexity, 方法 method) do not make much sense in the given context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-link-with-noh-theatre&quot;&gt;The link with Noh theatre&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the Little People, who Murakami calls the &lt;em&gt;hayashiyaku&lt;/em&gt;, calls out “Ho ho”, and the other six echo this in chorus. The translator of the book, the great Jay Rubin, translates  &lt;em&gt;hayashiyaku&lt;/em&gt; as “keeper of the beat” to reflect the meaning of &lt;em&gt;houhou&lt;/em&gt; as drum beat, and also because Murakami uses the verb &lt;em&gt;hayasu&lt;/em&gt; which literally means “to keep time”. So “says the keeper of the beat” is a very nice way to translate this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the literal meaning in Japanese is “member of a &lt;em&gt;hayashi&lt;/em&gt;”, and &lt;em&gt;hayashi&lt;/em&gt; (囃子) is &lt;a href=&quot;https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E5%9B%83%E5%AD%90&quot;&gt;the four-piece orchestra&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.glopad.org/jparc/?q=en/node/22767&quot;&gt;traditional Noh theatre&lt;/a&gt;, consisting of three drummers and a flutist. The task of the drummers is to keep the rhythm (&lt;em&gt;hayasu&lt;/em&gt;), but they also &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.the-noh.com/en/world/music.html&quot;&gt;use their voices to create drum calls&lt;/a&gt;. Another component of Noh is the chorus, usually &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noh#Chant_and_music&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;six to eight&lt;/em&gt; people&lt;/a&gt;. And finally there are the actors, who unlike in traditional Western theatre do not ony speak their own lines, but can also &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noh#Chant_and_music&quot;&gt;‘describe events from the perspective of another character or even a disinterested narrator’&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this interpretation, Murakami allocates to his seven Little People the roles of actors, chorus and orchestra in a Noh performance, all at the same time, with an audience of one, the little girl. I think this is what lies behind the Little People saying “Ho ho”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
 &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt; In Japan, traditionally a month is split in three ten-day periods called &lt;em&gt;jun&lt;/em&gt;(旬).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;**&lt;/sup&gt; Murakami calls them リトル・ピープル (RITORU PIIPURU) which is &lt;em&gt;katakana&lt;/em&gt; rendition of the English “Little People”. The little girl thinks of them as &lt;em&gt;kobito&lt;/em&gt; (小人) which also means “little people”. 
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;!--  – shimedaiko (締め太鼓),  otsuzumi (大鼓) and kotsuzumi (小鼓) –-&gt;
&lt;!--
It is often said that Murakami avoids references to traditional Japanese culture, and instead focuses on contemporary Japanese culture. Maybe it is rather the case that his references to traditional Japanese culture are more oblique. 
--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Repetition in Murakami&#39;s 1Q84</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/repetition-in-1Q84/"/>
        <updated>2018-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/repetition-in-1Q84</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/repetition-in-1Q84_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/learning-japanese/&quot;&gt;previous posts&lt;/a&gt;, I have been reading Murakami’s 1Q84 in Japanese (very slowly). I read the English translation when it was first published but I had never looked up any reviews. The Japanese paperback comes in six volumes and after finishing the third volume&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;, I decided to check some reviews, and I was somewhat surprised to find that most critics didn’t like the book very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the recurrent criticisms is that the characters repeat one another frequently. This is in particular the case for the conversations between Tengo and Fuka-eri.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Murakami mentions that Fuka-eri has dyslexia and based on her behaviour and speech it is likely that she also has autistic spectrum disorder (Murakami describes her speech as monotonous or flat, and she clearly prefers to use single words, although she can speak in full sentences; her facial expression is impossible to read; there are many more hints like this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Japanese, Murakami uses a specific writing style to express Fuka-eri’s way of speaking.
Japanese has three sets of characters: &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;katakana&lt;/em&gt; which are phonetic alphabets, and Chinese characters (&lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt;). In general, &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; are used to indicate the meaning of words, &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt; is used to express the grammar and &lt;em&gt;katakana&lt;/em&gt; is used for foreign words or as a kind of italics. Japanese has few distinct sounds, there are lots of homonyms, and the &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; disambiguate the meanings for the homonyms.
However, &lt;em&gt;katakana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt; can be used to phonetically write &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; but sentences without &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; can be difficult to read, especially because no spaces are used between words. Murakami renders Fuka-eri’s speech using &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;katakana&lt;/em&gt; characters only, without &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt;. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「セキブンのはなしはおもしろかった」&lt;br /&gt;
「予備校の僕の講義のこと？」&lt;br /&gt;
ふかえりは肯いた。&lt;br /&gt;
「君は数学は好き？」&lt;br /&gt;
ふかえりは短く首を振った。数学は好ではない。&lt;br /&gt;
「でも積分の話は面白かったんだ？」と天語は尋ねた。&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the English translation by Jay Rubin, the exchange is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘The calculus part was good.’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘You mean in my lecture?’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Fuka-eri nodded.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘Do you like math?’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;She gave her head a quick shake. She did not like math.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘But the part about calculus was good? he asked.’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though the translator has changed the wording slightly, the last sentence still mostly repeats the first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When written in roman alphabet, the first and the last sentence of the Japanese dialogue are virtually identical:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘sekibun no hanashi wa omoshirokatta’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘demo sekibun no hanashi wa omoshirokatta?’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, although the pronunciation is word for word identical, the effect in the original Japanese text is different because the first sentence, said by Fuka-eri, is written only in &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;katakana&lt;/em&gt; characters, while the last sentence, said by Tengo, uses &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt;. For example, while &lt;em&gt;sekibun&lt;/em&gt; has only one meaning, the &lt;em&gt;seki&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;sekibun&lt;/em&gt; could mean amongst others “stone” or “seat” or “red”; &lt;em&gt;bun&lt;/em&gt; could mean amongst others　”minute”, “sentence” or “mosquito”. Without the &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; it is harder for the reader, and requires more context, to work out the meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, Japanese has the particular grammar feature of &lt;em&gt;particles&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;joshi&lt;/em&gt;, 助詞). These are suffixes or short words that immediately follow a noun, verb, adjective, or sentence and can act as conjunctions, prepostions or modifiers. Some of these particles are attached at the very end of the sentence to add an emotion or tone, or convey that the sentence is a question. Fuka-eri never uses those sentence-ending particles, and in particular the question marking particle. As her speech is uninflected, and the word order in Japanese is the same for statements and questions, it is not always clear if she is asking a question or just stating something. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「わたしをだきたくない」とふかえりは疑問符抜きで尋ねた。&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘watashi wo dakitakunai’ to fukaeri wa gimonfunuki de tazuneta.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which Jay Rubin translates as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘You don’t want to hold me,’ Fuka-eri asked without a question mark.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the lack of question mark or particle, there is no way to know if this is a question or not.
&lt;!-- Murakami has added the &#39;_Fuka-eri asked without a question mark_&#39;.--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A proper Japanese sentence would have been either「私を抱きたくないか」or 「私を抱きたくない？」and indeed, Tengo says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「君を抱く？」&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘Hold you?’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lack of &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; and particles means that Fuka-eri’s sentences in Japanese are often quite ambiguous. So when Tengo repeats Fuka-eri’s sentences, he’s making sure that he understands her correctly, but Murakami also uses this to clarify to the reader what she’s just said. For example,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「イヘンがあろうとしている」&lt;br /&gt;
「イヘン」と天吾は言った。それが「異変」であると思い当たるまでに少し時間がかかった。&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘ihen ga arou toshite iru’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘ihen’ to tengo wa itta. sore ga ‘ihen’ de aru to omoiataru made ni sukoshi jikan ga kakatta.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The meaning of “ihen” (イヘン) is not clear when written in &lt;em&gt;katakana&lt;/em&gt;. In fact, a possible meaning of the sentence could be &lt;em&gt;‘You’ll have a leather cord’&lt;/em&gt;.
The Japanese sentence actually says that it takes a while for Tengo to realise that “ihen”,イヘン means ”something unusual”,異変. In the English translation, this becomes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘That something extra ordinary is starting.’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;It took Tengo a moment to realize this meant “extraordinary”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay Rubin has left out the sentence &lt;em&gt;‘ihen’ to tengo wa itta&lt;/em&gt;. He could have translated it as &lt;em&gt;‘Extra ordinary’ said Tengo&lt;/em&gt;, but that would have made the exchange even more repetitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Japanese version of 1Q84, the exchanges with Fuka-eri are my favourite parts. Her sentences are very easy to read, except for the lack of kanji; then Tengo’s paraphrasing puts in the kanji as well. So as a learner I get both the reading and the meaning. Another example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「わたしはここにのこっている」とふかえりは言った。&lt;br /&gt;
「君はここに残っている」と天語は反復した。&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘watashi wa koko ni nokotte iru’ to fukaeri wa itta.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘kimi wa koko ni nokotte iru’ to tengo wa hanpuku shita.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The translation says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘I’ll stay here,’ Fuka-eri said.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘You’ll stay here,’ Tengo echoed her.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, this looks more repetitive than the original.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The English translation of the first two books is by Jay Rubin, who is very renowned for translating Murakami’s works, and I think his translation of 1Q84 is excellent. However, the repetition in the English translation is fundamentally different from the Japanese original because of the writing system. It is impossible to translate the effect of the difference between words writtin in &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;katakana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; into a language with a single alphabet-based writing system like English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;After four years of reading.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--
The other frequent repetitions are in the conversation between Aomame and the Leader, and to my mind this is the result of an intentional symmetry. 1Q84 is highly structured: the three books each span 3 months, the chapters alternate between Tengo and Aomame (and in the third book, Ushikawa). The connection between the main characters is also very symmetrical. The Leader is Fuka-eri&#39;s father[^1] and they are linked in a fundamental way through their connection with the Little People (she&#39;s the &quot;perceiver&quot;, he&#39;s the &quot;receiver&quot;). Aomame and Tengo are also linked in a very fundamental way, I would say they complement one another. The repetitions in the conversation between the Leader and Aomame therefore echo those between Tengo and Fuka-eri.

[^1]: This would be obvious from the start to the Japanese readers: the Leader&#39;s name is Fukada, a common surname. For a pen name, Fuka[da] Eri[ko] is very transparent. The professor calls here Eri, which is a common abbreviation for Eriko, a common name for girls in the 80s.
--&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Stollen</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/stollen/"/>
        <updated>2018-12-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/stollen</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/stollen_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;stollen&lt;/em&gt; is a rich fruit loaf, typical for the festive season. This recipe is based on a Dresdner Christmas stollen recipe from an old cookbook&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I reduced the amounts of butter, raisins and candied peel by half compared to the original.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50 g raisins (I used a cereal topper mix)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;100 g candied orange/lemon peel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;300 g marzipan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7 g dried yeast&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;700 g white flour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.25 l milk&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;150 g butter (I used a mixture of butter and vegetable oil)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 tablespoons sugar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1/2 teaspoon salt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50 g butter to spread on top of the loaf after baking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2-3 tablespoons icing sugar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The preparation is quite similar to making bread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put the flour and salt in a bowl.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make a hollow in the middle and put in the yeast, 2 tablespoons sugar and some water.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cover with a teatowel and let the yeast do its work for 10 minutes or so.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mix the butter in with the milk (I heated it to a little above room temperature in the microwave).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the mixture to the flour and knead into a smooth dough. You may need add a little bit water if it is too dry.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leave to rise, covered, for 30 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quickly knead in the raisins and candied peel.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flatten the dough, shape the marzipan into a roll and fold the dough over it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leave to rise, covered, for another 30 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Preheat the oven on 200°C; bake for 15 minutes at 200°C, then 1 hour at 180°C.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While it’s still hot, spread butter on top and sprinkle on the icing sugar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A Dutch translation of a German cookbook, now long out of print: “De heerlijkste gerechten” by Annette Wolter, &lt;em&gt;Culinaire boekerij&lt;/em&gt;, 1988. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Veggie Binagoonang</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/veggie-binagoonang/"/>
        <updated>2018-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/veggie-binagoonang</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	
        	&lt;p&gt;Binagoongan Baboy sa Gata&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prep time
10 mins
Cook time
1 hour 30 mins
Total time
1 hour 40 mins&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Author: Lalaine&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Kawaling PInoy&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cuisine: Filipino
Yield: 4 Servings&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ingredients
oil
1 large eggplant, cut into cubes
2 cm ginger, finely chopped
1 teaspoon garlic oil or 2 cloves garlic
tofu sticks for 2 people
1 large tomato, chopped
1/2 tablespoon miso + 1/2 tablespoon tobanjan
1 tablespoons vinegar
0.2l coconut milk
1/4 cup water
0.5 teaspoon sugar
2 mild chili peppers, stemmed and minced
salt and pepper to taste&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instructions
In a wide pan or skillet over medium heat, heat about 2 tablespoons oil. Add eggplant and fry until lightly browned, turning on sides as needed. Remove from heat and drain on paper towels. Keep warm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the pan, heat another 1 tablespoon oil. Add ginger and garlic and cook until limp. Add tofu sticks and cook until lightly browned.
Add miso+tobanjan paste and cook, stirring occasionally, for about 3 to 5 minutes or until color darkens.
Add tomatoes and cook, mashing with the back of the spoon, until softened.
Add vinegar and allow to a boil, uncovered and without stirring, for about 3 to 5 minutes or until mostly absorbed. Add coconut milk, water, sugar and chili peppers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lower heat, cover, and simmer until liquid is reduced. Add eggplant and continue to cook until liquid is reduced.  Season with salt and pepper to taste.&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Veggie Binagoonang Talong</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/veggie-binagoonang-talong/"/>
        <updated>2018-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/veggie-binagoonang-talong</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	
        	Binagoongan Talong sa Gata
 
https://www.kawalingpinoy.com/binagoongan-talong/

Ingredients

- 2 tablespoons olive oil
- 2 medium aubergines, cut into cubes
- 2 cm ginger, finely chopped
- 1 stick celery, finely chopped
- 1 teaspoon garlic oil or 2 cloves garlic
- tofu sticks for 2 people
- 1 large tomato, chopped
- 1 tablespoon miso
- 1 tablespoon vinegar
- 0.2l coconut milk
- 1/4 cup water
- 1/2 teaspoon sugar
- 2 mild chili peppers, stemmed and minced


Instructions

- Soak the tofu sticks in very hot water for 30 minutes, drain and chop.
- Cook the aubergines 7 minutes in the microwave at full power (900W).
- Cook tomato 2 minutes in the microwave at full power (900W).
- Heat the oil in a deep pan. When the oil is hot, add ginger, celery and garlic and fry fir a few minutes over medium heat. Add tofu sticks and cook until lightly browned.
- Add _miso_, tomatoes and vinegar and cook, stirring occasionally, for a few minutes.
- Add coconut milk, water, sugar and chili peppers and simmer for a few minutes over lower heat.
- Add the aubergines and continue to cook until liquid is reduced.  

Season with salt and pepper to taste. Serve with rice 
        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Stollen</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/stollen/"/>
        <updated>2018-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/stollen</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	
        	Stollen

Based on &quot;Dresdner kerststol&quot;  (p. 335)

- 50 g raisins (I used a cereal topper mix)
- 100 g candied orange/lemon peel
- 300 g marzipan
- 7 g dried yeast
- 700 g white flour
- 0.25 l milk
- 150 g butter

3 tablespoons sugar
1/2 teaspoon salt

+ 50 g butter on top
+ 2-3 tablespoons icing sugar

- I did the recipe as in the book, which is basically making bread, except that with the dried yeast it does not need to sit for very long. 
- Also, I mixed the butter in the milk, heated it very slightly in the microwave.
- I had to add a little extra water
- I turned the loaf halfway (after 8 mins) during the first 15 mins 200 deg bake and every 15 minutes during the 1-hour 180 deg bake.


----
Stollen

- 50 g raisins (I used a cereal topper mix)
- 100 g candied orange/lemon peel
- 300 g marzipan
- 7 g dried yeast
- 700 g white flour
- 0.25 l milk
- 150 g butter
- 3 tablespoons sugar
- 1/2 teaspoon salt

+ 50 g butter on top
+ 2-3 tablespoons icing sugar

- Put the flour and salt in a bowl, make a hollow in the middle and put in the yeast, 2 tablespoons sugar and some water, and let the yeast do its work for 10 minutes or so. 
- Mix the butter in with the milk and add to the flour and knead into a smooth dough.
- Leave to rise for 30 mins.
- Quickly knead in the raisins and candied peel
- Flatten the dough, shape the marzipan into a roll and fold the dough over it.
- Leave to rise for another 30 mins.
- Preheat the oven on 200 C; bake for 15 mins, then 1 h for 180 C.
- While it&#39;s still hot, smear with butter and sprinkle on icing sugar



        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Aubergines and tofu sticks in Filipino-style creamy sauce</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/veggie-binagoonang-talong/"/>
        <updated>2018-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/veggie-binagoonang-talong</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/veggie-binagoonang-talong_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;This is a veggie version of a Filipino recipe, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kawalingpinoy.com/binagoongan-baboy-sa-gata/&quot;&gt;Binagoongan Baboy sa Gata&lt;/a&gt;. I added the aubergines to the pan as in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kawalingpinoy.com/binagoongan-talong/&quot;&gt;this Binagoongan Talong&lt;/a&gt; recipe. The less common ingredient in my recipe is &lt;a href=&quot;https://shop.waiyeehong.com/food-ingredients/dried-products/dried-beancurd-seaweed/dried-beancurd-sticks-tofu-bamboo-2?language=tw&quot;&gt;dried tofu (bean curd) sticks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegan&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#gluten-free&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;gluten-free&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#30-minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;30-minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;900 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#800-1000kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_4.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fresh ingredients &amp;amp; groceries
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 cm ginger, finely chopped&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 stick celery, finely chopped&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 cloves garlic&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 medium aubergines, cut into cubes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 large tomato, chopped&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;50 g tofu sticks&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;0.2 l coconut milk&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/4 cup water&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 mild chili peppers, stemmed and minced&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From the store cupboard
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/2 teaspoon sugar&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt; paste&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon vinegar&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cup of rice (preferably jasmine rice)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soak the tofu sticks in very hot water for 30 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meanwhile
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cook the aubergines 7 minutes in the microwave at full power (900W).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;In a separate pot, cook the tomato 2 minutes in the microwave at full power (900W).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Heat the oil in a deep pan. When the oil is hot, add the ginger, celery and garlic and fry for a few minutes over medium heat.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Drain the tofu sticks and cut them into pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the tofu sticks to the pan and cook until lightly browned.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt;, tomatoes and vinegar and cook, stirring occasionally, for a few minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add coconut milk, water, sugar and chili peppers and simmer for a few minutes over lower heat.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the aubergines and continue to cook until the liquid is reduced.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Season with salt and pepper to taste. Serve with rice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Stir fry of carrots, courgettes and tofu sticks</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/stir-fry-carrots-courgettes-bean-curd-sticks/"/>
        <updated>2018-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/stir-fry-carrots-courgettes-bean-curd-sticks</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/stir-fry-carrots-courgettes-bean-curd-sticks_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;This is a very simple stir fry, quick and easy to make. The less common ingredients in this recipe are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://shop.waiyeehong.com/food-ingredients/dried-products/dried-beancurd-seaweed/dried-beancurd-sticks-tofu-bamboo-2?language=tw&quot;&gt;dried bean curd sticks&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.japancentre.com/en/products/2872-wel-pac-dried-hijiki-seaweed&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;hijiki&lt;/em&gt; seaweed&lt;/a&gt;.
You can find these ingredients in most Asian supermarkets. I also used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.japancentre.com/en/products/2051-clearspring-organic-brown-rice-miso&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt; paste&lt;/a&gt;. You can find it in most supermarkets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegan&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#20-minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;20-minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;650 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#600-800kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_3.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fresh ingredients &amp;amp; groceries
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;300 g carrots&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;a medium courgette (about 200 g)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cm ginger, chopped very fine&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;50 g dried bean curd sticks&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon &lt;em&gt;hijiki&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From the store cupboard
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt; paste&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoons olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon sesame oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons pumpkin seeds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon sesame seeds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cup of rice (I used basmati)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soak the bean curd sticks in boiling hot water for about half an hour.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soak the &lt;em&gt;hijiki&lt;/em&gt; in hot water for about half an hour.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prepare the rice (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/basics/#toc0&quot;&gt;The Basics&lt;/a&gt; for instructions to cook rice).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meanwhile:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wash, scrape or peel the carrots and chop them (rather coarsely).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Microwave for 3 minutes at full power (900W) (if you like, add a splash of &lt;em&gt;mirin&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wash and chop the courgettes.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the courgettes to the carrots and microwave for another 3 minutes at full power (900W).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pour the cooking liquid into a bowl.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Heat the oil in a deep pan and fry the ginger and seeds for a few minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Drain the bean curd and chop into sections of 2-3 cm long.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fry the bean curd on medium to high heat for a few minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the vegetables and fry on medium to high heat for a few more minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Drain the &lt;em&gt;hijiki&lt;/em&gt; and add to the pan; fry for a few more minutes on low heat.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dissolve the &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt; in the cooking liquid of the vegetables and add it to the pan.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Turn off the heat and stir well until the liquid is absorbed.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Serve with the rice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Why does Japanese have kanji for very large numbers?</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/japanese-large-numbers/"/>
        <updated>2018-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/japanese-large-numbers</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/japanese-large-numbers_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;As a slow learner of Japanese, I often have to look up &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; (Chinese characters) in my dictionary. I was intrigued to notice that for some kanji, one of their meanings is a &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; large number:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Kanji&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Reading&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Number&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;万&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;man&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;億&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;oku&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;兆&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;chō&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;京&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;kei&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;垓&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;gai&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;20&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;𥝱&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;jo&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;穣&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;jō&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;28&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;溝&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;kō&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;32&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;澗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;kan&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;36&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;正&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;sei&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;40&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;載&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;sai&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;44&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;極&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;goku&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;48&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 1. &lt;em&gt;Kanji for large numbers with readings and number values&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- K computer picture and anecdote --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;kanji-and-the-supercomputer&quot;&gt;Kanji and the supercomputer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the character 京, which is the “kyō” in Kyoto (京都) means “metropolis”, but also 10&lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;. For that meaning it is pronounced “kei”, and this is the origin of the name of the famous Riken supercomputer in Kobe, the “K computer”: it is a computer capable of 10 petaflops, so 10&lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt; or &lt;em&gt;kei&lt;/em&gt; flops. Incidentally, it is probably the only supercomputer that has its own railway station, 京コンピュータ前駅.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/k-computer-mae_1600.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;K Computer Mae Station&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The 京コンピュータ前駅 (K Computer Mae Station) in Kobe.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!-- I asked a Japanese friend and he told me that originally, these kanji simply indicated degrees of large, and then they got numerical values, and then the intervals were increased over time. --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;counting-systems&quot;&gt;Counting systems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of how these kanji came to represent such large numbers is quite interesting. It started with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sf.airnet.ne.jp/~ts/language/largenumber.html&quot;&gt;the emergence of a number of different counting systems&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Japan has adopted kanji from China – the word &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; (漢字) means Chinese characters, the 漢 character meaning &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Han_Chinese&quot;&gt;“Han”&lt;/a&gt;.  The traditional numeral systems of China, Korea, and Japan are all decimal-based but grouped into ten thousands, also known as myriads (&lt;em&gt;man&lt;/em&gt;, 万), rather than thousands. Very long ago, the characters beyond &lt;em&gt;man&lt;/em&gt; simply indicated degrees of large, so &lt;em&gt;oku&lt;/em&gt; (億) was larger than &lt;em&gt;man&lt;/em&gt; (万), &lt;em&gt;chō&lt;/em&gt; (兆) was larger than &lt;em&gt;oku&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;kei&lt;/em&gt; (京) was larger than &lt;em&gt;chō&lt;/em&gt;, etc. Actual counting of numbers beyond one myriad was ten myriads, hundred myriads, thousand myriads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then over time the characters &lt;em&gt;oku&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;chō&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;kei&lt;/em&gt; etc. started to be used for this, in a counting system called &lt;em&gt;kasū&lt;/em&gt; (下数,かすう, “lower arithmetic”). So in this system, &lt;em&gt;oku&lt;/em&gt; was ten times &lt;em&gt;man&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;chō&lt;/em&gt; was ten times &lt;em&gt;oku&lt;/em&gt;, etc. This was very long ago, more than two thousand years, and clearly it was not entirely satisfactory because already from the Han dynasty onwards (i.e. 200 BCE), a separate counting system called &lt;em&gt;jōsū&lt;/em&gt;（上数,じょうすう,”upper arithmetic”）also became used. In this system, the character after &lt;em&gt;man&lt;/em&gt; got the value of &lt;em&gt;man man&lt;/em&gt; (万万), so &lt;em&gt;oku&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;man man&lt;/em&gt; = 10&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;. The next value &lt;em&gt;chō&lt;/em&gt; became  &lt;em&gt;oku oku&lt;/em&gt; (億億) = 10&lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;em&gt;kei&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;chō chō&lt;/em&gt; (兆兆) =10&lt;sup&gt;32&lt;/sup&gt; and so on.
Later, yet another system, called &lt;em&gt;chūsū&lt;/em&gt; (中数,ちゅうすう,”middle arithmetic”) came into use. In this system, the values for consecutive kanji where 10&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; apart. To be precise, in China there were two variants of &lt;em&gt;chūsū&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;manshin&lt;/em&gt; (万進) and (万万進) &lt;em&gt;manmanshin&lt;/em&gt;, the latter had intervals of 10&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The table below summarises the various systems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Kanji&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Reading&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;em&gt;kasū&lt;/em&gt;  (下数)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;em&gt;chūsū/manshin&lt;/em&gt;　(中数／万進)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;em&gt;chūsū/manmanshin&lt;/em&gt; (中数／万万進)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;em&gt;jōsū&lt;/em&gt;    (上数)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;万&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;man&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;億&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;oku&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×2&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;8×1&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×2&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;兆&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;chō&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×3&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;8×2&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×2&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;京&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;kei&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×4&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;8×3&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×2&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;32&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;垓&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;gai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×5&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;20&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;8×4&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;32&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×2&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;64&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;秭&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;jo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×6&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;8×5&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;40&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×2&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;128&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;穣&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;jō&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×7&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;28&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;8×6&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;48&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×2&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;256&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;溝&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;kō&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×8&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;32&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;8×7&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;56&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×2&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;512&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;澗&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;kan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×9&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;36&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;8×8&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;64&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×2&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;1024&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;正&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;sei&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×10&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;40&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;8×9&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;72&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×2&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;2048&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;載&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;sai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×11&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;44&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;8×10&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×2&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;4096&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;極&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;goku&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×12&lt;/sup&gt;= 10&lt;sup&gt;48&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;8×11&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;88&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;sup&gt;4×2&lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;8192&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 2. &lt;em&gt;Summary of the different counting systems used historically&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-edo-era-mathematics-book&quot;&gt;An Edo-era mathematics book&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Edo-era Japan, the 1634 edition of an influential mathematics book, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ndl.go.jp/math/e/s2/1.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;jinkōki&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E5%A1%B5%E5%8A%AB%E8%A8%98&quot;&gt;塵劫記&lt;/a&gt;), standardised on the &lt;em&gt;chūsū/manshin&lt;/em&gt; (中数/万進) system as shown in the table above. The work covers a wide variety of mathematical problems but its main purpose was to explain techniques for calculating using the &lt;em&gt;soroban&lt;/em&gt; (算盤), the Japanese abacus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-daimyo-the-samurai-and-the-soroban&quot;&gt;The daimyo, the samurai and the soroban&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.maa.org/press/periodicals/convergence/elementary-soroban-arithmetic-techniques-in-edo-period-japan&quot;&gt;The oldest &lt;em&gt;soroban&lt;/em&gt; in existence&lt;/a&gt; is the &lt;em&gt;Shibei Shigekatsu hairyo soroban&lt;/em&gt;, from 1591. It was made from plum tree wood and silver and given to the samurai Shibei Shigekatsu by the famous daimyō &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/biography/Toyotomi-Hideyoshi&quot;&gt;Toyotomi Hideyoshi&lt;/a&gt; (The word &lt;em&gt;hairyo&lt;/em&gt; (拝領) means “receiving from a superior”). It shows that this kind of calculating device was highly valued. This soroban has 20 number rods, so it can represent any number up to 10&lt;sup&gt;20&lt;/sup&gt;-1. So in any case the introduction of the &lt;em&gt;soroban&lt;/em&gt; made it easier to conceive very large numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;buddhist-angels-and-mustard-seeds&quot;&gt;Buddhist angels and mustard seeds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story so far does not quite explain where those different systems came from or &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; these choices were made, and indeed earlier editions of the &lt;em&gt;jinkōki&lt;/em&gt; used different combinations of &lt;em&gt;kasū&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;chūsū&lt;/em&gt;. In any case, it turns out that the origin of these very large numbers lies in ancient Buddhist texts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buddhism has the notion of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kalpa_(aeon)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;kalpa&lt;/em&gt; or aeon&lt;/a&gt;, a very long unit of time. There are in the old texts two definitions for a kalpa, provided by the Buddha by analogy. I found the following explanation on &lt;a href=&quot;http://gyafun.jp/ln/intro.html&quot;&gt;a Japanese web site for the book “巨大数入門” (“An introduction to very large numbers”)&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;『仏教では、とても長い時間を表すときに劫（こう）という時間の単位が使われます。「未来永劫」「億劫」「五劫のすり切れ」などの言葉は、ここから来ています。この「劫」には2通りの意味があり、1つ目は「磐石劫」で、四十里四方の大石を、いわゆる天人の羽衣で百年に一度払い、その大きな石が摩滅して無くなってもなお「一劫」の時間は終わらないと譬えています。 2つ目は「芥子劫」で、方四十里の城に小さな芥子粒を満たして百年に一度、一粒ずつ取り去り、その芥子がすべて無くなってもなお尽きないほどの長い時間が一劫であるとのことです。』&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loosely translated, this means that there are two definitions for a kalpa:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imagine a huge cube of rock of 40 &lt;em&gt;ri&lt;/em&gt; on the side. Every hundred years, an angel brushes the rock with its wings. A kalpa won’t have ended by the time it takes to entirely wear away the rock.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imagine a huge building of 40 &lt;em&gt;ri&lt;/em&gt; on the side. Every hundred years, a small mustard seed is put into it. The kalpa won’t have ended by the time the building is full.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To estimate how long a kalpa actually lasts, &lt;a href=&quot;http://gyafun.jp/ln/intro.html&quot;&gt;someone&lt;/a&gt; made the following assumptions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Suppose the angel’s wings remove one layer of atoms over an area of one square meter. Given that 1 &lt;em&gt;ri&lt;/em&gt; is 500 &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt; and the diameter of an atom is 0.2 &lt;em&gt;nm&lt;/em&gt;, it would take 4×10&lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt; years to wear away the rock.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For the second definition, assuming a mustard seed is 0.5 &lt;em&gt;mm&lt;/em&gt;, it would take  6.4×10&lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt; years to fill the entire volume.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s rather striking that both estimates produce the same order of magnitude, 10&lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt; years. For comparison, the estimated age of the universe is “only” 1.38×10&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt; years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grains-of-sand-in-the-ganges&quot;&gt;Grains of sand in the Ganges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless, it means that Buddhist scholar monks had a need to express very large numbers. In fact, Buddhism has concepts such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://diamond-sutra.com/read-the-diamond-sutra-here/diamond-sutra-chapter-11/&quot;&gt;the number of grains of sand in the Ganges&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;gōgasha&lt;/em&gt;,恒河沙), which are even larger than &lt;em&gt;goku&lt;/em&gt; (極, 10&lt;sup&gt;48&lt;/sup&gt;). The largest quantified term I could find in my dictionary is &lt;em&gt;muryōtaisū&lt;/em&gt; (無量大数,”immeasurably large number”),  with a value of 10&lt;sup&gt;68&lt;/sup&gt; using &lt;em&gt;chūsū&lt;/em&gt;, but often defined as 10&lt;sup&gt;88&lt;/sup&gt;, due to a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sf.airnet.ne.jp/~ts/language/largenumber.html&quot;&gt;variant system used for values above &lt;em&gt;goku&lt;/em&gt; used in the 1631 edition of the &lt;em&gt;jinkōki&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--

この時間がどの程度のものなのか「カガクのじかん」というサイト (http://d.hatena.ne.jp/inyoko/) では、次のように計算しています。 「磐石劫」では、「1里=500m」「原子=1辺0.2nmの立方体」「1回なでると、1平方メートルの範囲の原子が1層はがれる」という仮定の下、4𥝱、すなわち 4&amp;times;10&lt;sup&gt;24年という計算結果を出しました。

2つ目の「芥子劫」については、「1里=500m」、「けし粒=1辺0.5mmの立方体」、という仮定の下、6𥝱4000垓、すなわち 6.4&amp;times;10&lt;sup&gt;24年という計算結果を出しました。磐石劫でも芥子劫でも同じ𥝱の単位になるのは面白いところです。

----
宇宙の年齢は138億年程度であるとされていますので、それと比べて100兆倍ほどの気の遠くなるほど長い時間です。

----
恒河沙という数と劫という時間の単位を組み合わせれば、恒河沙劫というとても長い時間が表現できますので、そういう表現があるか検索してみたところ、『首楞厳経』という経典に恒河沙劫という表現が出てきて、親鸞が『尊号真像銘文』で引用していることが分かりました。恒河沙劫は、10の46乗年、すなわち100載年のオーダーになります。







載よりも上の単位である極から上は、元の朱世傑（しゅせいけつ、生没年不詳）による『算学啓蒙』(1299年)において登場しました。ここで極以外の単位はすべて仏教から取られたものです。恒河沙は「ガンジス川の砂」の意味で、それだけ大きな数ということです。 阿僧祇は「数えることができない」、 那由他は「極めて大きな数量」、 不可思議「思い測ったり言葉で言い表したりすることができない」 無量大数は、『算学啓蒙』では「無量数」として登場し、「量ることのできない数」ということです。

この中で恒河沙以外は「数え切れないほどの大きな数」と理解すれば良いのですが、恒河沙については、ガンジス川の砂の数という具体的な数になっているので、どの程度の大きさなのか見積もってみます。 今は恒河沙と言えば日本では10の52乗という意味になり、中国でも下数、中数、上数によって数は変わります。仏教の中ではそういう数を意味するものではなく、ガンジス川の砂の数という意味ですから、今の日本で恒河沙を意味する10の52乗と比較することは無意味です。


| Word | Reading | Number |
| ---- | ---- | ---- |
| 恒河沙 	| gōgasha 	| 10&lt;sup&gt;52,10&lt;sup&gt;56|
| 阿僧祇 	| asōgi 	| 10&lt;sup&gt;56,10&lt;sup&gt;64|
| 那由他, 那由多 	| nayuta 	| 10&lt;sup&gt;60,10&lt;sup&gt;72|
| 不可思議 	| fukashigi 	| 10&lt;sup&gt;64,10&lt;sup&gt;80|
| 無量大数 	| muryōtaisū 	| 10&lt;sup&gt;68,10&lt;sup&gt;88|

--&gt;

&lt;!--

## References

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Japanese_numerals
https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kalpa_(aeon)
https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buddhist_cosmology

https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E7%84%A1%E9%87%8F%E5%A4%A7%E6%95%B0
http://gyafun.jp/ln/intro.html
http://www.sf.airnet.ne.jp/~ts/language/largenumber.html
http://www.sf.airnet.ne.jp/~ts/personal/indexj.html
https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E5%91%BD%E6%95%B0%E6%B3%95

--&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Drawing the dancer of Ranryōō</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/ran-ryou-ou/"/>
        <updated>2018-08-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/ran-ryou-ou</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/ran-ryou-ou_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;Some years ago I was at the &lt;em&gt;yoiyama&lt;/em&gt; (宵山) – or maybe the &lt;em&gt;yoiyoiyama&lt;/em&gt; (宵々山), or even the &lt;em&gt;yoiyoiyoiyama&lt;/em&gt; (宵々々山) – in any case, the eve of the Gion Matsuri (祇園祭), Kyoto’s most famous festival. I came across a traditional dance performance and took some pictures, one of them is the banner for this post. This summer I wanted to make a drawing with a Japanese theme and I selected that picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- pic here? -&gt;

&lt;!--
At the time I thought, because of the colour of the costume, that the dance had something to do with the local shrine, and I interpreted the mask as a fox.
--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before starting on the drawing, I felt I had to find out more about the dance. Most of what follows is taken from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aisf.or.jp/~jaanus/deta/r/ryouou.htm&quot;&gt;the page about Ryōō 陵王 on the  Japanese Architecture and Art Net Users System&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E8%98%AD%E9%99%B5%E7%8E%8B_(%E9%9B%85%E6%A5%BD)&quot;&gt;Japanese Wikipedia page about Ranryōō (蘭陵王)&lt;/a&gt;, with some additional information from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nypl.org/blog/2017/04/06/bugaku-japanese-imperial-court-dance&quot;&gt;this New York Public Library&lt;/a&gt; blog article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-legend&quot;&gt;The legend&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common interpretation of the dance is that it celebrates the victory of Prince Lanling (Ranryōō, 蘭陵王) of Pohai (北斉 , Manchuria) over the Zhou dynasty, around 550 A.D. He was a general named &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gao_Changgong&quot;&gt;Gao Changgong&lt;/a&gt; who was given a fiefdom in Lanling, so he was also known as the Prince of Lanling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prince of Lan Ling was one of the four most handsome men in ancient Chinese history. A masterful warrior, he led his army into battle and vanquished his foes while wearing a fearsome &lt;em&gt;Ryōō&lt;/em&gt; mask to hide his beauty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His most famous battle was the breaking of the siege of Jinyong (金墉, near modern Luoyang) in 564 A.D. Gao Changgong led only 500 cavalrymen and fought through an army of Northern Zhou, which was attacking the city with 100,000 soldiers. He fought his way to the gates the city, surprising the defenders. The soldiers of Jinyong didn’t recognize him, so he took off his helmet and mask. The soldiers in the city rejoiced at his arrival and their courage returned. They opened the gates and joined the battle outside the city. Soon the army of Northern Zhou was defeated. To celebrate the victory, the soldiers composed the famous song and dance “Prince Lanling in Battle” (兰陵王入阵曲).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-tradition&quot;&gt;The tradition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are variations on the legend: some say that the prince wore the mask himself to frighten his enemies, others that his father’s ghost appeared wearing the mask. Others trace the dance back to the Eight Dragon Kings (&lt;em&gt;hachidai ryuuou&lt;/em&gt; 八大竜王) of the Buddhist Lotus Sutra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following this latter tradition, folk festivals in Japan since the 13th century often incorporate the dance of Ran-ryou-ou as a rain prayer, as dragons are associated with water. This may partly account for the great popularity of the dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-dance&quot;&gt;The dance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dance is called &lt;em&gt;ranryouou nyuujinkyoku&lt;/em&gt; (蘭陵王入陣曲) “The song of Prince Lan-Ling going into Battle”. It is a traditional Japanese court dance or &lt;em&gt;bugaku&lt;/em&gt; (舞楽) introduced in the Japanese Imperial courts in the 9th century, and performed to traditional Japanese court music or &lt;em&gt;gagaku&lt;/em&gt; (雅楽). For much of its history, &lt;em&gt;bugaku&lt;/em&gt; was an exclusive and privileged experience, performed only at the Japanese imperial court and, very rarely, as part of religious rituals at temples or shrines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In those days (the Heian era) the imperial court was organized with a strict Left and Right division. In terms of culture, poetry, music and dance, the Left was associated with China or India and the Right with Korea. Costumes for dances of the Left are primarily red. The music, &lt;em&gt;tougaku&lt;/em&gt; (唐楽) is a Japanese adaptation of Chinese musical styles prevalent during the T’ang Dynasty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Ranryōō&lt;/em&gt; is a dynamic dance of the Left (&lt;em&gt;sa-no-mai&lt;/em&gt; 左舞) and it is originally from either China or Southeast Asia (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chinaknowledge.de/History/Altera/champa.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;rin’yuugaku&lt;/em&gt; 林邑楽&lt;/a&gt;). It is performed by one person dressed in a fringed tunic and pantaloons (&lt;em&gt;ryoutou shouzoku&lt;/em&gt; 裲襠装束).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mask or &lt;em&gt;bugakumen&lt;/em&gt; (舞楽面) is of a fierce, mythical golden beast with a dragon perched on its head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-mask&quot;&gt;The mask&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Ranryōō masks can look vary different, they all share a common set of features: a sharp, long nose; bulging, rotating eyes (&lt;em&gt;dougan&lt;/em&gt; 動眼); a gaping mouth with huge teeth and dangling chin (&lt;em&gt;tsuriago&lt;/em&gt; 吊顎); wrinkles that line the face and the carved strands of heavy hair above the forehead. The golden face and metallic eyes are offset by the blue-green hair and vermilion mouth. There are tufts of animal hair suggestive of eyebrows, a moustache and beard. On the top of the head perches a crouching dragon. I found &lt;a href=&quot;https://ameblo.jp/togihideki/entry-12246120465.html&quot;&gt;an interesting blog post&lt;/a&gt; (in Japanese) by a Ranryōō dancer, where he compares various masks from his own collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-drawing&quot;&gt;The drawing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/ran_ryou_ou.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;the drawing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;!-- add a caption --&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The finished drawing&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to make a drawing with bright colours and a lot of detail, and also I prefer to draw human figures, but I didn’t want to do a portrait. So this Ranryōō dancer was a perfect match. I replaced the audience with people in &lt;em&gt;yukata&lt;/em&gt; (浴衣, a light summer kimono) to make the scene more homogeneous. For most of the &lt;em&gt;yukata&lt;/em&gt; designs I used my own pictures but the designs of the central four figures are based on the &lt;em&gt;yukata&lt;/em&gt; worn by the sisters in Hirokazu Kore-eda’s wonderful movie “海街 diary” (“Our little sister”). The main focus is of course the dancer, so I drew and coloured the musicians and audience in a much more sketchy way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper for this drawing is Arches 56cm x 76cm 300g/m2 “rough” watercolour paper. It’s a really nice paper with a pronounced grain and absorbs the water really well. As I did not tape it on a board, the sheet of course buckled a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used Derwent Inktense and Conté Aquaralle pencils as well as watercolour paint (various brands). The Inktense pencils give a very saturated colour. It was the first time I used them but I really like them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started the drawing as usual with a pencil ghost drawing. Because of the size of the drawing, I used a grid to make sure the figure was positioned correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/s01-P1080141proc-19Jul.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;the drawing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Pencil ghost drawing&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I added a first layer of detail and colour with the watercolour pencils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/s02-20180721_095211-21Jul.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;the drawing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;First layer of detail and colour&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I started to detail and wash the mask. I needed a very fine pencil and a magnifying glass for the eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/s03-20180722_181118.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;the drawing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Mask with washed watercolour pencils&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I worked on the tunic in the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/s04-20180729_113922.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;the drawing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Tunic with washed watercolours&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I did the trousers, which took a long time, and the sleeves, ending the first full pass of the entire figure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/s05-20180802_163432.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;the drawing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;First full pass of the entire figure&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I worked on the detail of the &lt;em&gt;yukata&lt;/em&gt; of the figures in the background, which I decided to do in indigo blue for all of them. Usually I use a relatively blunt pencil because in general that works better on coarse-grained paper, but to render the patterns on the fabric with very fine lines before washing them I used an extra-sharp pencil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/s06-20180804_180431.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;the drawing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Detailing the _yukata_ designs for the background figures&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I added more detail and colour to the musicians, but I left them quite sketchy on purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/s07-20180805_crop.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;the drawing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;More detail and colour on the musicians&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I put a second layer of colour on the dancer, to make the red and orange more vibrant, and make the shadows more pronounced. I used a mixture of watercolour paint and watercolour pencils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/s08-20180812_171109.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;the drawing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Second pass of the dancer&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally I did another pass of the entire drawing. I added more colour to the background figures but made them darker at the same time, as they are actually in the shadow. Adding the shadow layer was tricky because I could not just wash the entire background with a darker tint, as it would make the colours run. Instead, I used a layer of colour pencil. I added still more colour to the dancer, especially to the sleeves, again using a mixture of watercolour paint and watercolour pencils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To finish the drawing I added a description in Japanese, “蘭陵王　雅楽公演　祇園祭”, which means “&lt;em&gt;Ranryoo&lt;/em&gt;, public &lt;em&gt;bugaku&lt;/em&gt; performance, Gion &lt;em&gt;matsuri&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Cold pasta with raw carrots and mushrooms</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/pasta-raw-carrots-mushrooms/"/>
        <updated>2018-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/pasta-raw-carrots-mushrooms</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/pasta-raw-carrots-mushrooms_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;As this is the hottest summer in 40 years, I wanted to make something refreshing. This is a cold pasta with raw carrots and raw chestnut mushrooms, with a vinaigrette style dressing but using lemon juice rather than vinegar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegetarian&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegetarian&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#20-minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;20-minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;800 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#600-800kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_3.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fresh ingredients &amp;amp; groceries
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;300 g carrots&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 pack (200 g) chestnut mushrooms&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;50 g green olives&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cm ginger, chopped very fine&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;juice of 1 lemon&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cup grated hard cheese (parmezan or grana padano)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From the store cupboard
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;200 g pasta (linguine )&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;3 dried tomatoes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon tomato puree&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons pumpkin seeds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/2 teaspoon &lt;em&gt;toubandjan&lt;/em&gt; (black bean paste)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;some pepper&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cook the pasta (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/basics/#toc2&quot;&gt;basics&lt;/a&gt; for how to cook pasta). Add the dried tomatoes to the water from the start.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While the pasta is cooking:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wash, scrape or peel the carrots and chop them finely.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wash the mushrooms and chop them in thin slices and add them to the carrots.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the olives and the pumpkin seeds.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mix the lemon juice, 1 tablespoon olive oil, ginger, tomato puree and &lt;em&gt;toubandjan&lt;/em&gt; and some pepper.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pour this dressing over the vegetables and mix well.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take the dried tomatoes out of the water, chop them and add to the vegetables.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Toss the pasta in the remaining olive oil.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Serve the pasta in a deep bowl with the mushrooms and carrots on top.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sprinkle on the grated cheese.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Move over onion, here&#39;s ginger</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/ginger-vs-onion/"/>
        <updated>2018-05-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/ginger-vs-onion</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/ginger-vs-onion_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;If you’ve tried some &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/&quot;&gt;Quick and Tasty recipes&lt;/a&gt;, you will have noticed that they never contain onion. There is no special reason for this other than that I prefer ginger. So let’s make the case for ginger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people don’t like onion, raw or cooked. Also peeling and chopping onion is not pleasant, and the smell of onion is hard to wash off your hands. And yet most recipes contain onion. By contrast, few recipes contain fresh ginger. I argue that you don’t need onion to make tasty meals, and that you should consider using fresh ginger instead, and I present the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/&quot;&gt;Quick and Tasty recipes&lt;/a&gt; as evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main flavours cooked onion adds to a meal are sweetness and &lt;em&gt;umami&lt;/em&gt;. But onion is actually not a particularly good source of &lt;em&gt;umami&lt;/em&gt;. According to the web site of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.umamiinfo.com&quot;&gt;Umami Information Center&lt;/a&gt;, onion contains about 20-50 mg glutamate/100 g. Ginger contains about 20 mg as well. For reference, tomatoes — a great source of umami — contain almost 250 mg glutamate/100 g. There are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.umamiinfo.com&quot;&gt;many other ingredients&lt;/a&gt; that provide umami.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ginger has a unique fresh and very spicy taste, especially in raw form, but it does not burn the mouth like peppers. Raw ginger is great to spice up a salad. Frying reduces the spiciness and enhances the sweetness. The change in taste is the result of applying heat (&lt;a href=&quot;https://scienceandfooducla.wordpress.com/2014/09/30/ginger/&quot;&gt;which transforms &lt;em&gt;gingerol&lt;/em&gt; into &lt;em&gt;zingerone&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) so cooking in the microwave works fine as well, you don’t need to actually fry it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ginger has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthline.com/nutrition/11-proven-benefits-of-ginger&quot;&gt;many proven health benefits&lt;/a&gt;, but the great taste is reason enough to start using it. Here are a few examples of Quick and Tasty recipes with ginger:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- I find the taste of fried ginger much more interesting than that of fried onion.--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With raw ginger:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/asparagus-paneer-courgette-rocket-salad/&quot;&gt;Salad: Asparagus and paneer on a bed of rocket and courgettes
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/murakami-2/&quot;&gt;Soba noodles with  soy beans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With cooked ginger:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/winter-hotpot-root-vegetables-adzuki-beans/&quot;&gt;Simple winter hotpot with root vegetables and adzuki beans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/potato-vegetable-bake/&quot;&gt;Potato and vegetable bake with cream cheese&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With fried ginger:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/mild-root-vegetable-curry/&quot;&gt;Mild root vegetable curry with paneer and rice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/iridofu-carrots-shiitake/&quot;&gt;Iridofu with carrots and shiitake
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;appendix-ginger-carbon-footprint&quot;&gt;Appendix: Ginger carbon footprint&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most fresh ginger in the UK is imported from China (somewhat surprising as India is the main producer), so you might be concerned about your ginger carbon footprint. I calculated that the contribution of the ginger to my carbon footprint is at most 0.01%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldshipping.org/industry-issues/environment/air-emissions/carbon-emissions&quot;&gt;CO2 footprint of shipping&lt;/a&gt; is 10 g per km per 1,000 kg of freight.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://sea-distances.org/&quot;&gt;distance from China&lt;/a&gt; is 19,000 km.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My ginger consumption is about 100 g per 2 weeks (7-10 g per meal), so about 2.5 kg per year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;10*19,000*2.5/1,000 =19*25 = 475
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or about half a kilogram CO2 per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the &lt;a href=&quot;http://footprint.wwf.org.uk/&quot;&gt;WWF carbon footprint calculator&lt;/a&gt;, I estimate my carbon footprint to be 7-12 tons of CO2 per year.
This means that my ginger consumption accounts for no more than 0.5/7,000 or 0.0071% of my yearly carbon footprint.&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Japanese-style risotto of black rice, mixed mushrooms and aubergines</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/japanese-risotto-black-rice/"/>
        <updated>2018-04-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/japanese-risotto-black-rice</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/japanese-risotto-black-rice_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;This is a risotto but made from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sainsburys.co.uk/shop/gb/groceries/sainsburys-thai-black-rice-500g&quot;&gt;Thai black rice&lt;/a&gt;, cooked with &lt;em&gt;kombu&lt;/em&gt; seaweed according to a recipe from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/zen-cooking/&quot;&gt;Zen temple cookbook&lt;/a&gt; I bought in Japan.
I added mixed mushrooms and aubergines and serve it topped with &lt;em&gt;edamame&lt;/em&gt; soy beans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#Japanese-style&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Japanese-style&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegan&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#45-minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;45-minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;825 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#800-1000kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_4.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Main ingredients:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 pack (200 g) mixed mushrooms (I used oyster mushrooms, &lt;em&gt;shiitake&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;eryngii&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 small aubergines&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cup of frozen soy beans (&lt;em&gt;edamame&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cup black rice&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seasonings
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;a piece of about 5x10 cm &lt;em&gt;kombu&lt;/em&gt; seaweed&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons finely chopped fresh ginger&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons sesame seeds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon &lt;em&gt;mirin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon sesame oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;for serving: &lt;em&gt;shichimi tougarashi&lt;/em&gt;, golden sesame seeds (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is best (but not absolutely necessary) to soak the rice with the piece of &lt;em&gt;kombu&lt;/em&gt; for an hour in 2 cups of cold water. Otherwise, soak for 5 minutes at least in very hot water. Then take out the &lt;em&gt;kombu&lt;/em&gt; and cut it into small strips.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wash the aubergines and cut into chunks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cut the mushrooms in strips.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In a deep pan with a lid,  heat the olive oil and sesame oil and fry the ginger, mushrooms and sesame seeds until the mushrooms start to brown.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meanwhile, cook the aubergines in the microwave for 8 minutes at full power (900W).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the aubergines, &lt;em&gt;kombu&lt;/em&gt; and the rice to the pan with the soaking liquid of the rice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the &lt;em&gt;mirin&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt;, stir well to dissolve the &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cook, covered, until the liquid has almost been absorbed, so it’s &lt;em&gt;all’onda&lt;/em&gt; like a proper risotto.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meanwhile, cook the soy beans in the microwave for 3 minutes at full power (900W).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Serve with the soy beans as topping.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Yakisoba with carrots and edamame</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/yakisoba-carrots-edamame/"/>
        <updated>2018-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/yakisoba-carrots-edamame</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/yakisoba-carrots-edamame_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yakisoba&lt;/em&gt; (焼きそば) means “fried soba noodles”. This is a stir fry of carrots and soy beams with soba noodles added to the pan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#Japanese-style&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Japanese-style&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegan&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#20-minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;20-minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;625 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#600-800kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_3.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Main ingredients:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;200 g soba noodles&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cup of frozen soy beans (&lt;em&gt;edamame&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;400 g carrots&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;5 dried &lt;em&gt;shiitake&lt;/em&gt;  (soaked)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;some celery&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Seasonings&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon finely chopped fresh ginger&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons sesame seeds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon sesame oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon garlic oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cook the soba noodles for 5 minutes in plenty of water. Wash carefully and drain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meanwhile, microwave the soy beans for 2 minutes at full power (900W).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meanwhile, cut the carrots and the celery into &lt;em&gt;julienne&lt;/em&gt; strips and cook them in the microwave at full power (900W) for 2 to 3 minutes. Drain the cooking liquid into a small bowl.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meanwhile, heat the oil and fry the sesame seeds and ginger for a minute.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the carrots and celery and fry over high heat for a minute or maybe two, depending on how fine you cut them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the &lt;em&gt;shiitake&lt;/em&gt; and soy beans to the pan and fry for a few minutes over low heat.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lower the heat and let simmer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meanwhile, mix the cooking liquid with the &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the mixture to the pan, add the cooked soba noodles and fry over medium heat until the liquid has completely gone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Nabe of yellow peppers, celeriac, shiitake and tofu with rice</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/nabe-yellow-peppers-celeriac-shiitake-tofu/"/>
        <updated>2018-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/nabe-yellow-peppers-celeriac-shiitake-tofu</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/nabe-yellow-peppers-celeriac-shiitake-tofu_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;This is a Japanese-style recipe for a &lt;em&gt;nabe&lt;/em&gt; or hotpot, but with yellow peppers (黄色いピーマン), &lt;em&gt;shiitake&lt;/em&gt; and celeriac (セレリアック), a root vegetable that is less common in Japan.
You need several typically Japanese ingredients for this but I bought everything in the local supermarket except the &lt;em&gt;wakame&lt;/em&gt; and the black bean paste  which I bought in a local Chinese supermarket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fermented broad bean paste (called &lt;em&gt;doubanjiang&lt;/em&gt; in Chinese or &lt;em&gt;tobanjan&lt;/em&gt; (豆板醤) in Japanese) is optional but gives a mild spicy taste to the nabe. Make sure to check the ingredients as there are many types of chilli bean paste and a lot of them are not vegetarian. The Chinese characters are 豆瓣酱. If it says 辛豆瓣酱 then it will be very spicy. The brand I got is &lt;a href=&quot;https://shop.waiyeehong.com/food-ingredients/sauces-oils/other-sauces/chilli-bean-paste-toban-paste&quot;&gt;Pearl River Bridge Chilli Bean Paste&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;em&gt;wakame&lt;/em&gt; seaweed is a traditional ingredient in many &lt;em&gt;nabe&lt;/em&gt; recipes. I bought a Korean brand, &lt;a href=&quot;https://shop.waiyeehong.com/food-ingredients/dried-products/dried-beancurd-seaweed/dried-seaweed-ito-wakame&quot;&gt;A+ Hosan Dried Seaweed (Ito Wakame) (紫菜絲)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This recipe requires 30-45 minutes resting and soaking time for the Japanese rice and 20 minutes cooking time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#Japanese-style&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Japanese-style&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegan&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#gluten-free&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;gluten-free&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#one-pot&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;one-pot&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#20-minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;20-minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;550 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#400-600kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_2.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Main ingredients:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;4 baby yellow peppers (or one large one)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;half a celeriac (about 200 g)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 pack of &lt;em&gt;shiitake&lt;/em&gt; (200 g)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 block of firm tofu (200 g)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cup of Japanese rice&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For seasoning I used:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;a 2 cm piece of ginger, thinly sliced&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;half a teaspoon black bean paste (&lt;em&gt;tobanjan&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 teaspoons dried &lt;em&gt;wakame&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons &lt;em&gt;mirin&lt;/em&gt; (sweet rice wine, optional)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cook the rice  (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/basics&quot;&gt;basics&lt;/a&gt; for how to cook rice).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soak the &lt;em&gt;wakame&lt;/em&gt; in about half a liter cold water.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wash and clean the &lt;em&gt;shiitake&lt;/em&gt;, yellow peppers and celeriac.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cut the vegetables and tofu in pieces of about 2 by 3 cm and about 5 mm thick.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Slice the ginger as thin as you can.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put the peppers and ginger in a microwave pot and add the &lt;em&gt;mirin&lt;/em&gt;. Cook for 4 minutes at full power (900 W).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the &lt;em&gt;shiitake&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;wakame&lt;/em&gt; and celeriac and cook for 6 minutes at full power (900 W).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drain the cooking liquid into a bowl and use it to dissolve the &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt; and black bean paste.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the tofu pieces to the microwave pot.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pour the &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt; mixture over the other ingredients and mix.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cook for 3 minutes at full power (900 W).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Serve with the rice and season to taste with &lt;em&gt;shichimi togarashi&lt;/em&gt; and golden sesame seeds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Aubergines stuffed with stir-fried cauliflower and potato gratin</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/stuffed-aubergines-cauliflower-gratin/"/>
        <updated>2017-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/stuffed-aubergines-cauliflower-gratin</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/stuffed-aubergines-cauliflower-gratin_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;This is my second festive recipe for Quick and Tasty: aubergines stuffed with stir-fried cauliflower, served with potato gratin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegetarian&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegetarian&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#gluten-free&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;gluten-free&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#60-minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;60-minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;675 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#600-800kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_3.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fresh ingredients:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 aubergine (about 200 g)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;half a cauliflower (about 200 g)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tomato (about 100 g)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;400 g potatoes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cm ginger, finely chopped&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;juice of half a lemon&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;100 g Philadelphia cheese&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;4 tablespoons double cream&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;half a cup of grated hard cheese (I used a mix of half Grana Padano and half Jarlsberg)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From the store cupboard
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;a handful of porcini mushrooms, soaked in hot water for 30 minutes (keep the soaking liquid)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon coriander seeds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon cumin&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon allspice&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons pumpkin seeds, ground&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon pine kernels&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon soy sauce&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon sugar&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon garlic oil&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stuffed aubergines
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cut the cauliflower into small florets and cook for 4 minutes in the microwave at full power  (900 W).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cut the aubergine lengthwise into two and scoop out the flesh and set aside. Cook the shells for 4 minutes in the microwave at full power  (900 W).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If you want to save time, start cooking the potatoes for the gratin now.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Chop the aubergine flesh.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Chop the tomato into very small pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Heat the oil and fry the ginger, spices and ground pumpkin seeds for a few minutes. Add the pine kernels and cauliflower and stir-fry over high heat until the cauliflower starts to brown.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the soy sauce, tomato, aubergine flesh, sugar and lemon juice and stir-fry over medium heat until the tomato becomes soft and the aubergine flesh is done. Let it simmer for a few minutes more on low heat.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Stuff the aubergine shells with the mixture and cook for 2 minutes in the microwave at full power  (900 W).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Potato gratin
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cook the potatoes for 10 minutes in the microwave at full power (900 W).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cut the potatoes into thin slices and arrange them in an oven tray.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mix the cream with the Philadelphia cheese and two tablespoons of the porcini mushroom soaking liquid and heat in the microwave for a minute at full power (900 W). Stir and check if it is liquid enough to pour, otherwise heat a bit longer. Add a teaspoon of garlic oil and the porcini mushrooms and pour the mixture over the potatoes.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Bake the pototoes for 2 minutes in the microwave at full power (900 W).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the grated cheese on top and grill for 4 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Some observations from a slow learner of Japanese</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/more-on-learning-japanese/"/>
        <updated>2017-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/more-on-learning-japanese</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/yu_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;I’ve already written on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/learning-japanese&quot;&gt;why and how I started to learn Japanese&lt;/a&gt;, and explained &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/reading-japanese&quot;&gt;how I look up kanji when reading Japanese&lt;/a&gt;. The focus of this post is on how I’m learning and what tools I’ve been using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that the most important factor in learning Japanese is &lt;em&gt;not to give up, to keep working at it steadily, even if it’s only a few minutes every day&lt;/em&gt;. This is probably true for learning any language, but I think more so for Japanese because of the need to learn kanji.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/manpukuji_lanterns.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lanterns in the Manpukuji, a Zen temple in Obaku near Kyoto&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Lanterns in the Manpukuji, a Zen temple in Obaku near Kyoto. Each lantern bears the name of another temple in Kyoto.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started (in 2011), I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.japanesepod101.com/&quot;&gt;JapanesePod101&lt;/a&gt;, and I really think that for absolute beginners it is a very good way to start. I listened to the podcasts on my way to work and found that quite effective. The audio lessons also come with written material covering vocabulary and grammar and the JapanesePod101 YouTube channel has a very large collection of videos. Apart from that I also used &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guidetojapanese.org/learn/&quot;&gt;Tae Kim’s Guide to Learning Japanese&lt;/a&gt;, especially  the grammar guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned this way for about a year, but then I decided I wanted to focus more on reading and less on listening, so I started learning kanji. (To practise conversation I get a two-hour lesson with a Japanese teacher every two weeks.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I try to do at least 5 minutes of kanji practice per day. That really isn’t much, and yet it was sufficient to learn the 2,000 common use (Jouyou,常用) kanji in about four years. As I wrote in my earlier post, by summer 2012 I only knew about 100 kanji, and I finished the Jouyou series before the start of last summer. I still do my daily kanji practice because unless I revise I easily forget them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kanji#Kanji_education&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/817px-3002_Kanji.png&quot; alt=&quot;3002 kanji&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;!-- add a caption --&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A list of 3002 kanji in common use in Japan. The ones in colour constitute 95% of all kanji in newspapers.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have an Android phone, and initially I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.ankiweb.net/&quot;&gt;Anki&lt;/a&gt;, then &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=hu.danieleff.kanji_quiz&amp;amp;hl=en_GB&quot;&gt;Simple Kanji Quiz&lt;/a&gt;, but I felt that I made most progress when I started using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.memrise.com/&quot;&gt;Memrise&lt;/a&gt;. I still use Simple Kanji Quiz because it is very configurable but what I like about Memrise is its goalsetting. It’s quite rewarding to reach your daily goal after five minutes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wanikani.com/&quot;&gt;WaniKani&lt;/a&gt; as well because I love &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tofugu.com/&quot;&gt;Tofugu&lt;/a&gt;, but WaniKani only works if you start from scratch so by the time it came out I had already learned most of the basic kanji.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have thought quite a lot about the best ways to learn but in the end I’ve decided not to be very systematic. For example, my Memrise deck only tests if I know the meaning of a kanji, not its &lt;em&gt;on&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;kun&lt;/em&gt; readings. I have set up my Simple Kanji Quiz to practise readings both ways. So for a given kanji I’m either practising meaning or reading but not both at the same time. My only  kanji handwriting practice is looking up kanji on my phone (I use &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.leafdigital.kanji.android&amp;amp;hl=en&quot;&gt;Kanji Draw&lt;/a&gt; but the &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.renzo.japanese&amp;amp;hl=en&quot;&gt;Japanese&lt;/a&gt; app is also very good). Handwriting kanji on paper takes a lot of time, and unless you live in Japan I don’t think it is an essential skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- some pic here to illustrate vocabulary --&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/genji_uji.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sign with Japanese text&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A summary of Chapter 48 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Tale_of_Genji&quot;&gt;&quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;&lt;/a&gt;, the world&#39;s oldest novel, on a sign in Uji, near Kyoto, where this chapter takes place.&lt;br /&gt;The chapter&#39;s title「早蕨」means &quot;Bracken shoots&quot;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To expand my vocabulary my main approach is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/reading-japanese&quot;&gt;reading&lt;/a&gt;. I also sometimes listen to podcasts or &lt;a href=&quot;https://hooktube.com/watch?v=K-nytjFRTMw&quot;&gt;Japanese music&lt;/a&gt;, or watch &lt;a href=&quot;https://hooktube.com/watch?v=9rGJENEDep4&quot;&gt;anime&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://hooktube.com/watch?v=_LB1mT_u3Uo&quot;&gt;Japanese movies&lt;/a&gt;, and of course I should learn new words while talking to my teacher. But I don’t really spend time in memorising new words, I just let it happen. I found that encountering words in different contexts is a great way to learn. For example, a few days ago I read the word でかい (huge) in a blog post, and then I heard it used in the anime &lt;em&gt;Spirited Away&lt;/em&gt;. Now I’m pretty sure I will remember this word.　&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what really works best for me to build vocabulary is to go to Japan, so of course I would strongly recommend that. The constant immersion works wonders. Many words I remember because I see in my mind the situation where I first encountered them.　&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;70%&quot; src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/railway_crossing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Railway crossing near Kyoto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Celeriac and mushrooms with lentils and rice</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/celeriac-mushrooms-lentils-rice/"/>
        <updated>2017-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/celeriac-mushrooms-lentils-rice</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/celeriac-mushrooms-lentils-rice_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;This is another wintery recipe, a stir-fry of celeriac and mushrooms, with lentils and rice cooked together in one pot. It takes about 30 minutes to prepare. I used dried tomatoes, porcini mushrooms, tomato puree, black bean paste and garlic oil for the &lt;em&gt;umami&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegan&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#gluten-free&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;gluten-free&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#30-minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;30-minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;600 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#400-600kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_2.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fresh ingredients:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;half a celeriac (300 g)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 pack chestnut mushrooms (200 g)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cm fresh ginger, finely chopped&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From the store cupboard
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cup green lentils&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cup brown rice&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;5 dried tomatoes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons dried porcini mushrooms&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon ground cumin&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon ground coriander&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/2 teaspoon black bean paste&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon sunflower seeds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon pumpkin seeds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon tomato puree&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon soy sauce&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon garlic oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wash the rice and the lentils&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soak the 4 tomatoes &amp;amp; 1 1/2 porcini in hot water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put the lentils and rice in a pot with 4 cups of water. Add the cumin, one finely-cut dried tomato and half a tablespoon of porcini mushrooms in small pieces. Cook on the hob or in the microwave.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peel and dice the celeriac and cook in the microwave for 4 minutes at full power (900 W).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heat the oil in the frying pan.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the oil is hot, fry ginger, seeds and spices for a few minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Slice the mushrooms very fine and fry them for a few minutes over high heat.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the soaked tomatoes and porcini, finely cut, and fry  for a few more minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the celeriac, fry some more over medium heat&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the soy sauce, fry some more.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the bean paste and tomato puree, fry a little bit more, add a tablespoon of soaking liquid and serve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Curry of potatoes, parsnips and chickpeas</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/curry-potatoes-parsnips-chickpeas/"/>
        <updated>2017-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/curry-potatoes-parsnips-chickpeas</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/curry-potatoes-parsnips-chickpeas_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;This nice wintery recipe takes about 30 minutes to prepare, it’s a mild potato curry with parsnips and chickpeas with a base of spices and seeds. The tastes of allspice and parsnip go really well together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#curry&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;curry&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegan&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#gluten-free&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;gluten-free&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#30-minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;30-minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;575 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#400-600kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_2.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fresh ingredients:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;about 400 g small potatoes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 medium tomatoes (about 200 g)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;about 400 g parsnips&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tin of chickpeas&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cm fresh ginger, finely chopped&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From the store cupboard
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;spices: allspice, coriander seeds, turmeric, cayenne pepper to taste (I use about a teaspoon of each of the spices and just a pinch of the cayenne pepper)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons pumpkin seeds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon of soy sauce&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon garlic oil&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wash the potatoes and cut them in chunks. Cook them in the microwave for 5 minutes at full power (900 W).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meanwhile, wash the parsnips and cut them in chunks; add them to the potatoes and cook for another 5 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Slice the tomatoes as fine as you can, microwave them for 2 minutes at full power (900 W)..&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you’re using whole seeds like I do, grind the coriander seeds and allspice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heat the oil in a large deep pan. I recommend a non-stick pan with a lid.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the oil is hot, add the ginger, seeds and spices and fry over medium heat for a few minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the chickpeas and stir-fry for a few minutes more over high heat.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clear some space in the middle of the pan and put in the soy sauce. Stir vigorously.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the tomatoes and stir well. Lower the heat and leave to simmer for a few minutes until the tomatoes have softened.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meanwhile, add the potatoes and parsnips to the pan, stir until the potatoes are no longer looking white.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add garlic oil to taste.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is really a complete one-pan meal but you can serve it with rice too.&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Parsnips, bananas, adzuki beans and rice</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/parsnips-bananas-adzuki-beans-rice/"/>
        <updated>2017-09-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/parsnips-bananas-adzuki-beans-rice</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/parsnips-bananas-adzuki-beans-rice_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;I set out to make a curry but decided to make it a bit special by adding bananas and adzuki beans. The tastes combines really well with the parsnips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegan&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#gluten-free&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;gluten-free&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#one-pan&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;one-pan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#20-minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;20-minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;775 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#600-800kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_3.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fresh ingredients &amp;amp; groceries&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 medium parsnip&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 small banana&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 small courgette&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 medium carrot&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;a piece of ginger, about 1 teaspoon when chopped finely&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From the store cupboard&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tin of adzuki beans&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cup of brown rice&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/2 cup of crumbled toast&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon raisins&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon pumpkin seeds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon sunflower seeds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon ground turmeric&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon ground coriander&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon ground cumin&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/2 teaspoon shichimi togarashi or cayenne pepper&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon soy sauce&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon fruit juice&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cook the rice  (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/basics&quot;&gt;basics&lt;/a&gt; for how to cook rice).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clean and dice the parsnip, courgette and carrot and put them in a microwave pot. Cook for 6 minutes at full power (900W).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drain and wash the adzuki beans and let them leak out.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peel and dice the banana.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chop the ginger fine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heat the olive oil and when hot, stir-fry the spices, ginger and seeds over medium heat for about a minute.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the banana pieces and the breadcrumbs and stir-fry for a few minutes over medium heat, stirring all the time so the bananas get coated with the breadcrumbs and seeds.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The parsnips and sweet potato will be ready by now. Add them to the pan.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the raisins and stir-fry for about half a minute over high heat, until the bananas start to brown a little.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reduce the heat. Add the beans and stir-fry for a few minutes more.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the soy sauce and stir-fry briefly over high heat until it is evaporated.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the fruit juice and stir-fry briefly over high heat, then reduce the heat and stir-fry for a few minutes more.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the shichimi togarashi or cayenne pepper, stir and let simmer for about five minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Peppers, tofu, potatoes and black rice</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/peppers-tofu-black-rice/"/>
        <updated>2017-09-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/peppers-tofu-black-rice</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/peppers-tofu-black-rice_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;This is a simple, colourful and very tasty stir-fry of baby bell peppers, potatoes and tofu. In our local supermarket I found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sainsburys.co.uk/shop/gb/groceries/sainsburys-thai-black-rice-500g&quot;&gt;“Thai black rice”&lt;/a&gt;,  a delicious rice that makes for a very nice colour combination.  I cook this with &lt;em&gt;kombu&lt;/em&gt; seaweed according to a recipe from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/zen-cooking/&quot;&gt;Zen temple cookbook&lt;/a&gt; I bought in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegan&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#gluten-free&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;gluten-free&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#20-minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;20-minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;475 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#400-600kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_2.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fresh ingredients &amp;amp; groceries
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;300 g small sweet bell peppers&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;200 g firm tofu&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;200 g small potatoes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cm ginger, finely chopped&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;a handful fresh chives, roughly chopped&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From the store cupboard
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;half a cup of black rice&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 sheet of &lt;em&gt;kombu&lt;/em&gt; seaweed (about 5 cm x 10 cm)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;5 dried &lt;em&gt;shiitake&lt;/em&gt; mushrooms, soaked in hot water for at least half an hour.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon pumpkin seeds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon miso&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon mirin&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon sesame oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 garlic sesame oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put 1 cup of rice and a 5x10cm piece of &lt;em&gt;kombu&lt;/em&gt; together in a pot with 2 cups of cold water and cook for 10 minutes, either on the hob or in the microwave at reduced power (400W).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While the rice is cooking:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Slice the peppers and potatoes into bit-sized chunks and cook them in the microwave with a tablespoon of &lt;em&gt;mirin&lt;/em&gt; for twice 5 minutes at full power (900W). Strain the cooking liquid into a bowl.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;While the vegetables are cooking:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Cut the tofu into large slices and put it in the microwave for 3 minutes at full power (900W). Squeeze the moisture out of the slices as much as possible. Cut the slices into chunks.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Heat the olive oil and when hot, stir-fry the ginger and pumpkin seeds over medium heat for about a minute.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Cut the &lt;em&gt;shiitake&lt;/em&gt; mushrooms into strips and add them to the pan.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Add the chives and tofu and fry over high heat for a minute.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Then add the peppers and potatoes, fry over medium heat.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remove the &lt;em&gt;kombu&lt;/em&gt; from the pot with rice, slice it into smaller strips and return it to the pot. Continue cooking for another 15 minutes or until all the water has been absorbed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add 4 tablespoons of the &lt;em&gt;shiitake&lt;/em&gt; soaking liquid to the cooking liquid of the vegetables and dissolve the &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt; in it.
  _ Pour the mixture in the pan and stir over medium heat until the liquid has been absorbed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Fried potatoes with soy beans, peas and courgette in a mildly spicy sauce</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/potatoes-beans-peas-courgette/"/>
        <updated>2017-06-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/potatoes-beans-peas-courgette</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/potatoes-beans-peas-courgette_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;In this recipe I combined &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/udon-carrots-yuba-knots/&quot;&gt;my &lt;em&gt;umami&lt;/em&gt; sauce&lt;/a&gt; with potatoes, soy beans, peas and courgettes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one ingredient in this recipe that may be a bit harder to find, but it is really worth the effort! I bought these at a Chinese supermarket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fermented broad bean paste (called &lt;em&gt;doubanjiang&lt;/em&gt; in Chinese) is essential. Make sure to check the ingredients as there are many types of chilli bean paste and a lot of them are not vegetarian. The Chinese characters are 豆瓣酱. If it says 辛豆瓣酱 then it will be very spicy. The brand I got is &lt;a href=&quot;https://shop.waiyeehong.com/food-ingredients/sauces-oils/other-sauces/chilli-bean-paste-toban-paste&quot;&gt;Pearl River Bridge Chilli Bean Paste&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the other ingredients can be found in ordinary supermarkets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegan&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;550 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#400-600kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_2.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Main ingredients&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;400 g potatoes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;300 g courgettes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cup of frozen peas and soy beans (combined)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the sauce&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;6 dried tomatoes, finely chopped&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon tomato puree&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;a handful of dried shiitake&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons pumpkin seeds, crushed in a mortar&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cm ginger, finely chopped&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/2 teaspoon miso&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/2 teaspoon black bean paste&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon garlic oil&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two of the ingredients need soaking: the dried tomatoes and &lt;em&gt;shiitake&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soak each of these in a separate pot or bowl in freshly boiled water for at least 30 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After soaking:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Squeeze the liquid out of the tomatoes. Keep the soaking liquid.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wash the &lt;em&gt;shiitake&lt;/em&gt;, then squeeze the liquid out of them and cut the in strips. Keep the soaking liquid.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cook the frozen beans and peas for 2 minutes in the microwave at full power (900 W).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wash the potatoes and dice them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cook the potatoes in the microwave for 10 minutes at full power (900 W), stirring halfway through.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meanwhile, wash the courgettes and slice them thinly. You can cook them in the microwave for a few minutes at full power (900W) to speed up the frying.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meanwhile, heat the oil and fry the ginger for a minute or so.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the pumpkin seeds, the tomatoes and &lt;em&gt;shiitake&lt;/em&gt; and fry over low heat for a few minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the potatoes and courgettes and fry over high heat for a few minutes, until the courgettes are soft and the potatoes have browned.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the beans and peas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt;, black bean paste and tomato puree and two tablespoons each of the soaking liquid of the tomatoes and &lt;em&gt;shiitake&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cook further for a few minutes over low heat, stirring well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Curry of potatoes, spinach and chickpeas</title>
        <link href="http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/curry-potatoes-spinach-chickpeas/"/>
        <updated>2017-05-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/curry-potatoes-spinach-chickpeas</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/curry-potatoes-spinach-chickpeas_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;This very tasty recipe takes about 30 minutes to prepare, it’s a mild potato curry with spinach and chickpeas with a base of spices and seeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#curry&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;curry&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegan&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#gluten-free&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;gluten-free&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#30-minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;30-minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;500 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#400-600kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_2.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fresh ingredients:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;about 400 g small potatoes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 large tomatoes (about 200 g)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;about 200 g spinach&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tin of chickpeas&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cm fresh ginger, finely chopped&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From the store cupboard
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;spices: turmeric, coriander seeds, cumin seeds, cardamom pods, cayenne pepper to taste (I use about a teaspoon of each of the spices and just a pinch of the cayenne pepper)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon sesame seeds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon sunflower seeds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon pumpkin seeds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon of soy sauce&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon garlic oil&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wash the potatoes and cut them in two. Cook them in the microwave for 5 minutes at full power (900 W), stir, cook for another 5 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Slice the tomatoes as fine as you can.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you’re using whole seeds like I do, grind the coriander seeds, cumin seeds and cardamom pods.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heat the oil in a large deep pan. I recommend a non-stick pan with a lid.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the oil is hot, add the ginger, seeds and spices and fry over medium heat for a few minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the chickpeas and stir-fry for a few minutes more over high heat.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clear some space in the middle of the pan and put in the soy sauce. Stir vigorously.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the tomatoes and stir well. Lower the heat and leave to simmer for a few minutes until the tomatoes have softened.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cook the spinach in the microwave at full power (900W) for 1 minute.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meanwhile, add the potatoes to the pan, stir until the potatoes are no longer looking white.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cut up the spinach. Add the spinach to the pan, stir and let simmer for a few more minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add garlic oil to taste.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is really a complete one-pan meal but sometimes I serve it with rice too.&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>
