<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title>Quick &amp; Tasty</title>
    <generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll v4.0.0</generator>
		<icon>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/apple-touch-icon-precomposed.png</icon>
    <subtitle>Quick and Tasty</subtitle>
    <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2021-01-26T19:44:21+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</id>
    <author>
			<name>Wim</name>
			<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
			
		</author>

    
    <entry>
        <title>Ukifune</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/ukifune/"/>
        <updated>2021-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/ukifune</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/ukifune_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LfeKeQ2fhmA&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ukifune&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (浮舟) is a song from 2002 by the Japanese band &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GO!GO!7188&quot;&gt;GO!GO!7188&lt;/a&gt; and one of my all-time favourites. It is a song about broken love, with very poetic lyrics inspired by story from very long ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;春の匂いも芽吹く花も
立ちすくむあたしに君を連れてはこない&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;haru no nioi mo mefuku hana mo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;tachisukumu atashi ni kimi wo tsurete wa konai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When spring comes, I’ll still be frozen and the scents and budding flowers won’t bring you back to me.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;夏が来る頃は明け方の雨
静かに寄り添って　かけら拾い集める&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;natsu ga kuru koro wa akegata no ame&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;shizuka ni yorisotte kakera hiroiatsumeru&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When summer comes, the rain at dawn.&lt;br /&gt; 
Snuggling quietly, I gather up the fragments”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;秋が過ぎたらきっとあたしは
のびた黒い髪を切り落としてしまう&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;aki ga sugitara kitto atashi wa&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;nobita kuroi kami wo kiriotoshite shimau&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When autumn is gone I’m sure I will&lt;br /&gt; 
finally cut off my long black hair.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;愛しい人よ離れ顔なんて　3日もすりゃすぐに忘れてしまった
ただ染みついて消えないのは煙草の匂い&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;itoshii hito yo hanare kao nante mikka mo surya sugu ni wasurete shimatta&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;tada somitsuite kienai no wa tabako no nioi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Darling, you’ve been gone only three days and already I have totally forgotten your face.&lt;br /&gt;
All that remains is the ever-lingering smell of your cigarettes.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;君を待つ日々は足りない　切ない　鳴り止まない
不協和音が響き合って&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;kimi wo matsu hibi wa tarinai setsunai nariyamanai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;fukyouwaon ga hibikiatte&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Waiting for you day after day —&lt;br /&gt; 
it’s futile — heartrending — incessantly ringing —&lt;br /&gt;
a crashing dissonance.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;それがあたしの枯れない　溶けない　鳴り止まない
孤独の唄　来来来…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;sore ga atashi no karenai tokenai nariyamanai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;kodoku no uta rai rai rai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That is my unwithering, unthawing, incessantly ringing&lt;br /&gt;
song of solitude.&lt;br /&gt;
Come, come, come!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;かすかな別れを漂わすこともなく
足音は突然　絶切れた
あぁ悲しくも美しき白い冬&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;kasuka no wakare wo tadayowasu koto mo naku&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;ashioto wa totsuzen tachikireta&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;aa kanashiku utsukushiki shiroi fuyu&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Without even a faint hint of parting —&lt;br /&gt;
The sound of footsteps suddenly cut off.&lt;br /&gt;
Ah, the sad and beautiful white winter.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;会えるものならば他に何も望まない
降り積もるは　あの日も雪&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;aeru mono naraba hoka ni nanimo nozomanai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;furitsumoru wa ano hi mo yuki&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If I could only meet you I would not wish for anything else.&lt;br /&gt;
The snow was falling thickly that day.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;君を待つ日々は足りない　切ない　鳴り止まない
不協和音が響き合って
それがあたしの枯れない　溶けない　鳴り止まない
孤独の唄　来来来…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;kimi wo matsu hibi wa tarinai setsunai nariyamanai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;fukyouwaon ga hibikiatte&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;sore ga atashi no karenai tokenai nariyamanai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;kodoku no uta rai rai rai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Waiting for you day after day —&lt;br /&gt; 
it’s futile — heartrending — incessantly ringing —&lt;br /&gt;
a crashing dissonance.&lt;br /&gt;
That is my unwithering, unthawing, incessantly ringing&lt;br /&gt;
song of solitude.&lt;br /&gt;
Come, come, come!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title of the song, “Ukifune”, is the name of a character in the “Tale of Genji” (&lt;em&gt;Genji monogatari&lt;/em&gt;,源氏物語), a masterpiece of Japanese literature from the early 11th century (Heian period), written by the noblewoman and lady-in-waiting Murasaki Shikibu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word &lt;em&gt;ukifune&lt;/em&gt; (浮舟) is the title of &lt;a href=&quot;http://catalog.lambertvillelibrary.org/texts/Asian/japanese/genji/62.htm&quot;&gt;the chapter where the story starts&lt;/a&gt;. It can be translated as “A Drifting Boat”. As is common in the Tale of Genji, the name of the chapter is used as a nickname for the character. In this case, the title and the character’s name were based on a poem she wrote in which she calls herself “a drifting boat” to express her uncertainty and inner turmoil:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;橘の小島の色は変はらじをこの浮舟ぞ行方知られぬ&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tachibana no&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;kojima no iro ha&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;kawaraji wo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;kono ukifune zo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;yukue chirarenu&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The enduring hue of the Isle of Orange Trees may well never change, yet there is no knowing now where this drifting boat is bound”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The poem is written in winter, with all the land around Uji deeply covered in snow. With her suitor, they have gone out on the Uji river in small boat and moored at the Isle of Orange Trees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the story, when she finds herself caught between two powerful suitors, and it seems that whichever one she choses it will end badly, Ukifune tries to drown herself in the Uji river. She fails and becomes a nun. In the Heian period, when noble women became nuns, they would cut off their very long hair. And in the tale, it is indeed autumn by the time Ukifune becomes a nun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The song has many other classical references, such as the use of 〜き adjectives (美しき) and the &lt;em&gt;on&lt;/em&gt; reading (i.e. the reading derived from the original Chinese proncunciation of the character) &lt;em&gt;rai&lt;/em&gt; of 来 (“come”) used as refrain: &lt;em&gt;rai rai rai&lt;/em&gt;. The word for “song”, &lt;em&gt;uta&lt;/em&gt;, is usually written as 歌 but here as 唄, this more specifically refers to songs accompanied my &lt;em&gt;shamisen&lt;/em&gt;, the traditional three-stringed lute. The song’s mode and melody reflects those traditional songs. It is often said that GO!GO!7188’s music is influenced by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enka&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;enka&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; musical genre, but for this song it is probably more correct to say that it is influenced by the traditional music that gave rise to &lt;em&gt;enka&lt;/em&gt;. And although lost love and loneliness are typical &lt;em&gt;enka&lt;/em&gt; themes, they are universal themes that are also very common themes in the &lt;em&gt;Tale of Genji&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The song starts with a huge reverberating chord, reminiscent of the sound of a &lt;em&gt;biwa&lt;/em&gt; (琵琶), a traditional type of lute that in the Heian period was played at the Imperial court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then follow three verses that repeat the same melody (A) in crescendo. The first word of each verse is a season: spring 春, summer 夏 and autumn 秋.
Then a two new melodies (B/C) are introduced, and a new lyrical theme: the verses address the departed lover. This is followed by the refrain, the single character 来 &lt;em&gt;rai&lt;/em&gt; (“come”) repeated over and over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then follows and instrumental version of A, followed by a dissonant part reflecting the dissonance in the lyrics.
After this interlude comes a verse in melody B that is the heart of the song, the moment when the lover left. Its final word is “winter” 冬.
The following verse in melody C ends in “snow” 雪 and blends into a repetition of the first verse in melody C and the refrain D: the single syllable &lt;em&gt;ki&lt;/em&gt; is both use as the last syllable of the verse, the &lt;em&gt;ki&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;yuki&lt;/em&gt; (“snow”) and the first syllable of the next verse, &lt;em&gt;kimi&lt;/em&gt; (“you”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The references to the seasons in the song reflect the important role the seasons play in traditional Japanese culture. The Tale of Genji is full of allusions to the seasons, season-specific rituals and poetry. Traditional Japanese poetry (&lt;em&gt;waka&lt;/em&gt;) is also often inspired by the seasons, I discussed some of them in my article &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/my-own-private-japan&quot;&gt;“The Beautiful Japan of the Mind”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The banner picture of this article is the statue of Ukifune in Uji, near Kyoto, where the story is set. It is a picture I took during a visit in the summer of 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a live version of the song, recorded at Nihon Budokan in 2005.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;audio controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;source src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/audio/ukifune.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mpeg&quot; /&gt;
Your browser does not support the audio element.
&lt;/audio&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>The Beautiful Japan of the Mind</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/my-own-private-japan/"/>
        <updated>2021-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/my-own-private-japan</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/my-own-private-japan_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;Yasunari Kawabata  (川端康成) was the first Japanese novelist to receive the Nobel prize in Literature. I had read his novel “The Master of Go” (名人) and recently I listened to the BBC dramatised version of “A thousand cranes” (千羽鶴). This led me to look up his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/literature/1968/kawabata/lecture/&quot;&gt;Nobel lecture&lt;/a&gt; “Japan, the Beautiful and Myself” and it made a great impression on me, in particular his discussion of poems by Zen Buddhist monks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The English translation by the eminent &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Seidensticker&quot;&gt;Edward Seidensticker&lt;/a&gt; is excellent, but inevitably some features of the original get lost in translation. This is why I prefer to attempt to read the original Japanese text. 
The Nobel Prize site provides a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/literature/1968/kawabata/25542-yasunari-kawabata-nobel-lecture-1968/&quot;&gt;Japanese version of the lecture&lt;/a&gt; but unfortunately it is a series of images of handwritten text. The handwriting is incredibly regular but the images have such a low resolution that the text is very hard to read. Because of the poor quality, to read it I first created &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/kawabata-nobel-lecture/&quot;&gt;a readable version of the Japanese text&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been two other Japanese Nobel laureates, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/literature/1994/oe/lecture/&quot;&gt;Kenzaburo Oe&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/literature/2017/ishiguro/25124-kazuo-ishiguro-nobel-lecture-2017/&quot;&gt;Kazuo Ishiguro&lt;/a&gt; (who was born in Japan but moved to the UK at the age of five).  Both these authors wrote and delivered their lectures in English, so there is no original Japanese version. Kenzaburo Oe discusses Yasunari Kawabata’s lecture in his own Nobel lecture, titled “Japan, The Ambiguous, and Myself”, a clear reference to the title of Kawabata’s lecture:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Kawabata Yasunari, the first Japanese writer who stood on this platform as a winner of the Nobel Prize for Literature, delivered a lecture entitled Japan, the Beautiful, and Myself. It was at once very beautiful and vague. I have used the English word vague as an equivalent of that word in Japanese &lt;em&gt;aimaina&lt;/em&gt;. This Japanese adjective could have several alternatives for its English translation. The kind of vagueness that Kawabata adopted deliberately is implied in the title itself of his lecture. It can be transliterated as ‘myself of beautiful Japan’. The vagueness of the whole title derives from the Japanese particle ‘&lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;’ (literally ‘of’) linking ‘Myself’ and ‘Beautiful Japan’.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The vagueness of the title leaves room for various interpretations of its implications. It can imply ‘myself as a part of beautiful Japan’, the particle ‘&lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;’ indicating the relationship of the noun following it to the noun preceding it as one of possession, belonging or attachment. It can also imply ‘beautiful Japan and myself’, the particle in this case linking the two nouns in apposition, as indeed they are in the English title of Kawabata’s lecture translated by one of the most eminent American specialists of Japanese literature. He translates ‘Japan, the beautiful and myself’. In this expert translation the traduttore (translator) is not in the least a traditore (betrayer).”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will come back to Oe’s views on Kawabata’s lecture later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/literature/2017/ishiguro/25124-kazuo-ishiguro-nobel-lecture-2017/&quot;&gt;Nobel lecture by Kazuo Ishiguro&lt;/a&gt; is also very much worth reading. I like in particular his description of his realisation that “his” Japan is a mental construct:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I was starting to accept that ‘my’ Japan perhaps didn’t much correspond to any place I could go to on a plane; that the way of life of which my parents talked, that I remembered from my early childhood, had largely vanished during the 1960s and 1970s; that in any case, the Japan that existed in my head might always have been an emotional construct put together by a child out of memory, imagination and speculation. And perhaps most significantly, I’d come to realise that with each year I grew older, this Japan of mine — this precious place I’d grown up with — was getting fainter and fainter.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always been convinced that any place we visit, or a place where we come from but no longer live, is essentially a place “of the mind”, and that is why everyone’s experience of visiting the same place is so different. Our minds best retain the memories that made the strongest impressions on us, and what these are is different for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been to Japan several times, twice for visits of several months. During these visits I’ve worked with researchers at the Disaster Prevention Research Institute of Kyoto University, and explored the temples and shrines of Kyoto. Kawabata’s views and ideas resonate with me because they are close to my “Japan of the mind”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;source-text-and-translation&quot;&gt;Source text and translation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spelling&quot;&gt;Spelling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kawabata was born in 1899 and received the Nobel prize in 1968. This means that he learned to write in the period between 1900 and 1946 when the usage of &lt;em&gt;kana&lt;/em&gt; was &lt;a href=&quot;http://spellingsociety.org/uploaded_journals/j19-journal.pdf&quot;&gt;based on historical principles&lt;/a&gt;, i.e. they reflected the historical pronunciation rather than the actual one. For example, the verb &lt;em&gt;iru&lt;/em&gt; “to be” was written in &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt; as ゐる (&lt;em&gt;wiru&lt;/em&gt;) rather than いる (&lt;em&gt;iru&lt;/em&gt;). The noun &lt;em&gt;kao&lt;/em&gt; “face” was written かほ (&lt;em&gt;kaho&lt;/em&gt;) rather than かお (&lt;em&gt;kao&lt;/em&gt;). In general, many &lt;em&gt;kana&lt;/em&gt; writings used the “h”+vowel (&lt;em&gt;ha&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; etc.) and “w”+vowel (&lt;em&gt;wo&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;em&gt;wi&lt;/em&gt; etc.) were in modern Japanese only the vowel is used; for some words, what is now &lt;em&gt;ka&lt;/em&gt; was &lt;em&gt;kwa&lt;/em&gt;, written くわ. Other difference were the spelling やう (&lt;em&gt;yau&lt;/em&gt;) instead of よう(&lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;), せう(&lt;em&gt;seu&lt;/em&gt;) instead of  しょう (&lt;em&gt;shou&lt;/em&gt;) and similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1946 the &lt;em&gt;kana&lt;/em&gt; spelling was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Japanese_script_reform&quot;&gt;reformed&lt;/a&gt; into the simpler, pronunciation-orientated spelling that is still the standard in modern Japanese. Many &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; were also simplified.
Nevertheless, Kawabata’s Nobel lecture is largely written in the old spelling, and uses some of the old-style kanji (旧漢字, &lt;em&gt;kyuukanji&lt;/em&gt;). This gives the text a peculiar old-fashioned character that is not obvious from the translation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note for example the spelling of 言へる (now 言える) and してゐます (now しています) in one of the first sentences in the essay, a commentary on a poem by the Zen poet Myoe:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;明恵のこの歌には、歌物語と言へるぼどの、長く詳しい詞書きがあって、歌のこころを明らかにしてゐます。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Myoe no kono uta ni wa, utamonogatari to iheru hodo no, nagakukuwashii kotobagaki ga atte, uta no kokoro wo akiraka ni shitewimasu.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-limits-of-translation&quot;&gt;The limits of translation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Kenzaburo Oe pointed out above, exact translation is impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, Kawabata comments that the explanatory note (&lt;em&gt;kotobagaki&lt;/em&gt;, 詞書き ) by Myoe on this own poem is so long and detailed that it could be said to be an &lt;em&gt;utamonogatari&lt;/em&gt;(歌物語, meaning a “short Heian period tale in the form of a poem”), a level of detail not present in the translation which simply says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The second poem bears an unusually detailed account of its origins, such as to be an explanation of the heart of its meaning”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the essay, many poems are quoted, most of them by Buddhist monks. The translator, Edward Seidensticker, received help from a Buddhist scholar (Jikai Fujiyoshi,藤吉慈海) for the quotations and references. They had to translate them in a great rush as Kawabata was still writing his lecture in his hotel on the morning that he had to deliver it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the original Japanese text, the old poems are written in classical Japanese (&lt;em&gt;kobun&lt;/em&gt;, 古文) which is a very different language from modern Japanese, with different grammar and vocabulary. As it is impossible to render this in English, we get a modern translation instead. To a Japanese reader, the poems therefore have an entirely different feeling, probably similar to what an English reader experiences with the original &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/43521/beowulf-old-english-version&quot;&gt;Beowulf&lt;/a&gt;, or a Dutch speaker reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dbnl.org/tekst/_kar001kare01_01/_kar001kare01_01_0001.php&quot;&gt;Karel ende Elegast&lt;/a&gt;. This is of course not essential to the message of the lecture but it illustrates the difficulties facing the translator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;zen-buddhism-and-poetry&quot;&gt;Zen Buddhism and poetry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the poems quoted are &lt;em&gt;tanka&lt;/em&gt;, (短歌 meaning “short poem”), a poem consisting of 31 mora in  five units, usually following a 5-7-5-7-7 pattern of mora per unit. For example, the first poem (written here a unit per line to show the structure) is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;春は花&lt;br /&gt;
夏ほととぎす&lt;br /&gt;
秋は月&lt;br /&gt;
冬雪ざえて&lt;br /&gt;
冷しかりけり&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“In the spring, cherry blossoms, in the summer the cuckoo.&lt;br /&gt;
In autumn the moon, and in winter the snow, clear, cold.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and the second one&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;雲を出でて&lt;br /&gt;
我にとちなふ&lt;br /&gt;
冬の月&lt;br /&gt;
風や身にしむ&lt;br /&gt;
雪や冷めたき&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The winter moon comes from the clouds to keep me company.&lt;br /&gt;
The wind is piercing, the snow is cold.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I find most interesting is Kawabata’s observation on this second poem. Myoe provided the following note about his inspiration for this poem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“When the hour of the midnight vigil came, I ceased meditation and descended from the hall on the peak to the lower quarters, and as I did so the moon came from the clouds and set the snow to glowing. The moon was my companion, and not even the wolf howling in the valley brought fear. “&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kawabata says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“My reason for choosing [this poem] has to do with its remarkable gentleness and compassion. Winter moon, going behind the clouds and coming forth again, making bright my footsteps as I go to the meditation hall and descend again, making me unafraid of the wolf: does not the wind sink into you, does not the snow, are you not cold? I choose the poem as a poem of warm, deep, delicate compassion, a poem that has in it the deep quiet of the Japanese spirit.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kawabata further discusses a particular poem that is very easy to understand, but nevertheless loses a lot in translation, because the visual effect and structure are untranslatable:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;あかあかやあかあかあかやあかあかやあかあかあかやあかあかや月&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;aka aka ya&lt;br /&gt;
aka aka aka ya&lt;br /&gt;
aka aka ya&lt;br /&gt;
aka aka aka ya&lt;br /&gt;
aka aka ya tsuki&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that even this poem is a &lt;em&gt;tanka&lt;/em&gt;! The translation is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Bright, bright, and bright, bright, bright, and bright, bright.&lt;br /&gt;
Bright and bright, bright, and bright, bright moon.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kawabata observes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Seeing the moon, he becomes the moon, the moon seen by him becomes him. He sinks into nature, becomes one with nature. The light of the “clear heart” of the priest, seated in the meditation hall in the darkness before the dawn, becomes for the dawn moon its own light.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zen monks like Dogen and Myoe spent a lot of their time in meditation. As a result, they were able to live as much in the present as possible and to have as little sense of self as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dogen and Myoe lived in the 13th century. The final poem I want to highlight is the deathbed poem of the priest Ryokan who lived much later (1758-1831):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;形見として何か残さん舂は花山ほととぎす秋はもみぢ葉&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“What shall be my legacy? The blossoms of spring,&lt;br /&gt;
The cuckoo in the hills, the leaves of autumn.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kawabata says&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“In this poem, as in Dogen’s, the commonest of figures and the commonest of words are strung together without hesitation — no, to particular effect, rather — and so they transmit the very essence of Japan.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and further&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Ryokan pursued literature and belief in the benign spirit summarized in the Buddhist phrase “a smiling face and gentle words”. In his last poem he offered nothing as a legacy. He but hoped that after his death nature would remain beautiful. That could be his bequest.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The phrase “a smiling face and gentle words” is a “four-kanji idiom” (&lt;em&gt;yojijukugo&lt;/em&gt;,四字熟語), pronounced as &lt;em&gt;wagan aigo&lt;/em&gt;. Its origin is from a Buddhist text called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.acmuller.net/bud-canon/sutra_of_immeasurable_life.html#div-9&quot;&gt;“The Sutra of Immeasurable Life”&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“With an expression of tenderness in his face and with kindness in his speech, he spoke to others in consonance with their inner thoughts.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It carries the connotation that &lt;a href=&quot;https://crd.ndl.go.jp/reference/modules/d3ndlcrdentry/index.php?page=ref_view&amp;amp;id=1000061578&quot;&gt;the bodhisattva speaks gentle words to guide people&lt;/a&gt;. The web site of the Honganji temple in Kyoto has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hongwanji.or.jp/mioshie/words/000916.html&quot;&gt;a nice explanation (in Japanese)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-did-kawabata-include-these-poems-in-his-lecture&quot;&gt;Why did Kawabata include these poems in his lecture?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/literature/1994/oe/lecture/&quot;&gt;his own Nobel lecture&lt;/a&gt;, Kenzaburo Oe expresses his views on the use of classical poetry in Kawabata’s lecture:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Even as a twentieth-century writer Kawabata depicts his state of mind in terms of the poems written by medieval Zen monks. &lt;em&gt;Most of these poems are concerned with the linguistic impossibility of telling truth.&lt;/em&gt;  According to such poems words are confined within their closed shells. The readers can not expect that words will ever come out of these poems and get through to us. One can never understand or feel sympathetic towards these Zen poems except by giving oneself up and willingly penetrating into the closed shells of those words.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Why did Kawabata boldly decide to read those extremely esoteric poems in Japanese before the audience in Stockholm? I look back almost with nostalgia upon the straightforward bravery which he attained towards the end of his distinguished career and with which he made such a confession of his faith. Kawabata had been an artistic pilgrim for decades during which he produced a host of masterpieces. After those years of his pilgrimage, only by making a confession as to how he was fascinated by such inaccessible Japanese poems that baffle any attempt fully to understand them, was he able to talk about ‘Japan, the Beautiful, and Myself’, that is, about the world in which he lived and the literature which he created.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Daffodils</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/daffodils/"/>
        <updated>2020-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/daffodils</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/daffodils_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;A whimsical fedi music collaboration between Eidon and Wim. This is a twin post, the other version is &lt;a href=&quot;https://noblogo.org/eidon/daffodils&quot;&gt;on Eidon’s blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the finished track. We hope you like it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;audio controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;source src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/audio/Daffodils-integration-retimed.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mpeg&quot; /&gt;
Your browser does not support the audio element.
&lt;/audio&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eidon-says&quot;&gt;Eidon says:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 200%&quot;&gt;“It &lt;/span&gt;
all started from the title, really. “Daffodils”. Nice word, which reminds of many things – an Arcadia of beautiful flowers and their scent, or Wordsworth’s famous poem, for instance. Among the many spurious thoughts that such a word could evoke, there was one that triggered the resolve to create a piece of music from it: the presence of letters that can be interpreted as note names, together with others that can not. Of the many possible mappings, this one was chosen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/Theme.png&quot; alt=&quot;A piece of musical score showing the theme of Daffodils.&quot; title=&quot;A piece of musical score showing the theme of Daffodils.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The theme of &quot;Daddodils&quot;: ‘D’, ‘A’, ‘F’, ‘F’, rest, ‘D’, rest, rest, (rest)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where ‘real’ notes where used when a music counterpart existed, and `imaginary’ (inaudible) notes otherwise. The singular form led to 8 quavers and an easy 4/4 metre. The result was found sufficiently interesting and worth pursuing, and a composition was started from there. Three voices, initially appointed two two electric guitars and electric bass, with the theme exposed and repeated by the first guitar, soon joined by the cortege of its companions, all moving in an ostinato slow-pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In retrospective, it is possible that, from the very beginning, it all was leading to Wordsworth’s poem – the choice of the tempo, for instance. Whatever the actual case, at some point it became clear that the connection with “I Wandered Lonely As A Cloud” had to be made explicit. At first we thought to only sing the poem’s final verses; and then Wim had the great idea to recite the whole poem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The track was created with &lt;a href=&quot;http://tuxguitar.com.ar/&quot;&gt;TuxGuitar&lt;/a&gt;, a nice tabulature editor whose notes input interfaces include guitar fretboards. So yes all the instruments you can hear in Daffodils have been composed… on guitar ^_^. Some of the sounds were produced via the Timbres Of Heaven soundfont, while for others we used MuseScore, after importing MIDI files exported from TuxGuitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/Tux.png&quot; alt=&quot;TuxGuitar UI.&quot; title=&quot;The TuxGuitar UI.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The TuxGuitar UI&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://musescore.org/&quot;&gt;MuseScore&lt;/a&gt; is much more powerful than TuxGuitar. It allows to orchestrate voices from multiple soundfonts at the same time, for instance, and to export the voices as separate audio files. Once the voices have been chosen and isolated, we used Audacity to orchestrate them together. The original TuxGuitar voices were then mixed with MuseScore voices from the Sonatina Symphonic Orchestra,  and the Nice Keys Suite soundfonts, plus that of a Steinway piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.audacityteam.org/&quot;&gt;Audacity&lt;/a&gt; is perhaps not the best tool one could use, though it has certain valuable features. One such feature is so-called Envelope Tool: with it, it is possible to finely control the volume of each voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/Audax.png&quot; alt=&quot;Audacity UI for the Envelope Tool.&quot; title=&quot;Audacity UI for the Envelope Tool.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Each voice is wrapped in a “control envelope”, which changes the volume of the track proportionally to the ‘height’ of the envelope.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allows fade-ins and fade-outs, and thus can simulate the entrance and exit of instruments. This has been used extensively in Daffodils!
“&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wim-says&quot;&gt;Wim says:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 200%&quot;&gt;“Eidon &lt;/span&gt;
wrote this great track “Daffodils” as he explained above, and he sent me a draft and asked if I could recite the verses from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/45521/i-wandered-lonely-as-a-cloud&quot;&gt;Wordsworth’s poem&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t know what he thought my voice would contribute to the work, maybe he wanted a Flemish-Scottish accent?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eidon had in mind that I would recite the final two verses only:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And then my heart with pleasure fills,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;And dances with the daffodils.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I misunderstood him, and I recited the entire poem. That turned out to be serendipitous, as we are both happy with the final result. But I’m running ahead of myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used my laptop’s built-in mic as that is all I have. The audio quality is acceptable but far from great, so from the start I had this idea that I wanted to apply some distorting effects to the voice. I thought it might work well with the track which is quite modern and rather different from what a more conventional composer might associate with the image of daffodils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d never done this before, so it was an interesting experiment. I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.audacityteam.org/&quot;&gt;Audacity&lt;/a&gt; for the recording and for all processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recorded the audio in two takes, and combined the best parts. There is nothing to say about the recording: I just read the poem out loud, at a pace that seemed natural to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First I improved the audio quality. I knew from past experience that a good way to do it is to apply the following effects:
• Noise Reduction with default settings
• Equalisation (Graphic EQ) with the “Bass Boost” preset
• &lt;a href=&quot;https://manual.audacityteam.org/man/compressor.html&quot;&gt;Compressor&lt;/a&gt; with default settings
• &lt;a href=&quot;https://manual.audacityteam.org/man/reverb.html&quot;&gt;Reverb&lt;/a&gt; with the “Vocal I” preset&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then also doubled the voice, with a very slight shift between the tracks, so there is no perceptible echo but the sounds is a little bit fuller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially I had wanted to use only the vocoder. But Audacity’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://manual.audacityteam.org/man/vocoder.html&quot;&gt;Vocoder effect&lt;/a&gt; is not quite what I had in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The default setting for the Vocoder results in a rather tame distortion. My settings are&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;    Distance: 50.0
    Output choice: Both channels
    Number of vocoder bands: 60
    Amplitude of original audio (percent): 100.0
    Amplitude of white noise (percent): 0.0
    Amplitude of Radar Needles (percent): 50.0
    Frequency of Radar Needles (Hz): 80.0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is a bit like speaking through a tube, with added radar needles, a series of short pulses which give a robotic effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://manual.audacityteam.org/man/phaser.html&quot;&gt;Phaser&lt;/a&gt; could introduce some interesting distortions. Again, the default effect is quite tame. I used the following setting, on a separate copy of the voice track:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;    Stages: 20
    Dry/Wet: 180
    LFO Frequency (Hz): 0.6
    LFO Start Phase (deg.): 50.0
    Depth: 120
    Feedback (%): 75
    Output gain (dB): -3.0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is a space-like oscillator sound overlaying the speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was still not happy with the result so I added another copy of the voice track Reverb using the “Church Hall” preset, which gives a huge echoing sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I combined these three tracks with the original one, taking care that I did not entirely drown out the recitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then combined this track with Eidon’s music. I tweaked the pauses between the verses to match the music and tweaked the volume of the voice here and there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final verses are repeated three times, because somehow I thought that fit with the music.
“&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eidon-says-1&quot;&gt;Eidon says:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 200%&quot;&gt;“No &lt;/span&gt;
greater bias than the authors’ opinion, maybe, though we are quite pleased with the results. Music and verse dance together, and hearts with pleasure fill. Therefore, it is likely that this first move into musical/poetical co-creation shall be followed by new experiments soon!
“&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The track is available on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://open.tube/videos/watch/e26710c0-8813-4691-b4e6-ef0e36e49848&quot;&gt;OpenTube&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://peertube.uno/videos/embed/f746036d-76ec-48fa-bce0-8caf85b68195&quot;&gt;PeerTube.uno&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://funkwhale.it/library/tracks/826/&quot;&gt;Funkwhale.it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our album “Daffodils and Other Flowers” is available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://funkwhale.it/library/albums/184/&quot;&gt;Funkwhale.it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;330&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://funkwhale.it/front/embed.html?&amp;amp;type=album&amp;amp;id=184&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Daffodils” and “Daffodils and Other Flowers” is © 2020 Eidon and Wim. https://octodon.social/@wim_v12e, Eidon@tutanota.com.&lt;br /&gt;This work is licensed under a &lt;a rel=&quot;license&quot; href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;license&quot; href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Creative Commons Licence&quot; style=&quot;border-width:0&quot; src=&quot;https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-sa/4.0/88x31.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>The True Pure Land</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/shinshu-prayer/"/>
        <updated>2020-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/shinshu-prayer</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/shinshu-prayer_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;I am currently reading the original Japanese version of “Tokyo Ueno Station” by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miri_Yu&quot;&gt;Yu Miri&lt;/a&gt;,『JR上野駅公園口』. It’s a very nice but difficult novel, I may write more about it later. After I wrote the &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/four-wisdoms&quot;&gt;article on the Buddhist prayer “The Four Wisdoms”&lt;/a&gt;, I came across a passage in the novel that describes a Buddhist funeral and it contains a prayer used by the  Jōdo Shinshū (浄土真宗, “The True Essence of the Pure Land Teaching”),  known as Shinshū in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-prayer&quot;&gt;The prayer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prayer in the book is written in archaic Japanese with old forms of &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; and grammar and uncommon words:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;　 　 　 　 長 本 浄 娑 ツ 佛 イ 弘&lt;br /&gt;
　 　 　 　 時 師 土 婆 子 恩 ヅ 誓&lt;br /&gt;
　 　 　 　 ニ 釋 无 永 ニ フ レ ノ&lt;br /&gt;
　 　 　 　 慈 迦 爲 劫 弥 カ ノ チ&lt;br /&gt;
　 　 　 　 恩 ノ ヲ ノ 陀 ク ト カ&lt;br /&gt;
　 　 　 　 ヲ チ 期 苦 ヲ オ キ ラ&lt;br /&gt;
　 　 　 　 報 カ ス ヲ 念 モ ニ ヲ&lt;br /&gt;
　 　 　 　 ズ ラ ル ス ズ ヒ カ カ&lt;br /&gt;
　 　 　 　 ベ ナ コ テ ベ ツ 娑 フ&lt;br /&gt;
　 　 　 　 シ リ ト 、 シ 、 婆 ラ&lt;br /&gt;
　 　 　 　 　 　 　 　 　 　 ヲ ズ&lt;br /&gt;
　 　 　 　 　 　 　 　 　 　 い バ&lt;br /&gt;
　 　 　 　 　 　 　 　 　 　 デ&lt;br /&gt;
　 　 　 　 　 　 　 　 　 　 ン&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-puzzle&quot;&gt;The puzzle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could not understand the poem, but I was curious about its meaning so I tried to find out. First of all, here is a list of the special &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt;, words and constructions that I did not understand:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;弘誓 (ぐぜい, &lt;em&gt;guzei&lt;/em&gt;): &lt;a href=&quot;http://bschawaii.org/shindharmanet/bloom/ab-writings/salvation/&quot;&gt;Buddha’s universal vow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;娑婆 (しゃば, &lt;em&gt;shaba&lt;/em&gt;): The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sah%C4%81&quot;&gt;Sahā world&lt;/a&gt;, the mundane world.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;佛: an older form of 仏 (&lt;em&gt;butsu&lt;/em&gt;), Buddha&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;仏恩 (ブツオン、ぶっとん, &lt;em&gt;button&lt;/em&gt;): Buddha’s blessings, the grace of Buddha’s compassion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;弥陀 (みだ,&lt;em&gt;mida&lt;/em&gt;): Amitabha (a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/topic/Buddhism/Celestial-buddhas-and-bodhisattvas&quot;&gt;celestial Buddha&lt;/a&gt;, the principal buddha in Pure Land Buddhism)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;永劫 (えいごう, here pronounced &lt;em&gt;yōgō&lt;/em&gt;): Eternity, perpetuity. 劫 (&lt;em&gt;kō&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;gō&lt;/em&gt;) means &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kalpa_%28aeon%29&quot;&gt;kalpa&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;浄土 (じょうど, &lt;em&gt;jōdo&lt;/em&gt;): Lit. “pure land”, esp. the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/topic/Sukhavati&quot;&gt;Western Pure Land&lt;/a&gt; paradise of Amitabha.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;无爲: old kanji for 無為 &lt;em&gt;mui&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oxfordreference.com/view/10.1093/oi/authority.20110810104405611&quot;&gt;asaṃskṛta&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;the ‘unconditioned’, a term referring to anything that transcends conditioned (saṃskṛta) existence in the state of saṃsāra.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;期スル (ごする,&lt;em&gt;go suru&lt;/em&gt;): to live&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;本師 (ホンシ,&lt;em&gt;honshin&lt;/em&gt;): Lit. “fundamental guru”, i.e. Buddha&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;釋: an older form of 釈, lit. &lt;em&gt;shaka&lt;/em&gt;, short for &lt;em&gt;Shakamuni&lt;/em&gt; (釈迦牟尼), the historical Buddha.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;慈恩 (じおん_jion_): deep compassion, benevolence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ナリ: なり (&lt;em&gt;nari&lt;/em&gt;) is the classical version of である, “to be”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ベシ: べし (&lt;em&gt;beshi&lt;/em&gt;) is the classical version of べき, “something one ought to do”. In the prayer, 念 ずべし means 念 ずるべき,”should pray”, and 報 ずべし means 報 ずるべき, “should inform”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these terms and the &lt;em&gt;furigana&lt;/em&gt; in the novel, I could do a transcription in &lt;em&gt;romaji&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;guzei no chikara wo kafurazuba&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;idzure no toki ni ka shaba wo iden&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;button fukaku omohitsu,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;tsune ni mida wo nen zubeshi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;shaba yōgo no ku wo sute,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;jōdo mui wo go suru koto&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;honshi shaka no chikara nari&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;jōji ni jion wo hō zubeshi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So at least I can now pronounce the prayer, and I get a rough idea of the meaning. But of course I wanted to know the details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-origin&quot;&gt;The origin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By searching for snippets rewritten with modern &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt;, I found that the prayer is taken from a book of hymns called &lt;em&gt;Kōsō Wasan&lt;/em&gt; (『高僧和讃』, the “Japanese Hymns of Praise of the Virtuous Priest”), a collection of hymns written by the founder of the sect, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.learnreligions.com/shinran-449983&quot;&gt;Shinran (親鸞)&lt;/a&gt;, who lived between 1173 and 1263 and was a remarkable person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, these are the two final hymns from “Twenty-six Hymns based on the Writings of Master Shan-tao”. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chinabuddhismencyclopedia.com/en/index.php?title=Shan-tao&quot;&gt;Shan-tao&lt;/a&gt; is one of the seven masters (patriarchs) of Shinshū. He lived from 613 to 681 and is generally credited for popularizing the &lt;em&gt;nembutsu&lt;/em&gt; as the reciting of Amida’s name (see below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-meaning&quot;&gt;The meaning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complete works of Shinran in English translation are available &lt;a href=&quot;http://shinranworks.com/&quot;&gt;on line&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://shinranworks.com/hymns-in-japanese/hymns-of-the-pure-land-masters/shan-tao/&quot;&gt;translation of the two hymns&lt;/a&gt; taken from there is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Had we not received the power of the universal Vow,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;When can we part from this Saha world?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Reflecting deeply on the Buddha’s benevolence,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Let us think on Amida always.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Casting off long kalpas of painful existence in this world of Saha,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;We live in expectation of the Pure Land, the uncreated;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;That is the power of our teacher, Shakyamuni;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Let us respond always in gratitude for his compassion and benevolence.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pure Land Buddhism holds that there is a kind of Paradise called the Pure Land, and once one is there it is easier to reach Nirvana. Shinran advocated to trust to the power of Amitābha (&lt;em&gt;Amida&lt;/em&gt;), as made manifest in his Universal Vow, to attain enlightenment. The main Jōdo Shinshū practice is called &lt;em&gt;nembutsu&lt;/em&gt;, “Mindfulness of the Buddha”. The nembutsu is simply reciting the phrase &lt;em&gt;Namu Amida Butsu&lt;/em&gt; (“I take refuge in Amitābha Buddha”, written 南無阿弥陀佛). For more information see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.shinbuddhism.info/kw86.htm&quot;&gt;the detailed discussion of the meaning of the hymns&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-conclusion&quot;&gt;The conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is yet another example of how reading Japanese remains a difficult but very stimulating activity for me: there are lots of riddles to be solved. In translation, most of the mystery disappears. And every time I look into such a little mystery, I learn lots of new things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The banner picture is of the Nishi Hongan-ji (本願寺, Temple of the Primal Vow)) in Kyōto, the largest of all the Jōdo Shinshū branches.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>The four wisdoms</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/four-wisdoms/"/>
        <updated>2020-10-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/four-wisdoms</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/four-wisdoms_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;A friend asked me about if I knew a Japanese Buddhist prayer suitable for a funeral. I knew that at funerals and memorial services, the monks chant Buddhist text in &lt;em&gt;bongo&lt;/em&gt; (梵語), a Japanese transliteration of Sanskrit. The practice is known as &lt;em&gt;shōmyō&lt;/em&gt; (声明) and a text that is often chanted is called &lt;em&gt;shichi&lt;/em&gt; (四智), “the Four Wisdoms”, or &lt;em&gt;shichibongo&lt;/em&gt; (四智梵語) in full.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-four-wisdoms-text-in-japanese&quot;&gt;The Four Wisdoms text in Japanese&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, &lt;em&gt;shōmyō&lt;/em&gt; texts are written using specific and quite unusual Chinese characters, but they are used purely for their phonetic value, not for their meaning. Here is the text in full, from the site of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.buzan.or.jp/index-1-1.html&quot;&gt;Buzan sect&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.philtar.ac.uk/encyclopedia/easia/shingon.html&quot;&gt;Shingon Buddhism&lt;/a&gt;. It also has a recording of the chanting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/shingon_kongoukai.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chinese characters written left-to-right, top-to-bottom, columns of irregular length&quot; title=&quot;Chinese characters written left-to-right, top-to-bottom, columns of irregular length&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Four Wisdoms in kanji and hiragana, from the site of the Buzan sect&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same text with only very minor differences is used also by the sects of &lt;a href=&quot;https://tendaiuk.com/tendai-buddhism/&quot;&gt;Tendai Buddhism&lt;/a&gt;, but I focus here on Shingon only for convenience. The word &lt;em&gt;shingon&lt;/em&gt; (真言, lit. “True Words”) is the translation of the Sanskrit word Mantra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-the-japanese-text-to-the-original-sanskrit&quot;&gt;From the Japanese text to the original Sanskrit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found the &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;katakana&lt;/em&gt; for this text in &lt;a href=&quot;https://tais.repo.nii.ac.jp/?action=repository_action_common_download&amp;amp;item_id=450&amp;amp;item_no=1&amp;amp;attribute_id=22&amp;amp;file_no=1&quot;&gt;a Japanese academic paper on the meaning of the &lt;em&gt;shichibongo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;四智梵語&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
オム　バザラ　サトバ　ソギャラカ&lt;br /&gt;
唵　　嚩日囉　薩怛嚩　蘇蘗　囉賀&lt;br /&gt;
バザラ　アラタンノウ　マドタラン&lt;br /&gt;
嚩日囉　囉　怛　曩　　摩覩怛覧&lt;br /&gt;
バザラ　タラマ　キャヤタイ&lt;br /&gt;
嚩日囉　達　麽　誐　夜那&lt;br /&gt;
バザラ　キャラマ　キャロ　ハムバ&lt;br /&gt;
嚩日囉　羯　　磨　迦　嚕　婆　縛&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This transliterates in &lt;em&gt;romaji&lt;/em&gt; as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;shichibongo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;om bazara-satoba sogyaraka&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;bazara-aratannou madotaran&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;bazara-tarama kyayatai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;bazara-kyarama kyaro hamba&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same paper also gave the original Sanskrit phrasing, transliterated in the roman alphabet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;oṃ vajrasattva samgrahād&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;vajraratnam anuttaraṃ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;vajradharma gāyanair&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;vajrakarma karo bhava&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-does-the-sanskrit-text-say&quot;&gt;What does the Sanskrit text say?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sanskrit version allowed me to search for a translation. I found one in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.routledgehandbooks.com/doi/10.4324/9781315172354.ch3&quot;&gt;a book on Japanese music&lt;/a&gt; that discussed &lt;em&gt;shōmyō&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oṃ.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Receiving the blessing of the wisdom of Vajra-sattva,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;we obtain the ultimate vajra-ratna.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;By chanting the vajra-dharma,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;we may attain the vajra-karma of enlightenment.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not familiar with esoteric Buddhism so I found this translation hard to understand. I therefore looked a bit further into this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-background-on-esoteric-buddhism&quot;&gt;Some background on esoteric Buddhism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we need to know about &lt;em&gt;Vajrayana&lt;/em&gt;, also know as Esoteric  Buddhism, the Buddhist tradition of which Shingon Buddhism is a branch. According to the according to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/topic/Vajrayana&quot;&gt;Encyclopaedia Britannica&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vajrayana, (Sanskrit: “Diamond Vehicle” or “Thunderbolt Vehicle”) form of Tantric Buddhism that developed in India and neighbouring countries, notably Tibet. Vajrayana, in the history of Buddhism, marks the transition from Mahayana speculative thought to the enactment of Buddhist ideas in individual life. The term vajra (Sanskrit: “diamond” or “thunderbolt” ) is used to signify the absolutely real and indestructible in a human being, as opposed to the fictions an individual entertains about himself and his nature; yana is the spiritual pursuit of the ultimately valuable and indestructible.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/topic/Buddhism/Vajrayana-Tantric-or-Esoteric-Buddhism&quot;&gt;further&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vajrayana first emerged in various parts of India and Sri Lanka. The esoteric nature of Tantric doctrine and practice makes identifying the origins of the Vajrayana school difficult, but some Buddhist traditions associate them with Nagarjuna and Asanga and therefore suggest that Vajrayana began to develop quietly in the 2nd or 4th century CE. Vajrayana was prominent in India and Tibet, and a form of it spread to China and then to Japan, where it became associated with the Tendai and Shingon schools.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, we need to know about the concept of the &lt;em&gt;mandala&lt;/em&gt;. Again according to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/topic/mandala-diagram&quot;&gt;Encyclopaedia Britannica&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mandala, (Sanskrit: “circle”) in Hindu and Buddhist Tantrism, a symbolic diagram used in the performance of sacred rites and as an instrument of meditation. The mandala is basically a representation of the universe, a consecrated area that serves as a receptacle for the gods and as a collection point of universal forces.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-mandala-of-the-diamond-realm&quot;&gt;The Mandala of the Diamond Realm&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shingon Buddhism makes frequent use of two &lt;em&gt;mandalas&lt;/em&gt;, the Mandala of the Womb Realm and the Mandala of the Diamond Realm (Kongōkai Mandala, 金剛界 曼荼羅). &lt;em&gt;kongō&lt;/em&gt; (金剛) means “diamond” or “adamant, and is a translation of the Sanskrit “vajra”. These realms and their composition are based on an esoteric Buddhist sutra called the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.shingon.org/teachings/ShingonMikkyo/KongochoKyo.html&quot;&gt;Vajrasekhara Sutra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Diamond Realm (金剛界 Kongōkai) is a metaphysical space inhabited by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thezengateway.com/teachings/the-five-wisdom-buddhas-vairocana&quot;&gt;Five Wisdom Buddhas&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Shingon Buddhism, there is a group of deities, known as the Vajra Bodhisattva. The “Four Wisdoms” refers to the four Vajra Bodhisattva that surround &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.shingon.org/teachings/ShingonMikkyo/Dainichi.html&quot;&gt;Dainichi Nyorai&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.onmarkproductions.com/html/mandala-guidebook.html&quot;&gt;Shiin-e (四印会) section&lt;/a&gt; of the Kongōkai Mandala.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/Kongokai-shiin-e.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Detail of the Kongōkai Mandala showing five seated Buddha-like figures arranges in a cross, within a circle&quot; title=&quot;Detail of the Kongōkai Mandala showing five seated Buddha-like figures arranges in a cross, within a circle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Shiin-e (四印会) and ichiin-e (一印会) sections of the Kongōkai Mandala, Heian period, 9th century (Tōji Temple, Kyōto, National Treasure) (https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Kongokai.jpg)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dainichi Nyorai (大日如来) is the Buddha in the highest form of existence, dharmakaya, &lt;em&gt;hosshin&lt;/em&gt; (法身) in Japanese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;finally-back-to-the-four-wisdoms&quot;&gt;Finally, back to the Four Wisdoms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus the Four Wisdoms of the text refer to these four Vajra Bodhisattva:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kongōsatta 金剛薩埵 ( Vajra-sattva, “diamond being”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kongōhō 金剛宝 ( Vajra-ratna, “diamond treasure”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kongōhō 金剛法 ( Vajra-dharma, “diamond law”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kongōgyō 金剛業 ( Vadra-karma, “diamond action” ).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the explanation on the site of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.buzan.or.jp/index-1-1.html&quot;&gt;Buzan sect&lt;/a&gt;, these four bodhisattva are identified with the four wisdom buddha surrounding Dainichi Nyorai in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thezengateway.com/teachings/the-five-wisdom-buddhas-vairocana&quot;&gt;Five Wisdom Buddhas&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Four Wisdoms represents the wisdom of the four Wisdom Buddhas, and by making offerings to each other, the Four Wisdoms represent the entire mandala of Vajrayana, with Dainichi Nyorai in the center.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/902px-Kongokai.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Kongōkai Mandala, consisting of nine panels, three by three. Eight of them are  showing five seated Buddha-like figures arranges in a cross, within a circle. The middle panel in the top row shows a single larger seated Buddha-like figure.&quot; title=&quot;The Kongōkai Mandala, consisting of nine panels, three by three. Eight of them are  showing five seated Buddha-like figures arranges in a cross, within a circle. The middle panel in the top row shows a single larger seated Buddha-like figure.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Kongōkai Mandala, Heian period, 9th century (Tōji Temple, Kyōto, National Treasure) (https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Kongokai.jpg)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The banner picture is of the Great Buddha of Kamakura.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Frozen yoghurt with dates</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/frozen-yoghurt/"/>
        <updated>2020-07-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/frozen-yoghurt</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/frozen-yoghurt_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;This is a simple and low-tech recipe for frozen yoghurt with just two ingredients. It uses dates as a natural source of sugar. The amounts are for two portions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;250 g Greek style yoghurt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50 g Medjool dates, pitted and chopped&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon candied orange peel (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put the yoghurt, dates and orange peel in a freezer-safe container and stir.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For the lazy way, place the mixture in the fridge for a few hours or overnight (so the dates will dissolve) and stir; for the quick way, blend the mixture.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put the container in the freezer for 20 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stir the mixture well. Make sure to loosen ice forming on the walls of the container and to mix it in.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Repeat the freezing and stirring until you get the desired consistency. For soft ice texture this will take about four more cycles, for a more solid texture about seven.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>About reading Murakami as a way to learn Japanese</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/learning-japanese-reading-murakami/"/>
        <updated>2020-07-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/learning-japanese-reading-murakami</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/learning-japanese-reading-murakami_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in my previous posts (&lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/reading-murakami/&quot;&gt;Reading Murakami in Japanese&lt;/a&gt;,
   &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/more-on-learning-japanese/&quot;&gt;Some tips for reading Japanese as a learner&lt;/a&gt;,
   &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/learning-japanese/&quot;&gt;My journey of learning Japanese&lt;/a&gt;), I started reading Murakami Haruki’s “1Q84” in Japanese in October 2014. The paperback version consists of 6 volumes (2 for each Book), 2,057 pages in total. At the end of June 2020, I finally finished the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had started learning Japanese in early 2011 in preparation for a research trip. Unfortunately because of the tsunami and the nuclear disaster the trip didn’t go ahead. But I did go to Japan for two months in the summer of 2012 and again in the summer of 2014. So I had been learning Japanese for about four years and had four months of a more or less immersive experience before I started on the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I had been learning Japanese  in a rather haphazard, not very systematic way, because I felt it was more fun that way. Nevertheless, I had put in a considerable amount of time and effort.
I took some group lessons but they did not continue beyond the very basics. Then I took one-to-one lessons with a Japanese teacher, which was a much better way to learn. The lessons focused on conversation and grammar but we didn’t cover kanji. I started learning kanji using several apps. The one I’ve been using most consistently is Memrise, to study the meanings of the Jouyou kanji. I don’t like mnemonics-based methods like Heisig’s, and I’ve paid the price for that, because apparently with that method you can learn all readings and meanings for all 2,136 Jouyou kanji in a few months. Whereas all these years later, I still have to practise every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what did I learn through reading Murakami? Despite &lt;a href=&quot;http://selftaughtjapanese.com/2016/07/08/what-its-like-reading-haruki-murakami-novels-in-their-original-japanese/&quot;&gt;what others may say&lt;/a&gt;, I learned that reading Murakami is hard. Initially, a page took me more than half an hour. Now, after six years, it takes me about five minutes, but that is still much lower than my English reading speed: reading the same passage in English only takes a minute. Arguably Murakami’s writing style is comparatively straightforward, and personally I had (even) more difficulty reading Banana Yoshimoto’s “Tokage” than 1Q84, but that doesn’t mean that I found Murakami easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I determined, despite that or because of it, not to give up. I kept going, a few pages at a time. Eventually I got there.
I found that reading with a dictionary and looking up the readings and meanings of any character or word I didn’t know is not only wonderfully engaging but also really works as a way to learn Japanese. My reading skills have improved dramatically, and so have my vocabulary and my grasp of grammar. As a result, my writing, listing and speaking skills have also improved. So on the whole, I would recommend reading a Japanese novel as a way of learning Japanese, if you are not in a hurry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I also learned I still have so much to learn. I still don’t know all readings for the Jouyou kanji, and keep forgetting the meanings. I still struggle with conversation (although that may partly be as a result of my tendency of overcomplicating things and wanting to be too precise) and with handwriting. I started handwriting practice in 2018. It requires a better understanding of the structure of the kanji, but it is fun and my recall is improving. I still have a long way to go before I’ll be able to write all Jouyou kanji.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have written down some of my observations before: &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/reading-murakami/&quot;&gt;Reading Murakami in Japanese&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/more-on-learning-japanese/&quot;&gt;Some tips for reading Japanese as a learner&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/learning-japanese/&quot;&gt;My journey of learning Japanese&lt;/a&gt;. One specific thing I started noticing only when reading the last two volumes of 1Q84 is that, when I see a word and I think I can’t pronounce it, often it turns out I can after all, if I just make a little more effort, a kind of mental jump into the unknown. There is a wonderful Japanese expression for this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kiyomizu no butai kara tobioriru&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;清水の舞台から飛び降りる&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(きよみずのぶたいからとびおりる)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which literally translates as “to jump off the platform of the Kiyomizu-dera temple”, but means “to make a leap into the dark”. (The platform of the beautiful and ancient Kiyomizu-dera temple in Kyoto offers great views but is also twelve metres high, so jumping off it may not be a good idea.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recall is sometimes more about daring rather than about remembering: rather than going for conscious recall, trust your unconscious mind to pick the right reading. You actually remember more than you think you remember.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;coda-the-novel-itself&quot;&gt;Coda: the novel itself&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may wonder: having spent nearly six years reading it, do I think it is a good book? I do. It was certainly for the most part entertaining and interesting. I have written three posts about various remarkable points in the book (&lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/repetition-in-1Q84/&quot;&gt;Repetition in Murakami’s 1Q84&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/1Q84-kuukisanagi/&quot;&gt;Why the ‘Little People’ say ‘Ho ho’&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/cold-or-not/&quot;&gt;Cold or not: a riddle in Murakami’s 1Q84&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are there aspects I don’t like? Yes. The ending leaves me wanting to know what happened to the other characters. Also, there is a bit too much repetition, which I think is a consequence of the book being published in three parts, and in every part Murakami (or his publisher) has felt it necessary to provide sufficient background on what happened before so that each part can be read on its own. There are some parts that I found a bit slow, because I was impatient to get back to the plot, but usually even these parts were actually quite interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, will I ever re-read it? Maybe, if my Japanese reading speed ever gets close to my English one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The banner picture is the dragon-shaped spout of the water basin at the entrance of the Kiyomizu-dera temple in Kyoto&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Brownies with dates and walnuts</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/brownies/"/>
        <updated>2020-06-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/brownies</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/brownies_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;This is a simple and quick recipe for delicious brownies with very few ingredients. It uses dates as a natural source of sugar. The rich high-cocoa content chocolate makes butter unnecessary so they happen to be vegan. The amounts are for two brownies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50 g dark chocolate (70% cocoa)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;25 g extra dark chocolate (85% cocoa)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50 g Medjool dates, pitted and chopped&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;50 self-rising white wheat flour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5 tablespoons tepid water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;12 g walnuts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon candied orange peel (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heat the chocolate au bain marie, ideally at 35 °C.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the chocolate has melted, gradually add the flour, mixing thoroughly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add 2 tablespoons of water, mix well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then add the dates and the organge peel, mix well while adding in the rest of the water. The mixture must be moist and stick together.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then add the walnuts. You can also simply push the walnuts into the dough just before baking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put the mixture in small ramekins lined with aluminium foil.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Preheat the oven on 160 °C and bake for 25 minutes at 160 °C.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leave to cool in the ramekins.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Cold or not: a riddle in Murakami's 1Q84</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/cold-or-not/"/>
        <updated>2020-06-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/cold-or-not</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/cold-or-not_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/reading-murakami&quot;&gt;mentioned before&lt;/a&gt;, I have been slowly reading Haruki Murakami’s novel 1Q84 in Japanese. Like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/23/magazine/the-fierce-imagination-of-haruki-murakami.html&quot;&gt;all his novels&lt;/a&gt;, this novel is many things. For this article I want to view it as a reflection on morality. Almost all of the characters have to make complex moral choices based on incomplete or incorrect information. One such character is Tamaru, a bodyguard and security expert in the service of a rich old widow who has embarked on a personal crusade against domestic violence. He is at the same time a very cultured person and a consummate professional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this article is really about a something that puzzled me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one of the final chapters (Chapter 25 of Book 3), just before he has to make a very hard moral choice, Tamaru recounts an interesting story about the famous Swiss psychologist Carl Gustav Jung. He explains how Jung lived in a large house in Zürich, but wanted a place to think and work in solitude. So he built a place which he called the “Tower”, in Bollingen near the shore of the Zürich lake. He built it with his own hands from stones from a local quarry, and had to join the guild become a licensed stone mason to be allowed to do so. It was an austere place, without gas, electricity or running water. On the lintel above the entrance, Jung engraved a phrase which in Japanese reads:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;冷たくても、冷たくなくても、神はここにいる&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tsumetakutemo, tsumetakunakutemo, kami wa koko ni iru&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the English translation by Philip Gabriel, this runs “Cold or Not, God Is Present”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This phrase is also the title of the chapter, and I think that because of this story about Jung, this chapter might very well be the key chapter of the entire novel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was intrigued by the phrase and started to read up on Jung, to try and find out more about this story. It turns out that the story as told by Tamaru is not entirely accurate: Jung did indeed build the tower with his own hands. He started building it in 1923, when he was 48, and worked on it and reshaped it for most of the rest of his life &lt;a href=&quot;https://thefirstgates.com/2014/01/02/jungs-tower-simplicity-and-the-inner-life/&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. And he did put an inscription above the entrance of the original tower. It is the same inscription that was first engraved over the entrance of his house in Küsnacht &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jungatlanta.com/articles/summer14-two-houses.pdf&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the words as mentioned by Tamaru are different from the inscription. The original inscription is in Latin and reads “Vocatus atque non vocatus deus aderit”, which translates as “Bidden or unbidden, the god will be present”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The origin of this phrase is interesting: the Latin phrase is from the Adagia, a collection of sayings from ancient sources collected by Erasmus. The actual source is the  “History of the Peloponnesian War”, written around 400 BC by the Athenian historian and general Thucydides. In it, he recounts how the Spartans asked the Oracle of Apollo in Delphi if it would go well with them if they went to war with Athens. The oracle answered that if they put all their strength into the war, victory would be theirs, and that “the god himself would be there, whether invoked or uninvoked” &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.harvardreview.org/content/culled-and-not-culled-the-poet-will-be-there/#return-link-5&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jung himself knew this background, and he commented “It says: yes, the god will be on the spot, but in what form and to what purpose? I have put the inscription there to remind my patients and myself: Timor dei initium sapientiae.” (Fear of God is the start of wisdom) &lt;a href=&quot;http://carljungdepthpsychology.blogspot.com/2017/03/carl-jung-it-is-delphic-oracle-though.html&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. Jung’s view on religion was that people need a God because a person needs to recognise a higher authority than the ego. Without a God, a person will make a God out of something else. So there will be a God in people’s lives, whether they want it or not, for good or for worse. Hence the choice of the phrase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the original phrase is different from Tamaru’s quote, either Tamaru has it wrong, or in the parallel universe of 1Q84, the inscription is different. That is of course very well possible: as the novel makes clear, 1Q84 is superficially the same as 1984 but differs from it in many subtle ways; Tamaru being a person who is very precise in his mental habits, it is not so likely that he would not have checked the translation of a phrase which he considers so important. In fact, he comments that “There’s some deep allusion here, something difficult to interpret.”. So I am assuming that in the 1Q84 universe, the inscription is different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am of course not the first one to point this out &lt;a href=&quot;http://hyoshiok.hatenablog.com/entry/20130617/p1&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;, and several people have surmised that this is a pun on cold/called, [&lt;a href=&quot;https://chazzw.wordpress.com/2011/11/13/more-of-the-things-you-learn-in-books/&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&quot;https://citronimus.de/haruki-murakami-1q84/&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;] because a possible English translation of the Latin phrase is “Called or uncalled, God is present”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As explained above, this is only one possible translation – “vocatus” could be translated as “bidden” or “summoned” as well, and “the god” is more accurate than “God” – and somehow I find this theory not satisfactory.
At first sight, the cold/called theory may seem to be corroborated because Tamaru mentions that the Catholic orphanage where he grew up was always cold, even in summer. However, in Japanese, Tamaru there uses the word “samui” (寒い) which means that it felt cold to him, whereas in the phrase he uses the word “tsumetai” (冷たい), which means that something is cold. Because of his experience in that cruel place, he also says that as far as he is concerned, if God existed, He could not be said to be kind at all. The Japanese adjective shinsetsu (親切,しんせつ) which he uses means “kind,” but is used to describe the character of someone based on their actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am therefore inclined to interpret the “tsumetai” as “emotionally cold, unfeeling, indifferent”. In other words, God is here, but we don’t know if he is indifferent or not. That is to my mind also closer to Jung’s own interpretation of the Latin phrase, and yet different of course, as might be expected in 1Q84.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think it is a coincidence that Murakami introduces Jung at the end of this novel. Arguably, the actions of many of the characters match Jung’s views on good and evil. For example Ushikawa, who is the protagonist of the chapter, and quite a creep, is at some point shown his dark side (&lt;a href=&quot;http://compassreview.org/summer03/6.html&quot;&gt;what Jung calls the Shadow&lt;/a&gt;) but decides to embrace it instead of reject it. 
 And it is not a stretch to view the Little People as a kind of collective god: they have no individuality but collectively they have supernatural powers. They are also clearly not bound by human morals, and are (not unlike the Greek gods) quite indifferent to the fate of humans. And they speak through a human, i.e. a prophet, or an oracle. Considering that Jung developed the theory of the collective unconscious, and the notion of archetypes, having a collective god seems fitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The banner picture of this article is the cover of the 2nd volume of Book 3 in the Japanese paperback. In Japanese, “1Q84” and “1984” are both pronounced as “ichi-kew-hachi-yon”, that’s why this is written underneath the title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cover illustration for each volume is a detail of &lt;a href=&quot;https://archief.ntr.nl/tuinderlusten/en.html&quot;&gt;“The Garden of Earthly Delights” by Jheronimus Bosch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;a href=&quot;https://thefirstgates.com/2014/01/02/jungs-tower-simplicity-and-the-inner-life/&quot;&gt;Jung’s Tower: simplicity and the inner life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jungatlanta.com/articles/summer14-two-houses.pdf&quot;&gt;A Tale  of Two  Houses: Küsnacht and Bollingen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.harvardreview.org/content/culled-and-not-culled-the-poet-will-be-there/#return-link-5&quot;&gt;Culled and Not Culled, the Poet Will Be There&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4] &lt;a href=&quot;http://carljungdepthpsychology.blogspot.com/2017/03/carl-jung-it-is-delphic-oracle-though.html&quot;&gt; Carl Jung: It is a Delphic oracle though.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5] &lt;a href=&quot;http://hyoshiok.hatenablog.com/entry/20130617/p1&quot;&gt;冷たくても、冷たくなくても、神はここにいるの謎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6] &lt;a href=&quot;https://chazzw.wordpress.com/2011/11/13/more-of-the-things-you-learn-in-books/&quot;&gt;More…of The Things You Learn in Books&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7] &lt;a href=&quot;https://citronimus.de/haruki-murakami-1q84/&quot;&gt;Haruki Murakami: 1Q84 (in German)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8] &lt;a href=&quot;http://compassreview.org/summer03/6.html&quot;&gt;Jung and the moral self&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>White bread with raisins and walnuts</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/white-bread/"/>
        <updated>2020-04-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/white-bread</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/white-bread_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;Making bread is very easy if you take some care. You only need yeast, flour, water and salt. The whole process takes about four hours, but the total amount of active work is only half an hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from an oven, you will need the following items:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A recipient to mix your dough. It should hold least 2 or 3 l, for example a plastic pot or stainless steel cooking pot. I can strongly recommend the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lekue.com/eu/cookware/bread-maker-lekue.html&quot;&gt;Lekue Bread Maker&lt;/a&gt;, a silicone bread mould that can go straight into the oven.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A spoon or fork for mixing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optional: a baking tin to shape your loaf. I use the Lekue for this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optional: kitchen scales. Mine is a very plain model from Salter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this loaf you need only four ingredients:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3.5 g dried yeast (half a sachet)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;280 g water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;400 g strong white wheat flour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4 g salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following ingredients are optional. I like to add some seeds, nuts and/or dried fruit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;25 g raisins or sultanas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;25 g chopped walnuts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a handful of sunflower seeds to put on top&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main difference between this recipe and the more common ones is the amount of water, which is considerably higher (most recipes say 200 ml for 400 g).  As a result, the dough is not as easy to knead and much more sticky.
This is why we use the “folding” technique as explained in the videos from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bakewithjack.co.uk/videos/2019/6/6/bread-tip-101-beginners-sourdough-loaf-start-to-finish&quot;&gt;Bake with Jack&lt;/a&gt;. Another great tip from that video is to sprinkle your hands with water instead of flour to stop the dough from sticking to them.
With the extra water the dough rises a lot better, so the result is a more open texture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add all ingredients to your mixing container&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mix thoroughly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knead for about ten to fifteen minutes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leave to rise in a cold oven. I put a tray with hot water in the oven and let the dough rise there, so it keeps warm and wet.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After half an hour, fold the dough 12 times. “Folding” means that you pull on the dough, which is very elastic, and fold the pulled flap over the main ball of dough. The  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bakewithjack.co.uk/videos/2019/6/6/bread-tip-101-beginners-sourdough-loaf-start-to-finish&quot;&gt;Bake with Jack&lt;/a&gt;  video shows very clearly how to do this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leave for half an hour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fold 6 times; leave for half an hour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fold 6 times; leave for another half an hour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Preheat the oven on 230 °C&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fold another 6 times&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As you can see from the picure, I sprinkled some sunflower seeds on top.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bake for 15 minutes at 230 °C. I put a small container with very hot water on the baking tray to get some steam.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bake for another 30 minutes at 200 °C.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leave to cool on a rack.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Sourdough starter</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/sourdough-starter/"/>
        <updated>2020-04-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/sourdough-starter</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/sourdough-starter_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;Making &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sourdough&quot;&gt;sourdough&lt;/a&gt; bread is very easy if you take some care. The videos and blog from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bakewithjack.co.uk/videos/2019/6/6/bread-tip-101-beginners-sourdough-loaf-start-to-finish&quot;&gt;Bake with Jack&lt;/a&gt; helped me a lot.  In particular, I use his method for making the &lt;em&gt;sourdough starter&lt;/em&gt;, with only a minor tweak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;making-the-starter&quot;&gt;Making the starter&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making a sourdough starter is very easy. Most recipes use wholemeal rye flour but I use wholemeal wheat flour which is a little less sour. This recipe is for 150 g sourdough starter, which is the amount I use for a single loaf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take a container of about 500 ml. I use a plastic mug with a lid, it does not have to close tightly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add 25 g flour and 25 g water at 35 °C, mix (I use the handle of spoon), leave for 24 hours at room temperature (20-25 °C; the warmer, the quicker).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Repeat for three consecutive days. It should roughly double in volume. If so, it’s ready to use; if not, leave it for another day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;feeding-the-starter&quot;&gt;Feeding the starter&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have made this starter, keeping it going it is very simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When you make your first loaf with a fresh starter, leave about 20 g starter in the container to make your next batch. I just keep this in the fridge.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then, the day before I bake the next loaf, in the morning, add 75 g water  at 35 °C and 75 g flour to the container, stir well, and leave it at room temperature for a day. Put it in the fridge before you go to bed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The next day, take the started out of the fridge 3-4 hours before you start to bake.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Because you have now 170 g starter in the container, you can use 150 g for the loaf and then feed the starter again, for as long as you like.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Sourdough bread</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/sourdough-bread/"/>
        <updated>2020-04-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/sourdough-bread</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/sourdough-bread_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;Making &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sourdough&quot;&gt;sourdough&lt;/a&gt; bread is very easy if you take some care.  You only need flour, water and salt. The whole process takes about five hours, but the total amount of active work is only half an hour. The videos and blog from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bakewithjack.co.uk/videos/2019/6/6/bread-tip-101-beginners-sourdough-loaf-start-to-finish&quot;&gt;Bake with Jack&lt;/a&gt; helped me a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from an oven, you will need the following items:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A container of about 500 ml for the sourdough starter. I use a plastic mug with a lid, it does not have to close tightly. A glass jar is fine too.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A container of about 500 ml for water.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A spoon or fork for mixing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A recipient to mix your dough. It should hold least 2 or 3 l, for example a plastic pot or stainless steel cooking pot. I can strongly recommend the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lekue.com/eu/cookware/bread-maker-lekue.html&quot;&gt;Lekue Bread Maker&lt;/a&gt;, a silicone bread mould that can go straight into the oven.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optional: a baking tin to shape your loaf.  With my recipe, the dough is quite wet so it does not keep its shape well. I use the Lekue for this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optional: kitchen scales. Mine is a very plain model from Salter.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optional: a thermometer to make sure your water is at the right temperature. Not essential, but handy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference between sourdough bread and ordinary bread is that you use a &lt;em&gt;sourdough starter&lt;/em&gt; instead of baking yeast. The great thing about a sourdough starter is that you can very easily make it yourself, from just flour and water. Have a look at  &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/sourdough-starter/&quot;&gt;my recipe&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this loaf I only use four ingredients:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;150 g sourdough starter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;450 g water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;675 g wholemeal wheat flour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;8 g salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First add 150 g starter to your mixing container.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then add 450 g water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then add 675 g flour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then add 8 g salt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mix thoroughly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knead for about ten minutes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leave to rise in a cold oven. I put a tray with hot water in the oven and let the dough rise there, so it keeps warm and wet.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After 30 minuts, fold the dough 12 times. “Folding” means that you pull on the dough, which is very elastic, and fold the pulled flap over the main ball of dough. The  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bakewithjack.co.uk/videos/2019/6/6/bread-tip-101-beginners-sourdough-loaf-start-to-finish&quot;&gt;Bake with Jack&lt;/a&gt;  video shows very clearly how to do this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leave for an hour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fold 6 times; leave for an hour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fold 6 times; leave for another hour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Preheat the oven on 230 °C&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fold another 6 times&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As you can see from the picure, I sprinkled some pumpkin seeds on top.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bake for 20 minutes at 230 °C. I put a small container with very hot water on the baking tray to get some steam.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bake for another 40 minutes at 200 °C.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leave to cool on a rack.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I usually bake in the evening, and wrap the loaf in a towel overnight to keep the crust from drying out too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/sourdough-bread-slices.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A few slices of sourdough bread&quot; title=&quot;A few slices of sourdough bread&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Doesn't it look delicious?&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>The Winds of Kyoto</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/the-winds-of-kyoto/"/>
        <updated>2020-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/the-winds-of-kyoto</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/the-winds-of-kyoto_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;I wrote a very short story for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.writersinkyoto.com/2019/12/writers-in-kyoto-present-the-fifth-annual-kyoto-writing-competition/&quot;&gt;Fifth Annual Kyoto Writing Competition&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/kyoto-gis.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kyoto building heights heat map&quot; title=&quot;Kyoto building heights heat map&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Height of buildings in Kyoto,  from a paper [1] by  DPRI researchers&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the &lt;a href=&quot;www.dpri.kyoto-u.ac.jp/en/&quot;&gt;Disaster Prevention Research Institute&lt;/a&gt; of Kyoto University, researchers are modelling the flow of the wind over the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wind that blows over the tiny machiyas of Gion and around Kyoto station with its tall hotels and the Tower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spring, it scatters a storm of sakura petals all over the city. In the rainy season, it blows down from Arashiyama along the waters of the Katsuragawa, and carries streams of clouds over the hills. When the temple ponds are full of lotus flowers, it stirs the lanterns and chases the incense smoke, and cools the faces of the teams that pull the Yamaboko along Shijou Doori. At the end of summer, when the higanbana is blooming, that same wind follows the railway line to Uji and blows in through the open window of the researchers’ offices, rifling the stacks of diagrams that reveal its very flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But sometimes that flow gathers to a tremendous strength, and then a typhoon will lacerate the city. The models of the wind predicts this, to make sure the people of Kyoto are prepared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then Kyoto hunkers down, and waits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the storm has passed, the sky is a transparent clear and blue. The wind of Kyoto is once again cool and mild, blowing gently over the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/les-reynolds-stress.png&quot; alt=&quot;Reynolds stress of wind flow over Kyoto, at 4 different heights&quot; title=&quot;Reynolds stress of wind flow over Kyoto, at 4 different heights&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Result of wind flow simulation over Kyoto,  from a paper [1] by  DPRI researchers&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10546-018-0344-8&quot;&gt;Yoshida, T., Takemi, T. &amp;amp; Horiguchi, M. Large-Eddy-Simulation Study of the Effects of Building-Height Variability on Turbulent Flows over an Actual Urban Area. Boundary-Layer Meteorol 168, 127–153 (2018). &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>On puppets and being human</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/ghost-in-the-shell-puppets/"/>
        <updated>2020-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/ghost-in-the-shell-puppets</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/ghost-in-the-shell-puppets_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;Ghost in the Shell is a series of Japanese animated movies (&lt;em&gt;anime&lt;/em&gt;,アニメ) featuring cyborgs (“cybernetic organism”, in this case a  human with both organic and robotic body parts). I was struck by the frequent references to puppets in several of the movies, and I want to explore the symbolism behind this.
I will look in particular at the movies “Ghost in the Shell”, “Innocence” and “Solid State Society”, because in these movies the references are most clear. Familiarity with the movies is not required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;puppets-dolls-marionettes-mannequins&quot;&gt;Puppets, dolls, marionettes, mannequins&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use the word puppet as the most general word. A doll to my mind is a puppet used as a child’s toy. A marionette is a puppet with strings to manipulate it. And a mannequin is a puppet in the sense that it is a representation of a human. I would say that the crucial property is that a puppet is somewhat articulated or can be made to move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Japanese there are also several words for puppets and dolls.
The most common word is &lt;em&gt;ningyō&lt;/em&gt;, 人形 , “doll, puppet”. The word &lt;em&gt;nin&lt;/em&gt; means person and &lt;em&gt;gyō&lt;/em&gt; means form, shape.
Specifically, &lt;em&gt;ayatsuriningyō&lt;/em&gt;, 操り人形, sometimes shortened to just &lt;em&gt;ayatsuri&lt;/em&gt;, 操り, means a puppet controlled by an operator, e.g. a marionette. The word &lt;em&gt;ayatsuri&lt;/em&gt; means “manipulation”. The other word that is used in Ghost in the Shell is &lt;em&gt;kairai&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;kugutsu&lt;/em&gt;, 傀儡, this is an older word and not so common (neither of the kanji is in common use). It is an interesting word because both its characters mean “puppet”. The first, 傀, is composed of “person” and “ghost”; the second is likely simply a variant, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/%E5%82%80%E5%84%A1#Japanese&quot;&gt;is only used in this word&lt;/a&gt;. The reading &lt;em&gt;kugutsu&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://kotobank.jp/word/%E5%82%80%E5%84%A1%E5%AD%90-55054&quot;&gt;apparently&lt;/a&gt; derives from &lt;em&gt;kugu&lt;/em&gt;, 久具, a plant from which the baskets were woven that were used to transport the puppets by itinerant puppet players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cyberbrains-and-ghosts&quot;&gt;Cyberbrains and ghosts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Ghost in the Shell series, one of the main themes that is being explored is what defines a human. A cyborg is a human with all or parts of its body replaced by artificial components. In the Ghost in the Shell universe, even the brain can be treated this way, being augmented by a cyberbrain (&lt;em&gt;dennō&lt;/em&gt;,電脳), essentially an electronic system with a similar functionality, but connected to the net).
In the most extreme case, the entire human brain is replaced by a cyberbrain which contains the content of the original human brain.
By contrast, robots do not start out human. The difference between a robot and a full-cyborg human is only the origin of the data in the brain.
In Ghost in the Shell, the word ghost is colloquial slang for an individual’s consciousness or soul, which is what sets it apart from a robot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the plot of the second movie, “Innocence”, is that robots get a ghost through a process called “ghost dubbing”, i.e. copying the ghost from a human and putting it into the robot cyberbrain. This idea returns in the recent “Arise” series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-brief-note-on-the-characters&quot;&gt;A brief note on the characters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article I will mention a few characters from the series who belong to a kind of special state intelligence unit called “Public Security Section 9” (公安９課):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“The Major”, Motoko Kusanagi, a female cyborg, the main character in the series.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Batō, a male cyborg, the protagonist in “Innocence”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Togusa, a human with a cyberbrain, the companion of Batō in “Innocence”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I mention a character from “The Individual Eleven” series, Hideo Kuze, a male cyborg, a very charismatic revolutionary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ghost-in-the-shell-1995&quot;&gt;Ghost in the Shell (1995)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first Ghost in the Shell movie, there is no strong symbolism of puppets, but there are several references.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Project 2501&lt;/em&gt; is a program that can stealthily manipulate politics and intelligence, altering databases and the memories in people’s cyberbrains. While traversing the net as it performed its tasks, Project 2501 acquired and processed so much information that it eventually achieved self-awareness. Its creators regarded this as a bug in the program. When Project 2501 realised that its programmers would try to kill it when they discovered it had become sentient, it devised a plan to ensure its own safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the manipulations of Project 2501 are discovered, they are initially assumed to be the work of an extremely skilled hacker, nicknamed the Puppet Master (人形使い,&lt;em&gt;ningyoutsukai&lt;/em&gt;), presumably because it is a master manipulator and the people whose cyberbrains are hacked become effectively sock puppets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth nothing that at the end of the movie, Project 2501 is assimilated into the cyberbrain of Motoko Kusanagi. So from a certain angle Kusanagi becomes the Puppet Master.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more oblique but to my mind more important puppet reference is the scene where Motoko Kusanagi rides on a passenger boat on the canals of Hong Kong. This is a long montage without dialogue. Kusanagi sees someone very much like herself at a table in a restaurant. Is it a human or a cyborg? She also looks at some mannequins in a shop window, and the scene ends with an empty shop with undressed, partially disassembled mannequins. You can’t help but think about how she must see a parallel between herself and these puppets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;innocence-2004&quot;&gt;Innocence (2004)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second Ghost in the Shell movie, “Innocence”, is where the puppet symbolism is present most strongly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main reference to puppets in Ghost in the Shell “Innocence” is an implicit one: the title song is called the Puppet Song, of which I wrote in &lt;a href=&quot;http://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/ghost-in-the-shell-manyoshi/&quot;&gt;an earlier article&lt;/a&gt;. The full title of the song is &lt;em&gt;kugutsu-uta: uramite chiru&lt;/em&gt; (傀儡謡「怨恨みて 散る」, くぐつうた「うらみてちる」) which means “Puppet song: The flowers resentfully fall”. The theme of the song is mortality. It is used a few times in the movie, but most prominently in the opening scene, which shows the creation of a humanoid robot, and in the parade scene, which is based on a Taiwanese Buddhist temple procession and involves giant puppet-like figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is another reference, one that I found particularly interesting. After the parade scene, Togusa sees the following poem written on a wall:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;落一棚生&lt;br /&gt;
落線頭死&lt;br /&gt;
磊断傀去&lt;br /&gt;
磊時儡来&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The writing order is top to bottom, right to left, and it is an archaic and poetic form of Japanese without hiragana. Togusa reads it in full as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;生死の去来するは、&lt;br /&gt;
棚頭の傀儡たり。&lt;br /&gt;
一線断ゆる時、&lt;br /&gt;
落落磊磊。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;せいしのきょらいするは、&lt;br /&gt;
ほうとうのかいらいたり、&amp;lt;b
いっせんたゆるとき、&lt;br /&gt;
らくらくらいらい&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;seishi no kyorai suru wa,&lt;br /&gt;
hōtō no kairai tari,&lt;br /&gt;
issen tayuru toki,&lt;br /&gt;
rakuraku rairai.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the dubbed version, this is translated as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Life and death come and go&lt;br /&gt;
like marionettes dancing on a table.&lt;br /&gt;
Once their strings are cut,&lt;br /&gt;
they easily crumble.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;rakuraku rairai&lt;/em&gt; is particularly poetic. &lt;em&gt;raku&lt;/em&gt; means&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to fall down; &lt;em&gt;rai&lt;/em&gt; means a heap of stones, the kanj&amp;lt;i 磊 is stone 石 repeated three times. Hence the overall meaning of crumble. Curiously, the word 磊磊落落 (&lt;em&gt;rairairakuraku&lt;/em&gt;) also exists; it means “openhearted; unaffected; free and easy”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original author of this poem is a Buddhist monk called Getsuan Soukou (月庵宗光), who lived 1326－1389, during the The Nanboku-chō period (南北朝時代). He used it in one of his sermons.
The poem got included in a famous treatise on Noh theatre, “A Mirror of the Flower” (Kakyō, 花鏡) by Zeami Motokiyo (世阿弥 元清) (1363–1443), who was the son of Kan’ami Kiyotsugu. Together they are considered the founders of Noh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Noh theatre is a form of classical Japanese theatre with music, poetry and dance. It is still regularly performed today, and has a similar status to opera in Western society. In Ghost in the Shell there are occasional references to Noh, in particular in “The Individual Eleven” where Hideo Kuze has a lengthy monologue about the origins of Noh and how it was cherished by the samurai class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zeami’s work “A Mirror of the Flower” deals amongst other topics with the link between marionettes and Noh theatre actors. The work &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/2384167&quot;&gt;has been translated into English (and you can read it for free)&lt;/a&gt; and I found in it a closer (and perhaps better) translation of the poem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Birth and death, goings and comings:&lt;br /&gt;
A marionette in play.&lt;br /&gt;
When one string snaps,&lt;br /&gt;
It falls and collapses.”&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The comment by Zeami is quite interesting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This [poem] exemplifies the condition of humans who act out the cycle of birth-and-death. Although the manipulation of an artificial figure upon the boards [of a puppet stage] may [make it] appear as all sorts of things, it is not really an object that moves [of its own will]. It is [the result of] the play of manipulated strings. Cut these strings and it collapses – such is the spirit [of this poem].”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also an interesting footnote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This poem appears in Gettan Osho Hogo (月庵和尚法語,’[Rinzai Zen] Priest Gettan’s Talks on Buddhist Principles’), a late 14th-century text. Zeami’s subsequent interpretation of the poem as descriptive of the relation between the actor’s mind and the ‘illusion’ of character that it creates differs from the Zen intent of
the poem, which admonishes the reader to break free from the trap of the illusory world of ‘birth-and-death’.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But considering the argument presented before the poem, what Zeami means is that as soon as the actor loses this ultimate state of awareness, the acting will collapse.
Zeami argues that when the actor achieves the ultimate state of awareness, he realizes how his mind can be used to create the illusion of reality that he presents to his audience with a detachment and skill associated with a master puppeteer. In other words, the actor on the stage is the puppet manipulated by the actor’s mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a very powerful concept, and closely related to the type of Buddhist meditation that focuses on existing in the moment. It is likely also why Noh appealed to the samurai. Within the context of Ghost in the Shell, this concept gets an extended meaning, not restricted to the mind and body of a human. Any self-aware entity controlling a humanoid form can be considered in this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is why this poem figures so prominently in the movie, but specifically in the scenes to do with the place where the robots are created (Etorofu, one of the Kuril Islands). The two main characters, Batō and Togusa, go there to interview a powerful hacker, Kim, who is obsessed with dolls and clockwork and who has transfered his own ghost into a puppet-like robot. Clearly, Kim is the one fascinated by this poem, as every appearance of it is connected to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generalizing Zeami’s view of the poem, I am inclined to interpret the strings in the poem as the connection between the robots and the mind that controls them. In a key scene, the protagonist Batō enters the factory ship where the robots are made. He is attacked by an army of robots programmed remotely to fight him.
Motoko Kusanagi hacks one of them and downloads her ghost into it, and fights on his side. She then gains control of the ship’s central computer, at which point all the robots except the one she controls collapse: their threads have been cut. This is a recurrent theme in Ghost in the Shell, for example in “Solid State Society” something very similar happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps more significant is the fact that to Batō, who clearly has missed the Major deeply since she disappeared at the end of the first movie, three years ago, immediately identifies the robot with her. As the robots on the ship are not dressed, he puts his jacket on her. And this despite the fact that the robot has no facial expression and looks identical to the others. When the Major disconnects from the robot, it also collapses. But Batō now knows that the ghost of the Major is always around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as if not to leave any doubt about the importance of the puppets in the movie, the final scene ends with a close-up of a doll held by Togusa’s daughter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/doll.png&quot; alt=&quot;Close-up of a child's doll with blond hair, blue eyes and a red hat&quot; title=&quot;Close-up of a child's doll with blond hair, blue eyes and a red hat&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Final shot of &quot;Innionce&quot;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ghost-in-the-shell-stand-alone-complex--solid-state-society-2006&quot;&gt;Ghost in the Shell: Stand Alone Complex – Solid State Society (2006)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right at the start of this third movie, there is a reference to “the Puppet Master”. The Major listens in to a conversation where the nickname is used, and comments “The Puppet Master? Not a bad name!”. Note that in Japanese the word is different from in the first movie: instead of &lt;em&gt;ningyōtsukai&lt;/em&gt; 人形遣い it is &lt;em&gt;kugutsumawashi&lt;/em&gt; 傀儡廻; &lt;em&gt;kugutsu&lt;/em&gt; is a different reading for &lt;em&gt;kairai&lt;/em&gt;, 傀儡, the word for puppet used in the poem in Innocence. The word &lt;em&gt;mawashi&lt;/em&gt;, 廻, means “to go around”, and &lt;em&gt;kugutsumawashi&lt;/em&gt; refers to wandering puppet players who went from village to village. Because of the different word choice, it is in the original Japanese version less obvious that there could be a link with the Puppet Master in the first movie.There is a however a clear link with the second movie because of the word &lt;em&gt;kugutsu&lt;/em&gt;, which is lost in the English version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As in the first movie, the initial assumption is that this Puppet Master must be some top-wizard-level hacker (超ウィザード級ハッカー); then the suspicion grows that it might be some distributed program which might have achieved some degree of self-awareness. But considering the first movie, it should come as no surprise that there is a connection with the Major.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early on we see the Major operating many different cyber bodies remotely, even several at once. At one point, she tries to control one too many and one of them collapses, and she remarks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;同時に義体を操るのは、2体迄が限界ね&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tōji ni gitai wo ayatsuru no wa, nitai made ga genkai ne&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The English subtitles say “Controlling two prosthetic bodies at the same time is apparently my limit”. The word &lt;em&gt;gitai&lt;/em&gt;,義体, is closer translated as cyber body; the word used for controlling is &lt;em&gt;ayatsuru&lt;/em&gt;,操る, exactly the word for manipulating a puppet. And there is a scene where one of the Major’s remote cyber bodies deactivates during a conversation, leading the person talking to it to comment, “Huh, that’s a puppet as well?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bonus-stills-of-the-puppet-poem-in-innocence&quot;&gt;Bonus: stills of the puppet poem in “Innocence”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first occurrence of the poem is after the parade scene:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/first-occurrence.png&quot; alt=&quot;A brick wall in tints of grey. On it, or maybe in front of it, a large stone frame with a stylised decoration, a kind of frieze reminiscent of ironmongery. This surrounds an area of about 1m x 1m on which is displayed a grid of 4x4 handwritten Chinese characters, in black ink or paint.&quot; title=&quot;A brick wall in tints of grey. On it, or maybe in front of it, a large stone frame with a stylised decoration, a kind of frieze reminiscent of ironmongery. This surrounds an area of about 1m x 1m on which is displayed a grid of 4x4 handwritten Chinese characters, in black ink or paint.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;First occurrence of the puppet poem, on a wall in the city.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also appears on the wall of Kim’s study:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/study-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;A study, executed mostly in dark purple tones. On the right a bookshelf; on the far wall a large 4x4 grid of Chinese characters written in an ancient mode. To the right at the back of the room, a person in a suit is bending over to receive a cup of tea from a small, doll-like figure in a kimono.&quot; title=&quot;A study, executed mostly in dark purple tones. On the right a bookshelf; on the far wall a large 4x4 grid of Chinese characters written in an ancient mode. To the right at the back of the room, a person in a suit is bending over to receive a cup of tea from a small, doll-like figure in a kimono.&quot; /&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/study-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;The same space, a similar angle. The person in the suit is now closer, centre-screen, carrying a white china tea cup.&quot; title=&quot;The same space, a similar angle. The person in the suit is now closer, centre-screen, carrying a white china tea cup.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Togusa in Kim's study, poem behind him&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Togusa narrowly escapes an attack on his cyberbrain :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/attack-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;A person seated in an office chair, seen from the back, with some kind of VR headset on. In front of him an explosion, he is being thrown back by the force.&quot; title=&quot;A person seated in an office chair, seen from the back, with some kind of VR headset on. In front of him an explosion, he is being thrown back by the force.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/attack-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;A person in a suit, with a kind of VR headset on his forehead so you can see his face. He is sitting on the floor, and in the air in front of him columns of Chinese characters appear.&quot; title=&quot;A person in a suit, with a kind of VR headset on his forehead so you can see his face. He is sitting on the floor, and in the air in front of him columns of Chinese characters appear.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/attack-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chinese characters in a 4x4 grid, seemingly written in pure light hanging in the air. The grid is repeated 6 times in different sized and at different angles.&quot; title=&quot;Chinese characters in a 4x4 grid, seemingly written in pure light hanging in the air. The grid is repeated 6 times in different sized and at different angles.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Poem appearing when an attack fries Kim's cyberbrain&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Batō and the Major manage to take control of the factory ship:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/factory-ship.png&quot; title=&quot;A grid of 4x4 Chinese characters in blood red paint, probably about 1m x 1m.  They appear on a heavy door, about 2m high and 3m wide, which seems to have been originally painted with diagonal yellow and black warning stripes, then overpainted with a grey rectangle on which are on the left the faded letters R11 and on the right a black square with a white border and some smaller white squares and rectangles inside it. There is also what looks like a kind of pasted notice, pale orange paper with black Chinese characters, about 30cm wide and 60cm high. The red Chinese characters are painted by hand on top of all that. The right side of the scene is illuminated, the left side is in shadows.&quot; alt=&quot;A grid of 4x4 Chinese characters in blood red paint, probably about 1m x 1m.  They appear on a heavy door, about 2m high and 3m wide, which seems to have been originally painted with diagonal yellow and black warning stripes, then overpainted with a grey rectangle on which are on the left the faded letters R11 and on the right a black square with a white border and some smaller white squares and rectangles inside it. There is also what looks like a kind of pasted notice, pale orange paper with black Chinese characters, about 30cm wide and 60cm high. The red Chinese characters are painted by hand on top of all that. The right side of the scene is illuminated, the left side is in shadows.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Final appearance of the poem, in the factory ship&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ekphrasisjournal.ro/index.php?p=artc&amp;amp;id=861&quot;&gt;Free: Filimon, Luiza Maria. “Dolls, Offsprings, and Automata. Analyzing the Posthuman Experience in &lt;em&gt;Ghost in the Shell 2: Innocence&lt;/em&gt;.” Ekphrasis. Images, Cinema, Theory, Media 17.1 (2017): 45-66.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/book/10.1057/9780230110069&quot;&gt;Not free: Brown, Steven T. “Tokyo cyberpunk: Posthumanism in Japanese visual culture.”, Springer, 2016.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Drawing the Naginata Hoko</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/naginata-hoko-kitsune/"/>
        <updated>2020-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/naginata-hoko-kitsune</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/naginata-hoko-kitsune_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;I have &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/ran-ryou-ou/&quot;&gt;written earlier&lt;/a&gt; about a drawing I made of a dancer at the Gion Matsuri in Kyoto. I made another drawing, this time based on a pictures I took of musicians on a festival float. I’d like to share the background to and the making of the drawing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-gion-matsuri&quot;&gt;The Gion Matsuri&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gion Matsuri (祇園祭) is Kyoto’s most famous festival, held at the start of summer.  The festival itself can be dated back all the way to the Heian era, around 870.  It originated as a ritual for purification and pacification of evil spirits causing summer diseases and was at first connected with the Shintō deity of the Gion Shrine (Yasaka Shrine).
The festival has been held annually since 970. As early as the late 10th century two types of floats were paraded through the streets accompanied by musicians, dancers, and actors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Edo period (1600 to 1868) the matsuri became a way in which merchants could show off their wealth as well as their international outlook. In that period, the decoration of the floats became more detailed and luxurious and many started incorporating foreign artwork. In particular cotton merchants were among the parishioners of the Gion Shrine, so that textiles have always formed an important part of the festival decoration. The floats currently used in the parade mostly date from the end of the Edo era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-yamaboko-float-parade&quot;&gt;The Yamaboko float parade&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the morning of 17 July there is a parade (&lt;em&gt;junkō&lt;/em&gt;, 巡行) of festival floats through the streets of the city. There are two float types, &lt;em&gt;yama&lt;/em&gt; (山, meaning “mountain” but also “festival float”) and &lt;em&gt;hoko&lt;/em&gt; (鉾, meaning both “festival float” and “halberd”), hence the name &lt;em&gt;yamaboko junkō&lt;/em&gt; (山鉾巡行).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-koi-yama&quot;&gt;The Koi Yama&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;yama&lt;/em&gt; is a rectangular box containing an artificial mountain crowned by a tree, usually a pine. Textiles decorate the four sides. This type of float is carried through the streets on the shoulders of young men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to mention one of these &lt;em&gt;yama&lt;/em&gt; in particular, although it has nothing to do with my drawing. The &lt;em&gt;koi yama&lt;/em&gt; (鯉山, “carp float”) features a huge carp swimming upstream towards the sky. This refers to the Chinese legend about a carp who desired to become a dragon and had to go through many trials to reach the Dragon Gate Waterfall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is particularly interesting about the Koi Yama float are the decorations: they consist of parts of an authentic 16th-century Flemish tapestry depicting scenes of the Trojan War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was quite a surprise to me to find a Flemish tapestry decorating a festival float in Kyoto. So I wanted to find out more, and this is the story:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 16th century, Flemish tapestries were luxury items coveted throughout Europe, and common as diplomatic gifts. The Japanese nobles were particularly interested in images of warriors [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/3050146&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Koi Yama tapestry was part of a set of six created by the atelier of the Flemish weaver Nicaise Aerts in Brussels in the 1590s, probably based on cartoons by the famous Michel Coxie. There are different theories of how they came to Japan.
The could have been brought to Japan by the Portuguese on request of the Jesuits around 1605 [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/3050146&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;] as a gift to the first Tokugawa shōgun Ieyasu, or by the Netherlands East India Company (Vereenigde Oostindische Compagnie; VOC) in 1633 [&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iassrt.org/detail/symposium/154.html&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;], as a diplomatic gift to the third Tokugawa shōgun Iemitsu. Or maybe they could have been gifts from Pope Paolo V to daimyō Date Masamune’s diplomatic/trade mission to Europe, and entered Japan as contraband just as the Tokugawa shōgun closed Japan to limit foreign influence (in 1633) [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gionfestival.org/koi-yama/&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, when the power moved from the shōguns to the merchant classes, the tapestries were sold on. One was lost early on and one during a fire in 1909, but the other four, though mostly cut up, still survive. Around 1800,  one of them was acquired to serve as decoration for the Koi Yama, and cut into nine pieces using “a carpenter’s chisel” (&lt;em&gt;daiku no nomi&lt;/em&gt;, 大工のノミ) [&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.koiyama.com/index2.html&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is some dispute as to the scenes depicted on the Koi Yama tapestries, as indeed on the other tapestries in the set: some scholars say they are from the Illiad, and show King Priam and Queen Hecuba [&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.koiyama.com/index2.html&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;]; others say the set is based on the Aeneid and that the Koi Yama tapestry shows the Roman emperor Augustus, the descendant of Aeneas [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/3050146&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iassrt.org/detail/symposium/154.html&quot;&gt;[1] &lt;em&gt;Tapestries Brought to Japan through the Maritime Silk Road and Their Influence&lt;/em&gt;, Masako Yoshida, Professor, Kyoto City University of Arts, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.koiyama.com/index2.html&quot;&gt;[2] (Koi Yama official web site) 鯉山町衆, 公益財団法人鯉山保存会, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/3050146&quot;&gt;[3] &lt;em&gt;Sixteenth-Century European Tapestries in Tokugawa Japan&lt;/em&gt;, Grace A. H. Vlam, The Art Bulletin Vol. 63, No. 3 (Sep., 1981), pp. 476-495&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gionfestival.org/koi-yama/&quot;&gt;[4] &lt;em&gt;Koi Yama 鯉山 The Carp That Became A Dragon&lt;/em&gt;, C. Pawasarat, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-naginata-hoko&quot;&gt;The Naginata Hoko&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;hoko&lt;/em&gt; is a tall, rectangular tower with a steepled roof, placed on huge wooden wheels. Underneath the roof there is room for musicians and actors, or dolls representing heroes and heroines from the legendary or historical past. All four sides of the tower are hung with textiles. This type of float is pulled through the streets by teams of thirty to forty men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 32 floats in the Yamaboko Junko, and each year their order is decided by lots drawn officially by the Mayor of Kyoto, except for one: the Naginata Hoko (長刀鉾) always leads the procession. The name comes from the &lt;em&gt;naginata&lt;/em&gt;, a long sword or halberd, that decorates its central pole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legendary Heian swordsmith &lt;a href=&quot;https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E4%B8%89%E6%9D%A1%E5%AE%97%E8%BF%91&quot;&gt;Sanjō Munechika (Sanjō no Kokaji)&lt;/a&gt; crafted the original halberd sword in the 10th century. The halberd is said to have the power to exorcise the evil spirits which cause epidemics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was at the &lt;em&gt;yoiyama&lt;/em&gt; (宵山, the day before the parade) in 2012 I took a few pictures of musicians in a &lt;em&gt;hoko&lt;/em&gt;, and it was only when I decided to make a drawing based on it that I realised this is not just a float, but the famous Naginata Hoko. There is a lot more to be said about this particular float, I have provided some links below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;kitsune-masks-and-yukata&quot;&gt;Kitsune masks and yukata&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to give the characters in the drawing fox masks to make the scene more distinct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fox masks (&lt;em&gt;kitsune men&lt;/em&gt;, 狐面) have a long tradition in Japan. In Shinto, the fox is a messenger of the god (&lt;em&gt;kami&lt;/em&gt;, 神) Inari, who is the protector of rice, agriculture, and fertility. The gods themselves can take on fox shapes. The mask are use in Noh, Shinto music and dance (&lt;em&gt;kagura&lt;/em&gt;, 神楽) and &lt;em&gt;kabuki&lt;/em&gt; performances and worn at many festivals – and of course &lt;a href=&quot;https://hooktube.com/watch?v=cK3NMZAUKGw&quot;&gt;by Babymetal’s Kami band&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was particularly inspired by the mask worn by the character Gin in the wonderful anime &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hotarubi.info/gallery/tr05.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hotarubi no Mori e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (蛍火の杜へ, “To the Forest of the Light of the Fireflies”), but I researched other mask variants as well, in particular because the musicians have to wear half-masks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The musicians in my drawing wear the same summer kimonos (&lt;em&gt;yukata&lt;/em&gt;) as in the picture, save a few minor details, but for the other characters I used different patterns based on other pictures I took.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-drawing&quot;&gt;The drawing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/gion-matsuri-float-musicians-fin-1280px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;the drawing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;!-- add a caption --&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The finished drawing&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/ran-ryou-ou/&quot;&gt;Ranryōō dancer drawing&lt;/a&gt;, I wanted a drawing with bright colours and a lot of detail, and the float has really abundant detail and colour. It is quite amazing how every part of the surface has some detailed decoration. I think I now appreciate the float a lot more because to draw it I had to study every little detail in the picture. I also like to have human figures in my drawings. I think the fox masks make the scene more interesting than the original picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper for this drawing is Fabriano Artistico 56cm x 76cm 300g/m2 “rough” watercolour paper. It’s a really nice paper with a very pronounced grain. As usual I did not tape it on a board but it only buckled a little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used mainly Derwent Inktense, which do give quite deep colours, but also Conté Aquarelle and Faber-Castell Graphite Aquarelle pencils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual I started the drawing with a ghost drawing in pencil. Because of the size of the drawing, I used a grid to make sure the figure was positioned correctly. The focus of detail is on the characters and in particular the masks, the further away from these the more sketchy and impressionistic I treated the drawing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/gion-matsuri-float-musicians-pencil-1280px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;the drawing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Pencil ghost drawing&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/gion-matsuri-float-musicians-pencil-detail-1280px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;the drawing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Pencil ghost drawing detail, start of colouring&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I added detail and colour with the watercolour pencils. The float has a lot of gold and silver on the hangings, and these are very difficult to render in colour pencil. The level of details is such that to really reproduce it would require very smooth paper and very fine brushes. I picked the coarse paper on purpose and the pencils are not particularly sharp. This forces me to abstract a lot of the detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/gion-matsuri-float-musicians-colour-pencil-detail-1280px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;the drawing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;First layer of detail and colour&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I did some separate sketches for the non-musician characters, because they are to my mind very important in this drawing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/gion-matsuri-float-musicians-sep-detail-1280px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;the drawing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Separate drawing of non-musician characters&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left the characters until the end and washed the watercolours starting from the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/gion-matsuri-float-musicians-almost-finished-1280px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;the drawing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Partially washed drawing&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally I did the characters. The eyes on the masks are the only places where I used a very fine brush, because a tiny change in the shape can make a big change in expression. Then I did another pass of the entire drawing. I darkened the background behind the characters and the ceiling to have more contrast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To finish the drawing I added a description in Japanese:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;狐 長 祇&lt;br /&gt;
  の 刀 園&lt;br /&gt;
  面 鉾 祭&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which reads &lt;em&gt;Gion matsuri naginata hoko kitsune no men&lt;/em&gt; and means “Gion festival / Halberd float / Fox masks”. The “の” is not really required but I wanted the characters to form a 3x3 grid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.discoverkyoto.com/event-calendar/july/gion-festival-yasaka-shrine-downtown/&quot;&gt;Discover Kyoto page on the Gion festival&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gionfestival.org/yamaboko-floats/saki-matsuri/naginata-boko/&quot;&gt;Offical Gion festival page on the naginata hoko&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gionmatsuri.or.jp/yamahoko/naginatahoko.html&quot;&gt;Offical Gion matsuri page on the naginata hoko (Japanese and English)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://eng.trip.kyoto.jp/spot/db/nikenchaya-nakamurarou/&quot;&gt;A page on the role of a chigo ritual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.city.kyoto.lg.jp/shimogyo/page/0000011341.html&quot;&gt;Offical Kyoto City page on the yamaboko (in Japanese)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.city.kyoto.lg.jp/shimogyo/page/0000011773.html&quot;&gt;Offical Kyoto City page on the naginata hoko (in Japanese)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!--
_nomi_, written in the text in katakana, has the wonderfully complex _kanji_ 鑿
--&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Kale Potatoes Tofu Skins</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/kale-potatoes-tofu-skins/"/>
        <updated>2020-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/kale-potatoes-tofu-skins</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	
        	200 g kale
400 g potatoes
60 g dried tofu skins
1 tablespoon sunflower seeds
2 tablespoons sesame seeds
2 dried tomatoes
1 tablespoons tomato puree
1/2 teaspoon tobanjan
1 teaspoon ground cumin
1 clove garlic
1 cm ginger
sesame seed oil, rapeseed oil
1 tablespoon soy sauce

wash the kale and squeeze forcefully, repeat a few times
soak the dried tofu skins in boiling hot water for at least 20 mins
soak the dried tomatoes  in boiling hot water for at least 20 mins

Drain the tofu skins and cut into strips
Cut the potatoes in quite small chunks and cook them in the microwave for 10 minutes at 900W
Drain the cooking liquid into a small bowl


Fry the garlic, ginger, cumin and seeds for a few minutes over medium heat. 
Add the kale and fry over high heat until it just starts to wilt
Add the cut tofu skins to the pan and fry for a few minutes more.
Add the potatoes to the pan and fry for a few minutes more until the start to brown. 
Turn down the heat.

Add the tomato puree, tobanjan and soy sauce to the cooking liquid of the potatoes. Stir until it's smooth, then add to the pan and stir in.
        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Okra with tomatoes and tofu sticks</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/okra-tomatoes-tofu-sticks/"/>
        <updated>2019-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/okra-tomatoes-tofu-sticks</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/okra-tomatoes-tofu-sticks_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;This recipe is inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kawalingpinoy.com/curried-okra-with-tomatoes/&quot;&gt;Curried okra with tomatoes&lt;/a&gt; from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kawalingpinoy.com&quot;&gt;Kawaling Pinoy&lt;/a&gt; Filipino recipe site.
I added &lt;a href=&quot;https://shop.waiyeehong.com/food-ingredients/dried-products/dried-beancurd-seaweed/dried-beancurd-sticks-tofu-bamboo-2?language=tw&quot;&gt;tofu (bean curd) sticks&lt;/a&gt; and used more tomatoes; also the spices are a bit different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes a bit longer because I used Japanese short-grained brown rice (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.japancentre.com/en/products/3274-yumenishiki-brown-rice&quot;&gt;Yumenishiki Brown Rice&lt;/a&gt;, grown in Italy) and that takes longer to cook than white rice. The actual preparation time is about 20 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegan&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#gluten-free&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;gluten-free&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#45-minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;45-minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;575 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#400-600kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_2.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fresh ingredients &amp;amp; groceries
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;300g fresh or frozen okra (I could only find frozen)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 large tomatoes, chopped&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;50 g dried tofu sticks&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 cm fresh ginger, finely chopped&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 cloves garlic, peeled and finely chopped&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/2 cup water&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From the store cupboard
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cup of rice (I used brown Japanese rice)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons sesame seeds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon ground turmeric&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon ground coriander&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon ground cumin&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/4 teaspoon &lt;em&gt;tobanjan&lt;/em&gt; (or a pinch of chilli powder)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt; paste&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon &lt;em&gt;yuzu&lt;/em&gt; juice (you can use lemon, lime or even vinegar as substitute)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon rapeseed oil or other cooking oil&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soak the tofu sticks in very hot water for 30 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meanwhile
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cook the rice (as it is wholegrain rice, it takes rather long, up to 45 minutes)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cook the okra 6 minutes (4 minutes for fresh okra) in the microwave at full power (900W), stir every 2 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Heat the oil in a deep pan. When the oil is hot, add the ginger, garlic, sesame seeds and spices and fry for a few minutes over medium heat.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Drain the tofu sticks and cut them into pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the tofu sticks to the pan and cook until lightly browned.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the tomatoes, okra, &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;tobanjan&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;yuzu&lt;/em&gt; juice and cook, stirring occasionally, for a few minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the water and let it simmer for another 10 minutes or so.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Serve with the rice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Greek-style green beans in tomato sauce with feta and rice</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/fasolakia-ladera/"/>
        <updated>2019-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/fasolakia-ladera</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/fasolakia-ladera_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;In October I went on a research retreat in Greece. The food was delicious. Celeste from Artisa, who runs the retreat, is an excellent cook and by popular demand she &lt;a href=&quot;https://artisagreece.org/artisa-food-cookbook-with-delicious-vegetarian-meals/&quot;&gt;published a cookbook&lt;/a&gt;. This recipe is my adaptation of Celeste’s recipe for “Fasolakia ladera” (Φασολάκια λαδερά), green beans in tomato sauce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegetarian&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegetarian&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#45-minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;45-minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;750 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#600-800kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_3.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fresh ingredients &amp;amp; groceries
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;375 g green beans (I used stringless runner beans)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;4 small potatoes (150 g)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 cm ginger, finely chopped&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 large beef tomatoes (300 g)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;half a cup of fresh mint leaves&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From the store cupboard
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cup rice (I used Basmati)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;4 tablespoons tomato puree&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon sugar&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon pine kernels&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon garlic oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;4 tablespoons olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;salt and pepper to taste (I added 1/4 teaspoon salt, and sprinkled some pepper on serving)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wash the tomatoes, chop them fine and cook them in a large pot in the microwave for 5 minutes at full power (900W). Stir and cook for another 5 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meanwhile,
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cook the rice (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/basics/#toc0&quot;&gt;“The Basics”&lt;/a&gt; for how to cook rice).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wash and clean the beans and break them in two or three pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wash the potatoes and cut them in 4 pieces (no need to peel them).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Heat the olive oil and garlic oil in a large deep pan and stir-fry the ginger and beans for about 5 minutes over high heat.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the pine kernels at the end and fry for another minute or so until they start to brown. Take care as they burn very easily.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the content of the pan to the pot with the tomatoes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the potatoes, the tomato puree and the sugar.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cook in the microwave for 5 minutes at full power (900W).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add the fresh mint leaves.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cook in the microwave for a further 5 minutes at full power (900W), and then 5 minutes are reduced power (300 W).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leave the dish for a few minutes before serving.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cut the feta in thick slices, season with olive oil and oregano.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Serve with the feta and rice and season with pepper to taste.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Ghost in the Shell and the Manyoshi</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/ghost-in-the-shell-manyoshi/"/>
        <updated>2019-10-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/ghost-in-the-shell-manyoshi</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/ghost-in-the-shell-manyoshi_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;The first “Ghost in the Shell” anime has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ebkGo-nUPhk&quot;&gt;a very striking opening theme&lt;/a&gt;. It was expanded for the second movie, “Innocence”. I was in particular intrigued by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WOEEfPpSAZ8&quot;&gt;the “Puppet Song”&lt;/a&gt; in Innocence, and tried to unwrap the many layers behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ghost-in-the-shell&quot;&gt;Ghost in the Shell&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1995, the first “Ghost in the Shell” anime was released, based on the 1991 manga &lt;em&gt;koukaku kidoutai&lt;/em&gt; (攻殻機動隊, “mobile armoured riot police”) by Shirō Masamune. It’s a cyberpunk, near-future science fiction anime about cyborgs and to my mind it deals with the question of what makes a human human. It is one of my favourite anime, and one of the reasons for this is the score by Kenji Kawai. In particular, the film has a very striking opening theme sung by a choir, “謡I - Making of Cyborg”. The character 謡 (&lt;em&gt;uta&lt;/em&gt;) indicates that the song is a traditional folk ballad or chant, otherwise the more common character for “song”  歌 (also &lt;em&gt;uta&lt;/em&gt;) would be used. There are three of these chants in the movie, but I want to focus on the first one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;making-of-cyborg&quot;&gt;Making of Cyborg&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=z64HCi2rQkE&quot;&gt;listening to this song&lt;/a&gt;, what struck me is that it sounds similar to the choral songs of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AFgzzWT3zX4&quot;&gt;“Le Mystère des Voix Bulgares”&lt;/a&gt;, which was the name of a 1975 recording of Bulgarian folk songs performed by the Bulgarian State Radio &amp;amp; Television Female Vocal Choir. It only became widely known after being re-released by the British independent record label 4AD in 1986.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, this is not a coincidence: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gamesetwatch.com/2010/02/sound_current_kenji_kawai_the.php&quot;&gt;in an interview&lt;/a&gt;, the composer explained he had wanted a chorus in Bulgarian style but using Japanese folk singers. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%82%A4%E3%83%8E%E3%82%BB%E3%83%B3%E3%82%B9&quot;&gt;the Japanese Wiki&lt;/a&gt;, he used only three singers for the recording. The result is a very interesting combination of a traditional Bulgarian mode with Japanese lyrics and singing style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is also very interesting is the nature of the song: it is intended to be similar to a traditional Japanese wedding song, but as far as I could gather the composer wrote the lyrics. He used a very archaic style, dating back to the Heian period (794 to 1185, when Kyoto became the capital) or even the earlier Nara period (710 to 794, when Nara was the capital).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original lyrics are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;吾が舞へば&lt;br /&gt;
麗し女　酔ひにけり&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;吾が舞へば　&lt;br /&gt;
照る月　響むなり&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;結婚に　神降りて&lt;br /&gt;
夜は明け　鵺鳥　鳴く&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt; this reads:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;あがまへば&lt;br /&gt;
くわしめ　よひにけり&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;あがまへば&lt;br /&gt;
てるつき　とよむなり&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;よばいに　かみあまくだりて&lt;br /&gt;
よはあけ　ぬえとりなく&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in &lt;em&gt;romaji&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;agamaeba&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;kuwashime yoinikeri&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;agamaeba&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;terutsuki toyomunari&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;yobai ni amakudarite&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;yo wa ake nuetori naku&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I based my translation on &lt;a href=&quot;https://ameblo.jp/mazdafamilia2010/entry-11170063067.html&quot;&gt;a modern Japanese version&lt;/a&gt; of the archaic Japanese:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;私が舞うと　
美しい女が酔った&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;私が舞うと　
照る月が　鳴り響く&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;結婚するために　神が天から　降りてきて
夜が明けて　鵺鳥が　鳴く&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My translation is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As I dance, the beautiful woman is enchanted&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;As I dance, the shining moon reverberates&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The god descends from heaven to get married&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The night turns into day and the thrush cries&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last words in the song quite dramatically change the atmosphere because of the negative connotations of the cry of the &lt;em&gt;nue&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few notes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“to get married”: the word used in the song is &lt;em&gt;yobai ni&lt;/em&gt;, where &lt;em&gt;yo&lt;/em&gt; (夜) means “night” and &lt;em&gt;bai&lt;/em&gt; (這い) “to crawl”. In the Heian era, a nobleman sneaking into a lady’s bedroom at night constituted a marriage proposal. There are many examples in the famous novel &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Tale_of_Genji&quot;&gt;The Tale of Genji&lt;/a&gt;. The lyrics in kanji above have “結婚に” (&lt;em&gt;kekkon ni&lt;/em&gt;)  which means to get married.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“The thrush cries”: the specific bird is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White's_thrush&quot;&gt;White’s Thrush&lt;/a&gt;. Nowadays, 鵺 &lt;em&gt;nue&lt;/em&gt; also refers to a mythological creature, a Japanese version of the chimaera, but that was not the case in the Heian era. Nevertheless, the cry of this bird is an ill omen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;innocence&quot;&gt;Innocence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2004, the second Ghost in the Shell anime, “Innocence”, was released, with the same director (Mamoru Oshii) and continuing the themes from the first movie but with a much more explicit exploration of the philosophical themes through quotes and imagery. Also there are more pronounced archaic elements, for example sometimes the characters use archaic Japanese, and of course there is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HtxRCwZH-OA&quot;&gt;the famous parade scene&lt;/a&gt;. I think this anime is a masterpiece. But my focus is again only on the opening theme song, the Puppet Song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-puppet-song-i&quot;&gt;The Puppet Song (I)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full title of the song is &lt;em&gt;kugutsu-uta: uramite chiru&lt;/em&gt; (傀儡謡「怨恨みて 散る」, くぐつうた「うらみてちる」) which means “Puppet song: The flowers resentfully fall” (the word “flowers” is not present in the title but implicit from the lyrics). A translation I found in many places is “The flowers grieve and fall” but 怨恨 is not grief but resentment, even hate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The song is in the same choral mode as “Making of Cyborg”. The harmony and delivery are also quite similar but the melody is distinctly different. Musically, another notable difference is that the composer expanded the choir from three singers to 75. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LqGq2QgDQR8&quot;&gt;live performance of this song with the full choir&lt;/a&gt; is very impressive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lyrics are written in a similar archaic style, but they are longer and a lot less straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original lyrics are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;一日一夜に　&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.asahi-net.or.jp/~sg2h-ymst/yamatouta/sennin/kawati_t.html&quot;&gt;月は照らずとも&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
悲傷しみに　鵺鳥　鳴く&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://manapedia.jp/text/1659&quot;&gt;吾がかへり 見すれど&lt;/a&gt;　&lt;a href=&quot;https://art-tags.net/manyo/five/m0798.html&quot;&gt;花は散りぬべし&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://manyou.plabot.michikusa.jp/manyousyu5_898.html&quot;&gt;慰むる　心は&lt;/a&gt;　&lt;a href=&quot;https://art-tags.net/manyo/twelve/m3039.html&quot;&gt;消ぬるがごとく&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;新世に　神集いて&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://art-tags.net/manyo/fifteen/m3598.html&quot;&gt;夜は明け&lt;/a&gt;　鵺鳥　鳴く&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;咲く花は　&lt;a href=&quot;http://k-amc.kokugakuin.ac.jp/DM/detail.do?class_name=col_dsg&amp;amp;data_id=68283&quot;&gt;神に祈ひ祷む&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://manyou.plabot.michikusa.jp/manyousyu4_746.html&quot;&gt;生ける世に&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://manapedia.jp/text/2077&quot;&gt;吾が身悲しも&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
夢は 消ぬ&lt;br /&gt;
怨恨みて&lt;br /&gt;
散る&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt; this reads:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ひとひひとよに　つきはてらずとも&lt;br /&gt;
かなしみに　ぬえとり　なく&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;あがかへり　みすれど　はなはちりぬべし&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;なぐさむる　こころは　けぬるがごとく&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;あらたよに　かむつどいて&lt;br /&gt;
よはあけ　ぬえとりなく&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;さくはなは　かみにこひのむ&lt;br /&gt;
いけるよに&lt;br /&gt;
わがみかなしも　&lt;br /&gt;
いめは　けぬ&lt;br /&gt;
うらみて&lt;br /&gt;
ちる&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in &lt;em&gt;romaji&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;hitohi hitoyo ni tsuki wa terazu to mo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;kanashimi ni nuetori naku&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;agakaeri misuredo hana wa chirinubeshi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;nagusamuru kokoro wa kenuru ga godoku&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;arata yo ni kamu tsudoite&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;yo wa ake nuetori naku&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;sakuhana wa kami ni kohinomu&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;ikeru yo ni&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;wa ga mi kanashi mo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;ime wa kenu&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;uramite&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;chiru&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I tried to read and understand this text, I got stuck on almost every single line. I was quite surprised to find that almost all the parts that I did not understand occur in the Manyōshū.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-manyōshū&quot;&gt;The Manyōshū&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Manyōshū&lt;/em&gt; (万葉集), literally “Collection of Myriad Leaves”, is the oldest existing collection of poetry in classical Japanese, compiled during the Nara period. It is extremely highly regarded, for example the name of the current era, 令和 (&lt;em&gt;reiwa&lt;/em&gt;) &lt;a href=&quot;https://japan-forward.com/manyoshu-know-the-poetry-collection-where-japans-new-era-name-comes-from/&quot;&gt;was inspired by one of its poems&lt;/a&gt;. It has been studied by scholars for a very long time, and therefore it is possible to find explanations and translations of the poems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-puppet-song-ii&quot;&gt;The Puppet Song (II)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the original lyrics of the Puppet Song above, each linked phrase occurs in a poem from the &lt;em&gt;Manyōshū&lt;/em&gt; collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s quite remarkable that the lyrics of the theme song of a cyberpunk science fiction anime are so strongly inspired by 7th-century classical Japanese poetry. I am also intrigued how the composer could write in such an archaic style, which I assume only very few people master today. And of course this explains why I did not understand so many of the lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, thanks to the Manyōshū scholars and a number of existing translations, it was possible for me to put together a translation of the song that I’m happy with, although whether it is correct or not is certainly debatable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Every day, every night,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;even if the moon does not shine,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;the thrush cries in sadness&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I turned and looked back,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;but the flowers had already scattered;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;all consolation disappeared from my heart&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The gods leave to gather in the new world&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As night turns into day, the thrush cries&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Although in this living world&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;we ourselves become sad,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;at least may our dreams never vanish!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;the blossoms beseech the gods, as they resentfully fall&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few notes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“even if the moon does not shine”: this is my interpretation of とも.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“As night turns into day, the thrush cries”: this is a literal quote from the Wedding Song from Ghost in the Shell.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“all consolation disappeared from my heart”: this is a bit free, more literally would be “my comforted heart vanishes irrevocably”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“does not shine” and “never vanish”: 照らず and 消ぬ are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kokugobunpou.com/%E5%8A%A9%E5%8B%95%E8%A9%9E/%E3%81%AA%E3%81%84-%E3%81%AC-%E3%82%93/&quot;&gt;archaic grammar constructions still in current use (&lt;em&gt;-zu&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;-nu&lt;/em&gt; endings)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“the blossoms beseech the gods”: the verb used is &lt;em&gt;kohinomu&lt;/em&gt; (to pray), and  &lt;a href=&quot;http://k-amc.kokugakuin.ac.jp/DM/detail.do?class_name=col_dsg&amp;amp;data_id=68283&quot;&gt;as this scholar explains &lt;/a&gt;, it means “to earnestly pray to the gods (for happiness)”. So “beseech” seems more apt than just “pray”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>A shop, the planets and the days of the week</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/suikin-planets-weekdays/"/>
        <updated>2019-09-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/suikin-planets-weekdays</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/suikin-planets-weekdays_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;In Tokyo there is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hpfrance.com/Shop/Brand/suikin.html&quot;&gt;a shop called &lt;em&gt;Sui Kin Chi Ka Moku Do Ten Mei Kai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, written 水金地火木土天冥海. At first glance this seems a very long, hard to pronounce and difficult to remember name, so why name a shop like that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-names-of-the-planets-in-the-solar-system&quot;&gt;The names of the planets in the solar system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The explanation is that the name refers to a mnemonic for the planets in the solar system: each &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; in the name of the shop is the first kanji of the name of a planet, starting from the one closest to the sun. So most Japanese people will recognise and remember the name. And because in Japanese everything gets abbreviated if at all possible, in practice everyone calls the shop “Suikin”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One oddity about the name is that most people will in school have learned the sequence &lt;em&gt;Sui Kin Chi Ka Moku Do Ten Kai Mei&lt;/em&gt; ( 水金地火木土天海冥), so the last two names are swapped. This is because when the shop was founded (in 1984), Pluto (冥王星, &lt;em&gt;meiōsei&lt;/em&gt;) was closer to the earth than Neptune (海王星, &lt;em&gt;kaiōsei&lt;/em&gt;), but because of Pluto’s strongly elliptical orbit, this is only the case for two periods of about 20 years in the total of 248 year it takes to complete one orbit around the Sun. The last time this happened was between 1979 and 1999, and it won’t happen again until 2227.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What puzzled me is the connection between the order of the planets and the order of the days of the week in Japanese. The names of the planets are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;English name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Japanese name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Reading&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Meaning&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mercurius&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;水星&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;suisei&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Water Star&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Venus&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;金星&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;kinsei&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Metal Star&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Earth&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;地球&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;chikyuu&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Terrestrial Globe)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mars&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;火星&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;kasei&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Fire star&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Jupiter&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;木星&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;mokusei&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Wood star&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Saturn&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;土星&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;dosei&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Earth star&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Uranus&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;天王星&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;ten-ōsei&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;King of Heaven’s Star&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Neptune&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;海王星&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;kai-ōsei&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;King of the Sea’s Star&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Pluto&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;冥王星&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;mei-ōsei&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;King of the Dark’s Star&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 1. Names of the planets in English and Japanese&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The suffix &lt;em&gt;-sei&lt;/em&gt; (星) actually means “star”. The names of the last three planets are Japanese descriptions of the roles of the gods Uranus, Neptune and Pluto. The other five planets are named after the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Five_elements_(China)&quot;&gt;Five Elements (五大, &lt;em&gt;godai&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; used in Chinese philosophy: water (水), metal (金), fire (火), wood (木), and earth in the sense of soil (土).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The days of the week are listed in Table 2. The suffix &lt;em&gt;-yōbi&lt;/em&gt; (曜日) means “weekday”. I’ve added the names used in the Roman calendar for comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Day&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Japanese&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Reading&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Roman name&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sunday&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;日曜日&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;nichiyōbi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sun-day&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Monday&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;月曜日&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;getsuyōbi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Moon-day&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tuesday&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;火曜日&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;kayōbi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mars-day&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Wednesday&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;水曜日&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;suiyōbi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mercury-day&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thursday&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;木曜日&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;mokuyōbi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Jupiter-day&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Friday&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;金曜日&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;kinyōbi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Venus-day&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Saturday&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;土曜日&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;doyōbi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Saturn-day&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 2. Names of the days of the week in English and Japanese and their Roman name&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-order-of-the-days-of-the-week&quot;&gt;The order of the days of the week&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I found intriguing is that the days of the week occur in the same order in our calendar and in the Japanese calendar. My first assumption was that the Japanese simply borrowed the Western convention after contact with the West, which would have been in the 16th century at the earliest, but it turns out that this is not the case: the adoption of a 7-day week and the naming of the weekdays was introduced in China in the 4th century (from either  ancient Mesopotamia or Egypt, and likely via Greece) and from there in Japan in the 9th century. I found the answer on the website of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sendai-astro.jp/observation/blog/2016/01/qa025.html&quot;&gt;Sendai Astronomical Observatory (&lt;em&gt;Sendaishi Tenmondai&lt;/em&gt;, 仙台市天文台)&lt;/a&gt;. What follows is a rewording of that explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In ancient times, people read the time and season from the stars in the night sky. They discovered that five of these “stars” were moving in a strange way, overtaking each other and sometimes appearing to move backwards. They called these &lt;em&gt;wakusei&lt;/em&gt; (惑星), literally “perplexing stars”. These are the five planets Mercury, Venus, Mars, Jupiter and Saturn that can be seen with the naked eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ancients thought that planets, the sun and the moon were turning around the earth. As a result of their observations they thought the moon was closest to the earth followed by Mercury, Venus, the Sun, Mars, Jupiter, and Saturn:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;月&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;水&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;金&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;日&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;火&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;木&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;土&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Moon&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mercury&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Venus&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sun&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mars&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Jupiter&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Saturn&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the belief was that the sun, the moon, and the five planets were “star gods”  (星の神, &lt;em&gt;hoshi no kami&lt;/em&gt;) who dominated time and space. And the astronomers observed the moon cycle of 28 days, which was split into four 7-day units, with one day dedicated to each star god. This was the basis for the notion of the ​”week”. The division of the day into 24 hours had already evolved based on the concept of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.japantimes.co.jp/community/2011/10/22/our-lives/telling-time-with-animals/&quot;&gt;twelve constellations of the zodiac&lt;/a&gt;. Each hour was believed to be controlled by a specific star god, and each day was believed to be dominated by the specific star god controlling the first hour of that day. And the order in which the star gods were assigned to the hours and days was based on the order in which the “stars” were observed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we start on the first hour of the first day with Saturn, the planet furthest away from the earth, this is Saturn’s day (土曜日). Each hour we move to the next closer planet in the geocentric model: Jupiter, Mars, the Sun,Venus, Mercury and the Moon, and we repeat this process, so after the Moon we start again with Saturn. Doing so, after 24 hours, we arrive at the Sun (日曜日), and 24 hours after that, the Moon (月曜日), then Mars (火曜日), Mercury (水曜日), Jupiter (木曜日), Venus (金曜日),   and after one week, this pattern repeats itself and we’re back at Saturn:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Hour in the day&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Day&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;１　２　３　４　５　６　７　８　９　…　２４&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Saturn’s day&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;土　木　火　日　金　水　月　土　木　…　火&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sun’s day&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;日　金　水　月　土　木　火　日　金　…　水&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Moon’s day&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;月　土　木　火　日　金　水　月　土　…　木&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mars’ day&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;火　日　金　水　月　土　木　火　日　…　金&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mercury’s day&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;水　月　土　木　火　日　金　水　月　…　土&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Jupiter’s day&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;木　火　日　金　水　月　土　木　火　…　日&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Venus’ day&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;金　水　月　土　木　火　日　金　水　…　月&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Saturn’s day&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;土　木　火　日　金　水　月　土　木　…　火&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how the ancient astronomers in Mesopotamia or Egypt related the days of the week to the planets, and from there it was adopted in ancient Greece and Rome but also in ancient China and Japan. To my mind it’s really quite amazing to learn that the order of the days of the week relates in this way to the ordering of the “stars” in the geocentric model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bonus-track&quot;&gt;Bonus track&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a small &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.haskell.org/&quot;&gt;Haskell&lt;/a&gt; program that creates the week day sequences from the sequence of the “star gods”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;  starGodSequence = reverse [&quot;月&quot;,&quot;水&quot;,&quot;金&quot;,&quot;日&quot;,&quot;火&quot;,&quot;木&quot;,&quot;土&quot;]
  starGodsAllHours = concat ( repeat starGodSequence )
  starGodsDaysFrom s = (head s):starGodsDaysFrom (drop 24 s)
  weekDays = take 7 ( starGodsDaysFrom starGodsAllHours )
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program performs the operations explained above: it takes the list of “star gods” in geocentric order and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;reverse&lt;/code&gt;s them so that “土” (Saturn) is first, this is &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;starGodSequence&lt;/code&gt;. It then &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;repeat&lt;/code&gt;s this list forever (in Haskell you can do this). The &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;concat&lt;/code&gt; flattens this list of lists into a single list, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;starGodsAllHours&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The function &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;starGodsDaysFrom&lt;/code&gt; is recursive, what it does is take the first element in a list, then drops 24 elements (including this first one), and repeats the process, again potentially forever. We apply this function to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;starGodsAllHours&lt;/code&gt;. This produces a new list which repeats the days of the week forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, to get the seven days of the week, we &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;take&lt;/code&gt; the first seven elements of that new list.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The banner photo shows the moon-viewing room  (&lt;em&gt;shōgetsurō&lt;/em&gt;, 嘯月楼) of the Shisen-dō (詩仙堂) temple in Kyoto.&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Reading Murakami in Japanese</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/reading-murakami/"/>
        <updated>2019-05-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/reading-murakami</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/reading-murakami_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/learning-japanese/&quot;&gt;previous posts&lt;/a&gt;, I started reading Murakami’s 1Q84 in Japanese in October 2014, after I had been learning Japanese for about three years. The paperback (&lt;em&gt;bunko&lt;/em&gt;, 文庫) edition consists of 6 volumes, two volumes for each of the three Books that make up 1Q84. Each volume is about 400 pages. In July 2016 I finished the first volume. It is now May 2019 and I have finally finished the four volumes comprising Books 1 and 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, my reading speed was very slow, about half an hour per page, because I constantly had to look up kanji and grammar constructs. In the last three years, my reading speed has fortunately improved quite a bit: it takes me now five minutes to read a page in Japanese. However, to read the equivalent English translation takes only one minute, so I still have some way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As my reading improved, I started to use different ways of reading. 
&lt;!--
I am taking a break from 1Q84 and instead I started reading &quot;Lizard&quot; (Japanese title _tokage_ とかげ), a collection of short stories by Banana Yoshimoto, my other favourite Japanese author. It's very interesting to read a different author because it shows that what I have learned by reading Murakami is mainly how to read Murakami. It is taking me quite a while to get used to Banana Yoshimoto's use of style, vocabulary and grammar. 
--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reading-aloud&quot;&gt;Reading aloud&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Japanese, “reading aloud” is called &lt;em&gt;rōdoku&lt;/em&gt; (ろうどく, 朗読), a word I quite like because &lt;em&gt;rō&lt;/em&gt; means “melodious, clear, bright, serene, cheerful”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe somewhat surprisingly, it turns out that &lt;a href=&quot;https://qz.com/quartzy/1118580/the-beginning-of-silent-reading-was-also-the-beginning-of-an-interior-life/&quot;&gt;silent reading is a relatively young development&lt;/a&gt;: before the 17th century, reading essentially meant reading aloud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find reading aloud very useful because it helps me to understand the flow of the sentence and I also find it easier to understand the meaning. There are many other benefits to reading aloud, as explained in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.voices.com/blog/7_ways_reading_aloud_improves_your_life/&quot;&gt;this article on Voices.com&lt;/a&gt;.
 A small disadvantage is that I can get stuck on any kanji for which I don’t know the pronunciation – I find it hard to continue without looking it up right away in my dictionary. Still, I like to read aloud also because I simply like the sound of Japanese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reading-without-vocalising&quot;&gt;Reading without vocalising&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When reading Japanese silently (&lt;em&gt;mokudoku&lt;/em&gt; もくどく, 黙読), I usually &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Subvocalization&quot;&gt;subvocalise&lt;/a&gt;, i.e. I hear the text in my head. However, I found that &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; doing this has some interesting advantages. I am of course not the first one to make this observation, see e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theindependentbd.com/magazine/details/8098/Significance-of-Silent-Reading&quot;&gt;Significance of Silent Reading&lt;/a&gt;, but these are my observations for the particular case of reading Japanese as a non-native. 
For one, I don’t get stuck on unknown kanji readings, so my flow is not broken so easily. Also, it means that I go straight from word shapes to meanings. For example, I do not need to know that 菜食主義者 is pronounced &lt;em&gt;saishokushugisha&lt;/em&gt; (さいしょくしゅぎしゃ) to know that it means “vegetarian” (菜 &lt;em&gt;sai&lt;/em&gt; is vegetable, 食 &lt;em&gt;shoku&lt;/em&gt; is to eat, 主義 &lt;em&gt;shugi&lt;/em&gt; is doctrine and 者 &lt;em&gt;sha&lt;/em&gt; is person). Even for new words it is often possible to tell the meaning from the kanji – one of the advantages of a writing system based on logograms. 
When not vocalising, it is not necessary to read every individual character. In Japanese the grammar is usually conveyed using groups of hiragana characters and I find that just geting the overall shape is enough to see if a sequence of characters is a negation, or a polite suffix etc. And finally it allows me to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.irisreading.com/speed-reading-tips-5-ways-to-minimize-subvocalization/&quot;&gt;speed-read&lt;/a&gt;: I can simply scan the text for kanji that indicate the “interesting” parts. And I can now add speed reading to my vocabulary as well: &lt;em&gt;sokudoku&lt;/em&gt; (そくどく, 速読).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some articles for your perusal (&lt;em&gt;jukudoku&lt;/em&gt;, じゅくどく, 熟読).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An interesting Japanese article on silent reading and reading aloud: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.office-srr.com/column/silent-reading-vs-reading-aloud/&quot;&gt;黙読と朗読・音読の違い&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;About reading, but otherwise unrelated: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.japantimes.co.jp/life/2018/02/19/language/reading-roman-alphabet-japanese-isnt-easy-abc/&quot;&gt;Reading the Roman alphabet in Japanese isn’t as easy as ABC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A chapter from the book “A History of Reading” by Alberto Mangue, &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.stanford.edu/class/history34q/readings/Manguel/Silent_Readers.html&quot;&gt;The Silent Readers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Orzo with celeriac, mixed mushrooms and tofu sticks</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/orzo-celeriac-mushrooms-tofu-sticks/"/>
        <updated>2019-03-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/orzo-celeriac-mushrooms-tofu-sticks</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/orzo-celeriac-mushrooms-tofu-sticks_1600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;Orzo is durum wheat pasta shaped like grains of barley (called &lt;em&gt;orzo&lt;/em&gt; in Italian). In this recipe it is combined with celeriac and mixed mushrooms (oyster, shiitake, eryngii). The less common ingredient is &lt;a href=&quot;https://shop.waiyeehong.com/food-ingredients/dried-products/dried-beancurd-seaweed/dried-beancurd-sticks-tofu-bamboo-2?language=tw&quot;&gt;dried tofu (bean curd) sticks&lt;/a&gt;. For the seasoning I also used &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/nabe-yellow-peppers-celeriac-shiitake-tofu/index.html&quot;&gt;fermented broad bean paste (tobanjan)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegan&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;vegan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;post-tag&quot; href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#30-minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;30-minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  • &lt;em&gt;725 kcal per person&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#600-800kcals&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/battery_lvl_3.png&quot; style=&quot;height:1.0em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fresh ingredients &amp;amp; groceries
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;400 g celeriac&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;150-200 g mixed mushrooms&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 cm ginger, finely chopped&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 clove garlic&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;70 g dried tofu sticks&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From the store cupboard
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 cup of orzo&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;3 dried tomatoes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/2 teaspoon &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt; paste&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/2 teaspoon &lt;em&gt;tobanjan&lt;/em&gt; (broad bean paste)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon tomato puree&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon mirin&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons sesame seeds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon sunflower seeds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon pine kernels&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/2 teaspoon ground coriander&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1/2 teaspoon soy sauce&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soak the tofu sticks in very hot water for 30 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wash and peel the celeriac and chop it into small pieces (~ 1 cm).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If desired, wash the mushrooms, and chop them into small pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bring 2 l water for the orzo to the boil, with the dried tomatoes, and cook the orzo for 4 minutes over high heat. Switch off the hob and leave it for 8 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take out the dried tomatoes and chop them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meanwhile
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cook the celeriac for 5 minutes in the microwave at full power (900W).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Drain the cooking liquid of the celeriac in a small bowl and mix in the tomato puree, &lt;em&gt;miso&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;tobanjan&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;mirin&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Drain the tofu sticks and cut them into pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Heat the oil in a deep pan. When the oil is hot, add the ginger, garlic, sesame seeds and sunflower seeds and fry for a few minutes over medium heat.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the mushrooms and fry over medium heat until they just start to brown.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the coriander and the soy sauce to the pan.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the celeriac and tofu sticks to the pan and cook until lightly browned.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Turn the heat very low.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add the tomato puree mixture and the dried tomatoes to the pan&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Drain the orzo and add it to the pan.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Season pepper to taste.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Getting started with vegan cooking</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/balanced-vegan-meals/"/>
        <updated>2019-03-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/balanced-vegan-meals</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/balanced-vegan-meals_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;h2 id=&quot;going-vegan&quot;&gt;Going vegan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have recently decided or are considering to become vegan, it’s important to get off to a good start. Going vegan is great but there are some common pitfals if you come from a omnivorous diet. Just cutting out all non-plant-based food might leave you feeling dissatisfied, and craving some of your old food. If your vegan meals are not nutritiously balanced, this will also affect your health. Both are common reasons why people give up on a vegan diet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that making balanced and tasty vegan meals is quite easy. You could of course just make &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/tags/#vegan&quot;&gt;one of my recipes&lt;/a&gt;, but if you want to make your own, here are a few simple guidelines, &lt;a href=&quot;#resources&quot;&gt;supported by expert nutritional advice&lt;/a&gt;. But let’s first have a look at the fundamentals of a healthy diet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fundamentals-of-a-healthy-diet&quot;&gt;Fundamentals of a healthy diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A healthy diet should provide your body with the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Proteins&lt;/em&gt;, for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protein_(nutrient)&quot;&gt;growth and maintenance&lt;/a&gt;. Our bodies do not use the proteins we eat directly, but break them down into amino acids.  There are nine essential amino acids which we must obtain from our diet to prevent &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protein%E2%80%93energy_malnutrition&quot;&gt;protein-energy malnutrition&lt;/a&gt;. Making sure our meals contain sufficient amounts of these is easy, there are several foods such as beans and pulses that are “complete proteins” which provide all essential amino acids.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vitamins and minerals&lt;/em&gt; , &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nhs.uk/conditions/vitamins-and-minerals/&quot;&gt;nutrients our bodies need in small amounts to work properly and stay healthy&lt;/a&gt;. From this angle, there is not much difference between a vegan diet and other diets, with the exception of vitamin B12. As there are no plant-based sources, this needs to be taken as a supplement.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Essential fatty acids&lt;/em&gt; , needed for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/B9780702054013000278&quot;&gt;many physiological processes&lt;/a&gt;, including maintenance of cell membrane structure and skin integrity. There are only two of them, omega-3 and omega-6 fatty acids. Again, they are easy to add to your diet: several types of nuts, seeds and vegetable oils are good sources.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Carbohydrates&lt;/em&gt;, for energy and to aid digestion. Although recently “carbs” got a bad reputation, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bupa.co.uk/health-information/nutrition-diet/carbohydrates&quot;&gt;they are really essential for a healthy diet&lt;/a&gt;. There are three main types of carbohydrates: sugar,  starch, and fibre. For a healthy diet we need all of them, in the right amounts. The main sources are typical starchy foods like rice, pasta and potatoes. The less refined the food, the better as a source of fibre.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not really neccessary to have all components for every meal though, as long as your diet on the whole provides them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;simple-guidelines&quot;&gt;Simple guidelines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That may seem like a lot to take in. So how do you make sure you get all these on a daily basis? I use as a very simple rule that my meals should have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A source of protein. Based on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protein_Digestibility_Corrected_Amino_Acid_Score&quot;&gt;“Protein Digestibility Corrected Amino Acid Score”&lt;/a&gt;, the best sources are tofu, soy beans, chick peas and black beans, but other types of beans or pulses are good too. I use about 100 g per person per meal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A source of starchy carbohydrates, such as rice, pasta and other grain-based foods, or potatoes and similar root vegetables. For rice or pasta I use about 100 g per person per meal, for potatoes about 250g (uncooked weight).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A source of fresh vegetables, whatever you like, but as much variety as possible.  These provide you with vitamins and some of the minerals, as well as some carbohydrates and protein. I use about 200 g per person per meal (uncooked weight).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some nuts or seeds, like pumkin seeds, sunflower seeds or walnuts. These are great sources of omega fatty acids and minerals. Just a handful is enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these guidelines, you can be confident your vegan meals are balanced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes&quot;&gt;Quick &amp;amp; Tasty recipes&lt;/a&gt; follow this pattern. Why not get started with some of my favourites:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Very quick and easy to make: &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/murakami-2/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;soba&lt;/em&gt; noodles with &lt;em&gt;edamame&lt;/em&gt; soy beans.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Very simple: &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/carrots-potatoes-chickpeas/&quot;&gt;a stir-fry  of carrots, potatoes and chickpeas.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A bit more special: &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/recipes/butternut-squash-pear-blackeyed-beans/&quot;&gt;a stir-fry of butternut squash, pear and black-eyed beans with brown rice.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nhs.uk/live-well/eat-well/the-vegan-diet/&quot;&gt;NHS advice on vegan diet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://med.libretexts.org/Bookshelves/Nutrition/Book%3A_An_Introduction_to_Nutrition_(Zimmerman)&quot;&gt;An Introduction to Nutrition (Zimmerman), a free textbook from the LibreTexts library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hsph.harvard.edu/nutritionsource/&quot;&gt;Harvard School of Public Health’s “Nutrition Source”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Why the 'Little People' say 'Ho ho'</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/1Q84-kuukisanagi/"/>
        <updated>2019-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/1Q84-kuukisanagi</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/1Q84-kuukisanagi_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/learning-japanese/&quot;&gt;previous posts&lt;/a&gt;, I have been reading Haruki Murakami’s 1Q84 in Japanese (very slowly). After reading some reviews I wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/repetition-in-1Q84&quot;&gt;a blog post&lt;/a&gt; on why some of the characters frequently repeat one another, something critics didn’t like. Another thing several critics didn’t like is the Little People saying “Ho ho”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s have a look at this “Ho ho”. But first, in case you didn’t read the book, a quick setting of the scene may help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;air-chrysalys&quot;&gt;Air Chrysalys&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1Q84, there is a “book in the book” called “Air Chrysalys” (&lt;em&gt;kuukisanagi&lt;/em&gt;, 空気さなぎ). This book is a kind of fairytale told from the perspective of a ten-year-old girl who lives in a rural commune. As punishment for letting an old mountain goat die, she gets locked up in a shed with the dead goat for a period of ten days&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One night, the “Little People”&lt;sup&gt;**&lt;/sup&gt; appear from the mouth of the dead goat. This scene starts with one of my favourite descriptions in the Japanese text:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;あたりが暗くなると、死んだ山羊の目が星明かりを受けてきらりと光った。&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;atari ga kuraku naru to, shinda yagi no me ga hoshiakari wo ukete kirari to hikatta.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the English translation by Jay Rubin, this reads:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When darkness falls, the dead goat’s eye sparkles in the starlight.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Japanese sentence sparkles a bit more because &lt;em&gt;kirari to&lt;/em&gt; means “with a momentary flash of light” and &lt;em&gt;hikatta&lt;/em&gt; means shine or glitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Murakami puts the reader nicely on the wrong foot, because when six small figures emerge from the goat’s mouth, the little girl thinks “This is like Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs, but there is one missing”. The “Little People” read her thoughts and when she counts again there are seven of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with the girl they start to make an “air chrysalys” by pulling white threads out of thin air and weaving a kind of cocoon from them. While doing so, they talk to the girl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ho-ho-says-the-keeper-of-the-beat&quot;&gt;“Ho ho,” says the keeper of the beat&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Little People don’t have names or personalities and indeed it is impossible to keep them apart or even describe them in detail, but they have distinct voices. Usually, each of them speaks a short sentence in turn.
There is a recurrent pattern where one of them, in translation called the “keeper of the beat”, says “Ho ho”, and the others chorus “Ho ho”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;｢ほうほう｣はやし役のリトル・ピープルがはやした &lt;br /&gt;
｢ほうほう｣残りの六人が声を合わせた &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“houhou” hayashiyaku no RITORU PIIPURU ga hayashita&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;“houhou” nokori no rokunin ga koe wo awaseta&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Japanese text, the “keeper of the beat” is called &lt;em&gt;hayashiyaku&lt;/em&gt; (はやし役) and calls out &lt;em&gt;houhou&lt;/em&gt; (ほうほう). This matters because if this “Ho ho” was merely an interjection or exclamation, it would likely be written &lt;em&gt;hoohoo&lt;/em&gt; (ほぉほぉ or ほおほお). So we can assume that &lt;em&gt;houhou&lt;/em&gt; has a meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Japanese has many homonyms and this is no exception. There are several possible ways to write &lt;em&gt;houhou&lt;/em&gt;, in &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; (Chinese characters), each with a different meaning. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://kotobank.jp/word/%E3%81%BB%E3%81%86%E3%81%BB%E3%81%86-628513#E7.B2.BE.E9.81.B8.E7.89.88.20.E6.97.A5.E6.9C.AC.E5.9B.BD.E8.AA.9E.E5.A4.A7.E8.BE.9E.E5.85.B8&quot;&gt;Kotobank&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;houhou&lt;/em&gt; (ほうほう) means&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;① 物を投げたりたたいたりする音、またはそのさまを表わす語。ぽんぽん。&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The sound of repeatedly throwing or striking something, or a word to representing it”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the kanji writings of &lt;em&gt;houhou&lt;/em&gt; (ほうほう) is 彭々), which makes the meaning more clear because the character 彭 means “the sound of a drum”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because Murakami wrote the word in hiragana, we can’t be entirely sure, but the meanings of the other kanji writings (這々 perplexity, 方法 method) do not make much sense in the given context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-link-with-noh-theatre&quot;&gt;The link with Noh theatre&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the Little People, who Murakami calls the &lt;em&gt;hayashiyaku&lt;/em&gt;, calls out “Ho ho”, and the other six echo this in chorus. The translator of the book, the great Jay Rubin, translates  &lt;em&gt;hayashiyaku&lt;/em&gt; as “keeper of the beat” to reflect the meaning of &lt;em&gt;houhou&lt;/em&gt; as drum beat, and also because Murakami uses the verb &lt;em&gt;hayasu&lt;/em&gt; which literally means “to keep time”. So “says the keeper of the beat” is a very nice way to translate this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the literal meaning in Japanese is “member of a &lt;em&gt;hayashi&lt;/em&gt;”, and &lt;em&gt;hayashi&lt;/em&gt; (囃子) is &lt;a href=&quot;https://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E5%9B%83%E5%AD%90&quot;&gt;the four-piece orchestra&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.glopad.org/jparc/?q=en/node/22767&quot;&gt;traditional Noh theatre&lt;/a&gt;, consisting of three drummers and a flutist. The task of the drummers is to keep the rhythm (&lt;em&gt;hayasu&lt;/em&gt;), but they also &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.the-noh.com/en/world/music.html&quot;&gt;use their voices to create drum calls&lt;/a&gt;. Another component of Noh is the chorus, usually &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noh#Chant_and_music&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;six to eight&lt;/em&gt; people&lt;/a&gt;. And finally there are the actors, who unlike in traditional Western theatre do not ony speak their own lines, but can also &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noh#Chant_and_music&quot;&gt;‘describe events from the perspective of another character or even a disinterested narrator’&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this interpretation, Murakami allocates to his seven Little People the roles of actors, chorus and orchestra in a Noh performance, all at the same time, with an audience of one, the little girl. I think this is what lies behind the Little People saying “Ho ho”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
 &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt; In Japan, traditionally a month is split in three ten-day periods called &lt;em&gt;jun&lt;/em&gt;(旬).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;**&lt;/sup&gt; Murakami calls them リトル・ピープル (RITORU PIIPURU) which is &lt;em&gt;katakana&lt;/em&gt; rendition of the English “Little People”. The little girl thinks of them as &lt;em&gt;kobito&lt;/em&gt; (小人) which also means “little people”. 
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;!--  – shimedaiko (締め太鼓),  otsuzumi (大鼓) and kotsuzumi (小鼓) –-&gt;
&lt;!--
It is often said that Murakami avoids references to traditional Japanese culture, and instead focuses on contemporary Japanese culture. Maybe it is rather the case that his references to traditional Japanese culture are more oblique. 
--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Repetition in Murakami's 1Q84</title>
        <link href="https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/repetition-in-1Q84/"/>
        <updated>2018-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <id>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/repetition-in-1Q84</id>
        <author>
					<name>Wim</name>
					<uri>https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/</uri>
					
				</author>
        <content type="html">
        	&lt;img src=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/images/repetition-in-1Q84_1600x600.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        	&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in &lt;a href=&quot;https://quickandtastycooking.org.uk/articles/learning-japanese/&quot;&gt;previous posts&lt;/a&gt;, I have been reading Murakami’s 1Q84 in Japanese (very slowly). I read the English translation when it was first published but I had never looked up any reviews. The Japanese paperback comes in six volumes and after finishing the third volume&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;, I decided to check some reviews, and I was somewhat surprised to find that most critics didn’t like the book very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the recurrent criticisms is that the characters repeat one another frequently. This is in particular the case for the conversations between Tengo and Fuka-eri.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Murakami mentions that Fuka-eri has dyslexia and based on her behaviour and speech it is likely that she also has autistic spectrum disorder (Murakami describes her speech as monotonous or flat, and she clearly prefers to use single words, although she can speak in full sentences; her facial expression is impossible to read; there are many more hints like this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Japanese, Murakami uses a specific writing style to express Fuka-eri’s way of speaking.
Japanese has three sets of characters: &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;katakana&lt;/em&gt; which are phonetic alphabets, and Chinese characters (&lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt;). In general, &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; are used to indicate the meaning of words, &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt; is used to express the grammar and &lt;em&gt;katakana&lt;/em&gt; is used for foreign words or as a kind of italics. Japanese has few distinct sounds, there are lots of homonyms, and the &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; disambiguate the meanings for the homonyms.
However, &lt;em&gt;katakana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt; can be used to phonetically write &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; but sentences without &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; can be difficult to read, especially because no spaces are used between words. Murakami renders Fuka-eri’s speech using &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;katakana&lt;/em&gt; characters only, without &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt;. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「セキブンのはなしはおもしろかった」&lt;br /&gt;
「予備校の僕の講義のこと？」&lt;br /&gt;
ふかえりは肯いた。&lt;br /&gt;
「君は数学は好き？」&lt;br /&gt;
ふかえりは短く首を振った。数学は好ではない。&lt;br /&gt;
「でも積分の話は面白かったんだ？」と天語は尋ねた。&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the English translation by Jay Rubin, the exchange is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘The calculus part was good.’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘You mean in my lecture?’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Fuka-eri nodded.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘Do you like math?’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;She gave her head a quick shake. She did not like math.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘But the part about calculus was good? he asked.’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though the translator has changed the wording slightly, the last sentence still mostly repeats the first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When written in roman alphabet, the first and the last sentence of the Japanese dialogue are virtually identical:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘sekibun no hanashi wa omoshirokatta’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘demo sekibun no hanashi wa omoshirokatta?’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, although the pronunciation is word for word identical, the effect in the original Japanese text is different because the first sentence, said by Fuka-eri, is written only in &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;katakana&lt;/em&gt; characters, while the last sentence, said by Tengo, uses &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt;. For example, while &lt;em&gt;sekibun&lt;/em&gt; has only one meaning, the &lt;em&gt;seki&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;sekibun&lt;/em&gt; could mean amongst others “stone” or “seat” or “red”; &lt;em&gt;bun&lt;/em&gt; could mean amongst others　”minute”, “sentence” or “mosquito”. Without the &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; it is harder for the reader, and requires more context, to work out the meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, Japanese has the particular grammar feature of &lt;em&gt;particles&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;joshi&lt;/em&gt;, 助詞). These are suffixes or short words that immediately follow a noun, verb, adjective, or sentence and can act as conjunctions, prepostions or modifiers. Some of these particles are attached at the very end of the sentence to add an emotion or tone, or convey that the sentence is a question. Fuka-eri never uses those sentence-ending particles, and in particular the question marking particle. As her speech is uninflected, and the word order in Japanese is the same for statements and questions, it is not always clear if she is asking a question or just stating something. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「わたしをだきたくない」とふかえりは疑問符抜きで尋ねた。&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘watashi wo dakitakunai’ to fukaeri wa gimonfunuki de tazuneta.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which Jay Rubin translates as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘You don’t want to hold me,’ Fuka-eri asked without a question mark.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the lack of question mark or particle, there is no way to know if this is a question or not.
&lt;!-- Murakami has added the '_Fuka-eri asked without a question mark_'.--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A proper Japanese sentence would have been either「私を抱きたくないか」or 「私を抱きたくない？」and indeed, Tengo says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「君を抱く？」&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘Hold you?’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lack of &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; and particles means that Fuka-eri’s sentences in Japanese are often quite ambiguous. So when Tengo repeats Fuka-eri’s sentences, he’s making sure that he understands her correctly, but Murakami also uses this to clarify to the reader what she’s just said. For example,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「イヘンがあろうとしている」&lt;br /&gt;
「イヘン」と天吾は言った。それが「異変」であると思い当たるまでに少し時間がかかった。&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘ihen ga arou toshite iru’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘ihen’ to tengo wa itta. sore ga ‘ihen’ de aru to omoiataru made ni sukoshi jikan ga kakatta.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The meaning of “ihen” (イヘン) is not clear when written in &lt;em&gt;katakana&lt;/em&gt;. In fact, a possible meaning of the sentence could be &lt;em&gt;‘You’ll have a leather cord’&lt;/em&gt;.
The Japanese sentence actually says that it takes a while for Tengo to realise that “ihen”,イヘン means ”something unusual”,異変. In the English translation, this becomes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘That something extra ordinary is starting.’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;It took Tengo a moment to realize this meant “extraordinary”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay Rubin has left out the sentence &lt;em&gt;‘ihen’ to tengo wa itta&lt;/em&gt;. He could have translated it as &lt;em&gt;‘Extra ordinary’ said Tengo&lt;/em&gt;, but that would have made the exchange even more repetitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Japanese version of 1Q84, the exchanges with Fuka-eri are my favourite parts. Her sentences are very easy to read, except for the lack of kanji; then Tengo’s paraphrasing puts in the kanji as well. So as a learner I get both the reading and the meaning. Another example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「わたしはここにのこっている」とふかえりは言った。&lt;br /&gt;
「君はここに残っている」と天語は反復した。&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘watashi wa koko ni nokotte iru’ to fukaeri wa itta.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘kimi wa koko ni nokotte iru’ to tengo wa hanpuku shita.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The translation says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘I’ll stay here,’ Fuka-eri said.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;‘You’ll stay here,’ Tengo echoed her.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, this looks more repetitive than the original.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The English translation of the first two books is by Jay Rubin, who is very renowned for translating Murakami’s works, and I think his translation of 1Q84 is excellent. However, the repetition in the English translation is fundamentally different from the Japanese original because of the writing system. It is impossible to translate the effect of the difference between words writtin in &lt;em&gt;hiragana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;katakana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;kanji&lt;/em&gt; into a language with a single alphabet-based writing system like English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;After four years of reading.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--
The other frequent repetitions are in the conversation between Aomame and the Leader, and to my mind this is the result of an intentional symmetry. 1Q84 is highly structured: the three books each span 3 months, the chapters alternate between Tengo and Aomame (and in the third book, Ushikawa). The connection between the main characters is also very symmetrical. The Leader is Fuka-eri's father[^1] and they are linked in a fundamental way through their connection with the Little People (she's the &quot;perceiver&quot;, he's the &quot;receiver&quot;). Aomame and Tengo are also linked in a very fundamental way, I would say they complement one another. The repetitions in the conversation between the Leader and Aomame therefore echo those between Tengo and Fuka-eri.

[^1]: This would be obvious from the start to the Japanese readers: the Leader's name is Fukada, a common surname. For a pen name, Fuka[da] Eri[ko] is very transparent. The professor calls here Eri, which is a common abbreviation for Eriko, a common name for girls in the 80s.
--&gt;

        </content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>